<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-06T09:38:43+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems Ltd</title><entry><title type="html">Approved Proposal To Delay Eu Mdr</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-04-20-approved-proposal-to-delay-eu-mdr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Approved Proposal To Delay Eu Mdr" /><published>2020-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T09:43:14+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/approved-proposal-to-delay-eu-mdr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-04-20-approved-proposal-to-delay-eu-mdr">&lt;p&gt;A vote in the European Parliament has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medtechdive.com/news/proposed-eu-mdr-delay-clears-parliament-enters-final-stages-coronavirus/576162/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;decisively approved a delay to full implementation of the EU's MDR&lt;/a&gt; by one year, allowing the medical device industry to prioritise its Covid-19 response efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The EU's MDR implementation date was set for 26th May 2020. However in light of this coronavirus pandemic and with an urgent need for medical device manufacturers to help supply much needed equipment to resource-stretched hospitals, a proposal crafted by the European Commission recevied an approval &amp;mdash; 693 votes in favor, 1 against, and 2 abstentions &amp;mdash; to push back the implementation date.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This delay will be welcomed by some companies that were not ready for the switch-over, and it offers more time to take stock, zoom out and re-assess their regulatory strategy. We offered &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2020-04-09-eu-regulators-may-delay-mdr-enforcement&quot;&gt;5 tips to make best use of more time&lt;/a&gt; that might help in such a re-evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A vote in the European Parliament has decisively approved a delay to full implementation of the EU's MDR by one year, allowing the medical device industry to prioritise its Covid-19 response efforts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eu Regulators May Delay Mdr Enforcement</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-04-09-eu-regulators-may-delay-mdr-enforcement" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eu Regulators May Delay Mdr Enforcement" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T09:42:53+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/eu-regulators-may-delay-mdr-enforcement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-04-09-eu-regulators-may-delay-mdr-enforcement">&lt;p&gt;It has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mobihealthnews.com/news/europe/medical-device-manufacturers-face-challenges-preparing-stringent-new-eu-regulation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;extensively documented&lt;/a&gt; that much of the medical device sector was facing challenges in being ready to meet the 26th May 2020 MDR implementation date. Sweeping regulatory changes and a lack of notified body capacity meant that many providers felt ill-prepared even before the emergence of the COVID-19 pandemic. Factor in the disruption caused by the coronavirus outbreak and it should be no surprise that many were calling upon regulators to delay full implementation of the MDR.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medtechdive.com/news/coronavirus-eu-mdr-commission-proposal-1-year-delay/574842/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reports now suggest&lt;/a&gt; that these calls may be answered.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;While this would be welcome news for many, what would a delay mean in practice? To what extent can preparations for EU MDR be put on ice?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Although it is sensible in the short-term to focus on dealing with the exceptional pressures caused by the coronavirus outbreak, we believe that the importance of preparing for MDR enforcement must not be entirely displaced. This possible delay calls for a new wave of focus, using the extra time productively to gain broader advantages from being ready for the MDR.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Up until now, many companies across the industry were trying to do &quot;just enough&quot; to scrape through the 26th May deadline, viewing the MDR as a challenge rather than an opportunity. Our view all along has been that, with the correct approach, the EU MDR presents a unique opportunity for exceptional companies to prove the worth of their products and their wider organisation. Any implementation delay simply magnifies that opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Wisely investing the extra time to re-evaluate and partly re-purpose your existing MDR transition strategy could yield opportunities to make better use of clinical data, build relationships with clinical sites, and find solutions to compliance challenges that can better serve the needs of your wider organisation. With the correct strategy, regulatory departments have the opportunity to spearhead the development of new publications and to safeguard the competitive position of the company against competitors who have taken their eye off the MDR ball.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;So what specifically can be done to make best use of an extra year? Here are 5 tips:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Enhance your understanding of the MDR as an instrument.&lt;/b&gt; At 175 pages, the MDR is a challenging instrument to work with. Very few in the industry would profess to have a thorough understanding of the legislation itself, yet it holds all the answers to ensuring MDR compliance of your products both now and in the future. &lt;!-- Download our white paper or register for one of our webinars to learn everything you need to know about the MDR. --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Perform a Gap Analysis.&lt;/b&gt; Go back to basics and use Annex I MDR to re-evaluate how robustly your existing clinical data portfolio demonstrates conformity with the general safety and performance requirements that are relevant to your products. Engage with our team of specially trained medical doctors to bring an expert medical opinion to your gap analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Re-visit your PMCF plan.&lt;/b&gt; Whatever your existing strategy for generating PMCF data, &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2019-12-18-sources-of-real-world-evidence&quot;&gt;a well-designed medical device product registry&lt;/a&gt; offers a host of advantages in data robustness, minimising bias, ensuring data continuity and building relationships with clinical sites.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Take stock of your technical documentation.&lt;/b&gt; Use the time to conduct an audit of your technical documents and compare your portfolio with the requirements in Annexes II and III of the MDR. &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;Contact us&lt;/a&gt; for help in updating your documents to the required standard.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Write a CER, even if not yet due.&lt;/b&gt; Compiling a CER to the requirements of the MDR rather than the MDD is a fantastic way to uncover any gaps in your clinical evaluation. It's about much more than just the document &amp;mdash; identifying any areas of deficiency now leaves plenty of time to address them before the revised MDR implementation date. Our medical specialists are experts at writing CERs and performing clinical evaluation of medical devices.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The likely delay to full MDR implementation is a great opportunity to take stock, zoom out and re-assess your regulatory strategy. A sensible investment of time now will ensure you are well ahead of the competition when the MDR does come into full force. This is much more than just a box-ticking exercise &amp;mdash; done properly, it helps ensure that your devices can continue to be where they are needed most &amp;mdash; in the hands of your customers, providing better and safer healthcare for patients everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Out of the woods? Not quite, but the regulators might have pruned the trees a little.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It has been extensively documented that much of the medical device sector was facing challenges in being ready to meet the 26th May 2020 MDR implementation date. Sweeping regulatory changes and a lack of notified body capacity meant that many providers felt ill-prepared even before the emergence of the COVID-19 pandemic. Factor in the disruption caused by the coronavirus outbreak and it should be no surprise that many were calling upon regulators to delay full implementation of the MDR.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The New Mdr Compliance Challenge</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-01-23-the-new-mdr-compliance-challenge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The New Mdr Compliance Challenge" /><published>2020-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T09:42:36+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/the-new-mdr-compliance-challenge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2020-01-23-the-new-mdr-compliance-challenge">&lt;p&gt;26th May 2020 marks the end of the transition period from the old Medical Device Directive (MDD) to the new Medical Device Regulations (MDR) 2017/745.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;From this date, the MDR will be in full effect and EU-based medical device manufacturers will be required to provide updated technical documentation to meet the standards of the new legislative framework.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Across the industry, medical device companies are facing challenges in meeting the demands of the new legislative framework. Long-held claims of equivalence are no longer valid and the need to evidence every indication is placing huge demands on evidence-generation systems that are difficult to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Why has the Medical Device Directive (MDD) been replaced?&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Although generally robust and relatively permissive of innovation, the MDD was considered to have numerous flaws in enforcing medical device safety, reliability and general product quality, exposed by notorious incidents such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/metal-metal-hip-implants/concerns-about-metal-metal-hip-implants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the metal-on-metal hip scandal&lt;/a&gt;. Legislators were compelled to implement reform.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The new MDR attempts to reduce the likelihood of future incidents of this nature by tightening the requirements for proving safety and effectiveness of all medical devices, regardless of how long the product has been on the market.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;How will the industry be affected?&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;From an industry perspective, the most important changes are the need to provide evidence &lt;i&gt;&quot;on an ongoing basis&quot;&lt;/i&gt; to support every individual indication, in parallel with the reduced capacity to claim equivalence to devices already approved for sale.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;These changes mean that manufacturers across the industry face &lt;b&gt;a significantly increased evidence-generation burden&lt;/b&gt;, meaning a potentially huge increase in cost to meet the demands for medical device compliance. In some cases, this may even challenge the commercial viability of a product.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mantra Systems is the answer to this dilemma. We are experts at navigating the evidence-generation requirements of MDR and will ensure that you have the systems in place to meet the demands of the new legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;How can Mantra Systems help you?&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Obtaining a medical device CE-Mark under MDR requires robust clinical evidence in the form of Real world evidence (RWE), built from real world data (RWD). Generating RWE is difficult and resource-intensive. Our experienced specialists will work with you to design and  develop your real world evidence generation system to the highest level of legal and regulatory compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Our MEDDEV 2.12-based systems ensure full harmonization of  data collection standards across multiple locations in full adherence to GDPR and all relevant ISO standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">26th May 2020 marks the end of the transition period from the old Medical Device Directive (MDD) to the new Medical Device Regulations (MDR) 2017/745.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sources Of Real World Evidence</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2019-12-18-sources-of-real-world-evidence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sources Of Real World Evidence" /><published>2019-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T09:42:03+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/sources-of-real-world-evidence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/2019-12-18-sources-of-real-world-evidence">&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to generate Real World Evidence (RWE). At Mantra Systems our objective is to make sure that our clients choose the method of real-world data harvesting that is right for them. This article outlines some of the different methods available for collecting real-world data and producing RWE.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The choice of real-world data collection method is often driven by a combination of factors. Some of the factors to consider include:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;market sector&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;availability of external data sources&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;product type&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;available company resources &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;time and criticality&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the method chosen by medical device manufacturers often isn't the best one for their needs. A poor choice of RWE generation method tends to lead to an accumulation of problems over time, as weaknesses of either collection method or the data itself tend to compound as data collection is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Manufacturers may also find that compliance of data collection by investigators is far below requirements if insufficient attention is given to the choice of data collection method. Ultimately, the wrong choice leads to both time and money being wasted and leaves a critical problem remaining to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Differing market sectors&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Some market sectors are extremely fortunate in this regard as there are already a number of external or nationalised registries that collect data on the performance of multiple products within a sector. For example, the National Joint Registry in the UK collects real-world data on the performance of joint replacement implants. This is a rich source of data that companies can access to compile evidence for regulatory submission, and has the advantage of being consecutive, non-selective, and objective (ie administered by an external agent rather than the manufacturer of the product in question).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Other market sectors are not so fortunate. In the absence of such nationalised registries, manufacturers must find other ways to generate RWE.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For some products, a simple patient survey may suffice, perhaps collecting outcome measures such as EQ-5D-5L or pain VAS in return for a modest reward. This will suffice for lower risk devices where the level of scrutiny of RWE is comparatively light. The priority is to collect incidences of Adverse Events and, ideally, some limited functional outcomes data.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Common problems&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For products in higher risk categories (Class IIb and III under the &lt;abbr title=&quot;Medical Device Regulation&quot;&gt;MDR&lt;/abbr&gt;), a more robust system of real-world data collection will be required.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In some cases it may be possible to buy data from a commercial external database administered by a data provider. This has the advantage of avoiding the need to build a new data collection system &lt;i&gt;&quot;from scratch&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, however there are numerous disadvantages to this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Firstly, the manufacturer will have no control over which data points are collected, meaning that they have no ability to tailor the data collected to the needs of either themselves or their customers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Secondly, the manufacturer has no control over HOW the data was collected - in the era of GDPR and other important data control measures, the manufacturer will need to provide justification for the data collection methods employed in generating their RWE.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the data remains owned by the data provider, meaning there is no opportunity to make multiple uses of the same data at different times without paying repeatedly to extend licenses.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, such data is almost always retrospective. Regulators increasingly require prospective data to support regulatory submissions, and the inherent inflexibility of retrospective datasets may often mean that manufacturers need to seek alternative or ancillary data to maintain regulatory approval over time.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;A solution&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For these reasons and many others, a dedicated bespoke observational product registry offers numerous advantages. One particular advantage of a dedicated product registry is the ability to record data in real-time. In an increasingly digital world, this is a huge advantage of such a data collection system. Dedicated product registries are also prospective.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Our dedicated registry building service will ensure that you have the most robust, adaptable, personalised and appropriate Real World Evidence generation system for your individual requirements. Our team of experts will work with you to build the an observational device registry that will meet your RWE-generation needs both now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We also have the necessary experience to create a registry that offers value to your customers, allowing you and your customers to become strategic partners in both medical device scrutiny and data generation, the uses of which will stretch far beyond mere regulatory compliance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There are multiple ways to generate Real World Evidence (RWE). At Mantra Systems our objective is to make sure that our clients choose the method of real-world data harvesting that is right for them. This article outlines some of the different methods available for collecting real-world data and producing RWE.</summary></entry></feed>