<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-30T23:44:30+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 - Its impact on EU MDR and IVDR</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 - Its impact on EU MDR and IVDR" /><published>2024-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-19T16:02:26+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr"><![CDATA[<p>The European Parliament and the Council of the European Union recently amended the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR) and the EU <i>in vitro</i> Diagnostic Medical Device Regulation (IVDR) with <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=OJ:L_202401860&amp;qid=1720500341754" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Regulation (EU) 2024/1860</a>.</p>
      <p>In this article, we explain how in two key areas these amendments reinforce important elements of the previously published regulatory framework, helping maintain the high quality and safety standards of medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices.</p>
      <h2 id="1-gradual-roll-out-of-the-european-database-on-medical-devices-eudamed">1. Gradual roll-out of the European database on medical devices (EUDAMED)</h2>
      <p>This update requires that the Commission set up, maintain, and manage <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">EUDAMED</a>, a framework comprising seven interconnected electronic systems. EUDAMED aims to provide better transparency and traceability of medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices among EU member states. Four systems are complete to date, and two more are expected to be finished in 2024. The European Commission recently updated the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/04ce2012-97df-4dd0-8a39-d4f6993b9e16_en?filename=md_eudamed_roadmap_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EUDAMED roadmap</a>, outlining key roll-out dates.</p>
      <p>However, the complexity of clinical investigations and performance studies poses a significant challenge, leading to delays in implementing EUDAMED across member states. As a result, EUDAMED will gradually roll out as individual electronic systems, with each system being implemented after thorough verification by the Commission.</p>
      <h2 id="2-ensuring-a-smooth-transition-to-the-ivdr">2. Ensuring a smooth transition to the IVDR</h2>
      <p>The transition from the EU Medical Devices Directive (IVDD) to the IVDR poses a challenge for <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers</a>, as shown by comparing conformity assessment applications and certificates issued by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Bodies</a>. With the transitional period ending on 26 May 2025, there is a high risk of shortages of critical <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices, especially high-risk (Class D) devices.</p>
      <p>Thus, the transitional period has been extended to prevent device shortages, protect patient health, and mitigate market disruption. This extension aims to provide manufacturers and notified bodies with the time necessary to complete the necessary conformity assessments. 
        As part of this, manufacturers must inform the relevant authorities of any perceived disruptions or discontinuation of medical devices that could harm patients or public health.</p>
      <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>
      <p>These changes collectively aim to strengthen the regulatory framework for medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices, improve safety and transparency, prioritise public health and foster medical device innovation.</p>
      <p><b>At Mantra Systems, we are medical device regulatory experts with a track record of successful regulatory submissions.</b> Please contact <a href="mailto:shona&#64;mantrasystems.com">shona@mantrasystems.com</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to to find out how we can help you overcome regulatory challenges and gain approval for your device.</p>
      ]]></content><author><name>shona-richardson</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How does the recent Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 amendment affect the EU MDR &amp; IVDR?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDCG 2024-10 - Orphan medical devices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDCG 2024-10 - Orphan medical devices" /><published>2024-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-09T16:14:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices"><![CDATA[<p>With the introduction of the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR), there has been an increased emphasis on clinical evidence requirements. Manufacturers of medical devices indicated for rare diseases found these new obligations burdensome, potentially impacting patient access to these devices.</p>
    <p>Released in June 2024, the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/daa1fc59-9d2c-4e82-878e-d6fdf12ecd1a_en?filename=mdcg_2024-10_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2024-10 guidance</a> introduces and defines new terms to the MDR regulatory landscape and aims to address these challenges faced by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers of medical devices</a> indicated for use in rare diseases.</p>
    <p>In this article, we explore the impact of MDCG 2024-10 on clinical evidence requirements, shedding light on its key considerations and implications.</p>
    <h2 id="orphan-device-classification">Orphan device classification</h2>
    <p>An “orphan device” is defined as a medical device specifically intended to benefit patients in the treatment, diagnosis, or prevention of a disease or condition that affects no more than 12,000 individuals in the European Union per year. To qualify as an orphan device, at least one of the following criteria must be met:</p>
    <ol>
      <li><strong>Insufficiency of alternatives</strong>: There are no adequate alternative treatment, diagnostic, or preventive options available for the specific disease or condition.</li>
      <li><strong>Clinical benefit</strong>: The device offers an expected clinical benefit compared to existing alternatives or the current state of the art. This assessment considers both device-specific factors and the patient population.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Manufacturers seeking orphan device classification must provide a justification based on epidemiological data to the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Body</a>. Additionally, this information should be summarised in the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-report-cer">Clinical Evaluation Report</a>.</p>
    <h2 id="orphan-subpopulation-and-orphan-indication">Orphan subpopulation and orphan indication</h2>
    <p>In addition to the classification of orphan devices, the MDCG 2024-10 provides guidance for devices that serve specific patient sub-populations or have multiple indications.</p>
    <h3 id="orphan-subpopulation">Orphan subpopulation</h3>
    <p>This guidance applies to devices intended for use in the treatment, diagnosis, or prevention of a disease or condition within a clinically valid patient sub-population. Specifically, the sub-population should not exceed 12,000 individuals in the European Union per year (within a disease or condition with an annual incidence of more than 12,000 in the EU).</p>
    <h3 id="orphan-indication">Orphan indication</h3>
    <p>Sometimes, a medical device may have a specific intended purpose or indication for an orphan population (or orphan subpopulation) in addition to another intended purpose or indication in larger patient populations. In such cases, the MDCG 2024-10 outlines clinical evidence requirements specifically for the component of the intended purpose related to the orphan population.</p>
    <h2 id="clinical-vs-non-clinical-data-for-orphan-devices">Clinical vs. non-clinical data for orphan devices</h2>
    <p>When evaluating an orphan device, both clinical and non-clinical data play crucial roles.</p>
    <h3 id="clinical-data-considerations">Clinical data considerations</h3>
    <ol>
      <li><strong>Substantial evidence</strong>: If non-clinical data provide substantial high-quality evidence supporting the safety and performance of the orphan device, it can reduce the burden of pre-market clinical data requirements. This evidence can help justify CE marking, even when there are limitations in clinical data that can be addressed through <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf">Post-Market Clinical Follow-up (PMCF) activities</a>.</li>
      <li><strong>Acceptable limitations</strong>: Limitations in pre-market clinical data are acceptable under certain conditions:
        <ul>
          <li><strong>Expected clinical benefit</strong>: There must be sufficient clinical evidence demonstrating the expected clinical benefit, and the device must perform as intended with an acceptable level of safety.</li>
          <li><strong>Compliance with GSPRs</strong>: The device must meet all relevant General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</li>
          <li><strong><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf-plan">PMCF plan</a></strong>: A well-defined PMCF plan should generate additional clinical data within an appropriate time-frame, fully addressing any remaining limitations.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ol>
    <h3 id="clinical-data-sources">Clinical data sources</h3>
    <p>Sources of clinical data must relate to either the subject or equivalent devices, and include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Clinical investigations</strong>: Studies involving human subjects and undertaken to assess the safety or performance of a device.</li>
      <li><strong>Peer-reviewed scientific literature</strong>: Relevant research published in reputable journals.</li>
      <li><strong>PMCF</strong>: Data collected during post-market follow-up.</li>
    </ul>
    <h3 id="useful-non-clinical-data">Useful non-clinical data</h3>
    <p>Non-clinical data can complement clinical evidence. Useful sources include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Laboratory and animal tests</strong>: Results from in vitro and animal studies.</li>
      <li><strong>Computer modelling and simulated testing</strong>: Data from software-based models, 3D printed models, and other physical simulations.</li>
      <li><strong>Ex vivo and cadaveric studies</strong>: Insights gained from studies using tissue samples or cadavers.</li>
      <li><strong>Similar devices</strong>: Data from devices similar to the orphan device (when equivalence is not demonstrated).</li>
      <li><strong>State of the Art information</strong>: Understanding the technology landscape.</li>
      <li><strong>Health datasets</strong>: Previously collected patient health information, often used for software validation without exposing patients.</li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
    <p>MDCG 2024-10 offers guidance on the classification and clinical evidence requirements for orphan devices. Importantly, manufacturers of orphan devices may use non-clinical data, in combination with a rigorous <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf-plan">PMCF plan</a>, to supplement clinical evidence to address pre-market clinical data limitations.</p>
    <p>Please email <a href="mailto:simon&#64;mantrasystems.com">simon@mantrasystems.com</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to understand <strong>how Mantra Systems can help you meet your MDR requirements</strong>.</p>
    <p>Alternatively, for any general regulatory questions you need a quick answer to, have you tried our <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</a>? — it’s free and will answer your queries around the clock.</p>
    ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to apply MDR pre-market clinical evidence requirements to medical devices intended for limited usage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A medical device’s intended purpose - what is the point?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A medical device’s intended purpose - what is the point?" /><published>2024-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-14T12:56:38+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point"><![CDATA[<p>A clear idea of your medical device’s intended purpose is crucial in meeting the EU MDR regulatory requirements. Getting it right early in the development process is important, as it provides inputs to:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Objectives of the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>,</li>
    <li>Defining the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">SOTA</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="/articles/keeping-medical-devices-in-market-maintaining-ce-marks">Design of clinical investigations</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="/articles/five-tips-for-making-a-medical-device-equivalence-claim-under-the-mdr">Equivalence claims</a>,</li>
    <li>Evidence for conformity to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxyKV003WaY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relevant GSPRs</a>.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>A clinical evaluation should, according to its definition in Article 2(44) of the EU MDR, <q>“verify the safety and performance, including clinical benefits, of the device when used as intended by the manufacturer.”</q></p>
  <p>But what is the intended purpose, and how does it interact with indications for use, claims, and intended clinical benefits? <b>For each term, we will consider a fictional hip implant device.</b></p>
  <h2 id="intended-purpose">Intended purpose</h2>
  <p>‘Intended purpose’ should describe <b>what the device is used for and the effect of the device</b>. Article 2(12) of the EU MDR defines ‘intended purpose’ as <q>“the use for which a device is intended according to the data supplied by the manufacturer on the label, in the instructions for use or in promotional or sales materials or statements and as specified by the manufacturer in the clinical evaluation.”</q></p>
  <p>All medical devices will have an intended purpose. In the case of a hip implant, the intended purpose could be for the replacement of native hip joints in adult patients with moderate to severe hip osteoarthritis.</p>
  <h2 id="indication-for-use">Indication for use</h2>
  <p>‘Indication for use’ should describe <b>the clinical condition that the device targets</b>. MDCG 2020-6 defines the indication for use as <q>“the clinical condition that is to be diagnosed, prevented, monitored, treated, alleviated, compensated for, replaced, modified or controlled by the medical device.”</q></p>
  <p>Some devices, therefore, may not have an indication for use. An example would be a medical device intended to sterilise equipment. In the case of a hip implant, the indication for use could be hip osteoarthritis with an Oxford Hip Score less than 29.</p>
  <h2 id="clinical-benefit">Clinical benefit</h2>
  <p>‘Clinical benefit’ should describe <b>the benefit to the patient from using the device in a quantifiable manner</b>. Article 2(53) of the EU MDR defines clinical benefit as <q>“the positive impact of a device on the health of an individual, expressed in terms of a meaningful, measurable, patient-relevant clinical outcome(s), including outcome(s) related to diagnosis, or a positive impact on patient management or public health.”</q></p>
  <p>All devices will have a clinical benefit, but these can be either direct or indirect. In the case of a hip implant, the intended clinical benefit could be the reduction in pain VAS score by 25%. An example of a medical device with an indirect clinical benefit would be the scalpel used during the operation; a scalpel will not reduce pain in patients with osteoarthritis, but will facilitate insertion of the hip replacement and therefore lead to an improvement in pain VAS score.</p>
  <h2 id="claims">Claims</h2>
  <p>‘Claims’ are not defined in the EU MDR, but Article 7 prohibits any information supplied by the manufacturer that may mislead the user with regard to the intended purpose, safety, or performance. Claims, therefore, can be <b>derived from any manufacturer documents</b> and should be supported by clinical evidence in the clinical evaluation.</p>
  <p>Claims will encompass all of the intended use, indications for use, clinical benefits, as well as other terms not discussed in this article such as intended user, use environment, etc.</p>
  <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
  <p>To briefly summarise each of the points above:</p>
  <table class="simple">
    <tr>
      <th>Intended purpose</th>
      <td>Is the use and effect of the device.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Indications for use</th>
      <td>Is the clinical condition that the device targets.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Clinical benefit</th>
      <td>Is the measurable impact on the patient.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Claims</th>
      <td>Derived from the above, plus any other claims made in marketing materials, IFU, etc.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  <p>For further information on how we can help you meet your MDR requirements please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free and confidential discussion.</p>
  <p>Alternatively, for any general regulatory questions you need a quick answer to, have you tried our <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</a>? — it’s free and will answer your queries around the clock.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><category term="PMCF" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How do you define intended purpose, indication for use, intended clinical benefits, and claims?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR and MDCG chatbot</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR and MDCG chatbot" /><published>2024-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T16:04:02+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot"><![CDATA[<p>A deep understanding of the MDR and associated MDCG documents is crucial for achieving compliance with the EU Medical Device Regulations.</p>
  <p>However, the MDR itself is 175 pages long and the MDCG documents, at the time of writing, number over 100 files. With so much information available it can sometimes be difficult to find the relevant information.</p>
  <p>To solve this problem we have developed EnableChat, <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">your AI-powered regulatory chatbot</a>.</p>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="Mej0nkKHP7M"></div>
    <p class="video-caption">About EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</p>
  </div>
  <h2 id="the-solution">The Solution</h2>
  <p>EnableChat is, in simple terms, a question and answer service. Ask any question related to MDR compliance and, like magic, EnableChat will search the MDR and MDCG documents and find the answer you are looking for. It will even list the most relevant documents and provide a link, connecting you directly with them.</p>
  <p>More specifically, EnableChat is a retrieval-augmented generative question and answering web application that finds the most relevant MDCG documents or MDR pages, before using a large language model to answer the user’s question based on the relevant documents. This method ensures high accuracy while maintaining a friendly, conversational style.</p>
  <p>EnableChat is free to use (no sign-up required) and searches all the latest MDCG documents as well as the MDR text.</p>
  <p class="align-center"><a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat" class="button">Try EnableChat</a></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Search the MDR and MDCG documents in seconds by asking EnableChat your questions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying vigilant - A guide to searching for adverse events data</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying vigilant - A guide to searching for adverse events data" /><published>2024-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-14T12:28:14+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data"><![CDATA[<p>Searching for and analysing adverse events data relating to subject and similar devices is essential in any medical device MDR submission. Although intended to be a future major component of adverse events reporting, the EUDAMED database is not yet fully functional and does not currently allow for the searching of <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/vigilance">vigilance data</a>.</p>
  <p>In this article, we outline what other adverse event databases are available, along with the pros and cons of each.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-adverse-events-data-used-for">What is adverse events data used for?</h2>
  <p>Data gathered by the manufacturer’s <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">Post-Market Surveillance (PMS)</a> system, including adverse events, is used for the following purposes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>To detect and report types and frequencies of adverse events</li>
    <li>To identify any new risks not currently considered in <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk Management</a> files</li>
    <li>To determine trends of adverse events over time</li>
    <li>To understand side-effects and their potential impact on the benefit-risk analysis.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>PMS activities should include an analysis of adverse events relating to both the subject device and similar devices, as those relating to similar devices are likely to apply to the subject device.</p>
  <h2 id="sources-of-adverse-events-data">Sources of adverse events data</h2>
  <p>The monitoring of post-market surveillance data will be possible through the EUDAMED Vigilance module, which is under development and will be released when EUDAMED is declared fully functional. Use of this module will become mandatory from Q4 2027.</p>
  <p>Until then, adverse event report searches will rely on country-specific vigilance databases. Even following the deployment of the EUDAMED Vigilance module, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers</a> will still need to monitor other vigilance databases “in a manner that is proportionate to the risk class and appropriate for the type of device”. (EU MDR Chapter VII, Section 1, Article 83).</p>
  <p>The following databases are all commonly used by medical device manufacturers for Post-Market Surveillance activities:</p>
  <h3 id="us-maude"><a href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfmaude/search.cfm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US MAUDE</a></h3>
  <p>The largest database of vigilance data and an excellent resource to utilise. MAUDE offers the ability to search for adverse event reports received from healthcare professionals, patients, and manufacturers, as well as Field Safety Notices. It’s an extremely comprehensive database that can result in thousands of results, meaning that reviewers need a plan and some dedicated time to review and analyse. The site also contains a disclaimer that, because of the risk of duplicate entries, MAUDE shouldn’t be used to assess frequency of events.</p>
  <h3 id="uk-mhra"><a href="https://www.gov.uk/drug-device-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UK MHRA</a></h3>
  <p>The MHRA allows searches for Field Safety Notices, National Patient Safety Alerts, and device safety information. Search functionality is limited, however, and the format that results are presented in can take up a lot of time. Outputs are as PDF files only, further limiting functionality.</p>
  <h3 id="swissmedic"><a href="https://fsca.swissmedic.ch/mep/#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Swissmedic</a></h3>
  <p>Swissmedic provides an easy to use website with the ability to search for Field Safety Notices only. With excellent search functionality and easy to review results this is a great resource to utilise. Outputs are as PDF files only.</p>
  <h3 id="australian-daen"><a href="https://www.tga.gov.au/safety/safety/safety-monitoring-daen-database-adverse-event-notifications/database-adverse-event-notifications-daen-medicines" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Australian DAEN</a></h3>
  <p>The DAEN database allows searching of adverse event reports. The search function, however, can sometimes be difficult to use. Results can be output into an easy to read PDF document.</p>
  <h3 id="french-ansm"><a href="https://ansm.sante.fr/informations-de-securite/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">French ANSM</a></h3>
  <p>The ANSM website is in French, so an online translator may be helpful here. With a simple to use search function showing Field Safety Notices and device alert information, the French database can provide useful outputs.</p>
  <h3 id="german-bfarm"><a href="https://www.bfarm.de/EN/Medical-devices/Tasks/Risk-assessment-and-research/Field-corrective-actions/_node.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">German BfArM</a></h3>
  <p>The BfArM website is user friendly and responsive, showing predominantly Field Safety Notices. A great resource to utilise for your vigilance searches.</p>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>Adverse event data is a vital component of a clinical evaluation and post market surveillance. With such a wide range of sources available to collect this information from, appropriate planning and time should be allocated to this task.</p>
  <p>Need further information on vigilance database searches? Interested to hear more about Mantra Systems’ <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation Report Writing service</a>, which includes a vigilance database search as standard? <a href="/contact">Contact us</a> for a free, impartial and no obligation discussion with a member of our team.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We discuss the pros and cons of existing adverse event databases for vigilance data searching.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?" /><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T10:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp"><![CDATA[<p>In this article, we provide a brief overview of the Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP) process, a regulatory requirement applicable for high-risk implantable and class III devices under the EU MDR.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?</h2>
  <p>The <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)</a> is an entirely new document requirement introduced by the MDR. According to article 32 of the MDR regulation (MDR (EU) 2017/745), manufacturers are required to produce an SSCP for high risk implantable and class III medical devices (except custom-made or investigational devices).</p>
  <p>An SSCP is unique in its structure and format. It is written specifically for medical device end users, including both healthcare professionals and, if applicable, patients. If the SSCP contains information for both healthcare professionals and patients, the document should include distinct and easily identifiable sections for each audience.</p>
  <p>All SSCPs are required to be submitted to a recognised notified body for validation. Unlike other technical documents, the SSCP will be published for public access in the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">EUDAMED</a> database by the notified body after validation.</p>
  <h2 id="when-do-you-need-an-sscp-and-what-are-its-objectives">When do you need an SSCP and what are its objectives?</h2>
  <p>If you are a manufacturer of high-risk implantable devices, such as an arterial stent or vitreous implant, or class III devices such as breast implants or total or partial joint replacements, and wish to comply with the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:02017R0745-20170505" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDR (EU) 2017/745</a>, you must produce an SSCP for your devices.</p>
  <p>The main objective of the SSCP is to provide clinical data and other information concerning the safety and clinical effectiveness of the medical device and to make it accessible to the general public in an appropriate form. This will allow healthcare professionals to make more informed decisions about patient treatment, and enable the patients to look into the devices recommended by their healthcare providers.</p>
  <p>The SSCP must summarise both favourable and unfavourable data regarding the safety and clinical effectiveness of the device; that is, it is meant not only to demonstrate that the device is safe and effective, but also to highlight residual risks and potential safety or performance concerns and how these have been mitigated.</p>
  <p>However, the SSCP is not intended to be used in place of the IFU or implant cards associated with the medical device. It is also not meant to provide comprehensive advice on the diagnosis and treatment of specific medical conditions. The public access of SSCP via EUDAMED will also enable users to form a direct comparison of the subject device and similar alternative devices based on available clinical evidence.</p>
  <h2 id="what-support-is-available-when-writing-an-sscp">What support is available when writing an SSCP?</h2>
  <p>Being a publicly available document and an entirely new requirement under the MDR, the SSCP may present challenges to the manufacturers. It is important to become familiar with official guidance such as that published in <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2022-03/md_mdcg_2019_9_sscp_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG-2019-9 Rev 1</a>.</p>
  <p>However, as a new document type, it is also advisable to consider seeking professional advice and consulting support. <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">Mantra Systems offers a complete SSCP service</a> (including writing and readability testing), alongside a range of training resources and templates through the <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE platform</a>.</p>
  <p><b>If you have any questions about SSCPs and our range of support services, <a href="/contact">contact our team</a> for a free, no obligation discussion.</b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="SSCP" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We explain what the SSCP is, when you'll need it and what its objectives are.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Validity Reports – Foundation of the IVDR Performance Evaluation</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports-foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Validity Reports – Foundation of the IVDR Performance Evaluation" /><published>2023-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T13:13:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports%E2%80%93foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports-foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation"><![CDATA[<p>A Performance Evaluation Report (PER) is a cornerstone of any submission under the IVDR. In this series of articles, we break down the three major components of a PER and outline their purpose and requirements, starting with the Scientific Validity Report.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-scientific-validity">What is scientific validity?</h2>
  <p>Scientific validity is defined as the <q>“association of an analyte with a clinical condition or a physiological state”</q>. It is a component of clinical evidence collection which is required for the performance evaluation of an <i>in vitro</i> medical device under the IVDR.</p>
  <p>The evidence to prove scientific validity is presented in the Scientific Validity Report (SVR), a supporting document for the PER.</p>
  <p><b>‘Performance evaluation’</b> of an <i>in vitro</i> medical device is an assessment and analysis of data to establish or verify the scientific validity, analytical and, where applicable, the clinical performance of a device (Source: <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746&amp;qid=1698152662286" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EU IVDR 2017/746. Section 1, Article 2 (44)</a>).</p>
  <p>Establishing the scientific validity of an analyte is the first and most important step when generating the argument as to why an IVD is considered to be state of the art and suitable to fulfil its intended purpose.</p>
  <h2 id="what-type-of-evidence-is-required-to-establish-scientific-validity">What type of evidence is required to establish scientific validity?</h2>
  <p>In order to demonstrate scientific validity, <a href="https://www.imdrf.org/sites/default/files/docs/ghtf/final/sg5/technical-docs/ghtf-sg5-n7-2012-scientific-validity-determination-evaluation-121102.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">guidance has been provided</a> on the potential sources of source(s) of information to be used:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Information on IVD medical devices that measure the same analyte and with the same intended use that have marketing history (e.g. Instructions for Use).</li>
    <li>Systematic literature review: peer reviewed articles, regulatory guidance documents, conference proceedings, etc.</li>
    <li>Review of expert opinions: textbooks, clinical guidance documents, position statements from academic and professional organisations.</li>
    <li>Results from proof of concept studies: smaller scale scientific studies to identify the fundamental association of the analyte with the clinical condition/physiological state.</li>
    <li>Results from clinical performance studies.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="what-should-be-included-in-the-systematic-literature-review">What should be included in the systematic literature review?</h2>
  <p>A state-of-the-art literature review, according to MedDev 2.7/1 Rev 4, describes what is currently and generally considered to be standard of care or best practice for the medical condition or treatment for which the device is used. The systematic literature review will be used to find data to evidence the state of the art, in accordance with the intended purpose of the IVD under evaluation.</p>
  <p>This literature search should include information on the medical conditions associated with the test, the alternative diagnostic options available, the target populations for the test as per the intended purpose, any risks associated with the technology used and specific details about the analyte and the test.</p>
  <p>A systematic literature search for competitor devices is also necessary in order to determine performance outcomes which can be used to determine acceptance criteria, against which the subject device will be compared.</p>
  <p>The evidence for scientific validity has to be appraised for its relevance and quality, with references, justifications and conclusions and presented in a Scientific Validity Report (SVR).</p>
  <h2 id="what-if-my-analyte-or-assay-has-a-well-established-connection-to-a-clinical-condition">What if my analyte or assay has a well-established connection to a clinical condition?</h2>
  <p>The definition of performance evaluation given above mentions the requirement to <i>‘establish <b>or verify</b>’</i> the scientific validity. This means that if the analyte has a well-established and recognised association with a clinical condition (e.g. the association of haemoglobin levels with anaemia), there will be no need to provide as much evidence as perhaps a new analyte, or a new intended purpose.</p>
  <p><a href="https://www.bsigroup.com/globalassets/localfiles/en-th/Medical%20devices/whitepapers/performance-evaluation-under-ivdr-th.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to guidance from the notified body BSI</a>, for well-established assays, a description of clinical guidelines or published evidence will be enough. However, with a newly developed analyte which perhaps has limited published evidence, there may be a need for the manufacturer to provide their own evidence, such as proof-of-concept studies or clinical performance studies.</p>
  <h2 id="do-all-ivds-require-scientific-validity-to-support-clinical-evidence">Do all IVDs require scientific validity to support clinical evidence?</h2>
  <p>If the device under evaluation is Class A or a calibrator, it may not require the demonstration of scientific validity. If the device does not perform the test itself, it will be necessary to explain and justify, in the Performance Evaluation Plan (PEP), why scientific validity is not applicable for this specific device. It will, however, be necessary to explain that the scientific validity of the associated assay is valid. Therefore, an SVR is needed to describe the association of the analyte for the assay(s) it is supporting.</p>
  <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
  <p>Scientific Validity is a crucial component of the clinical evidence required under the IVDR. It provides the clinical background and context for the environment in which the IVD operates and is necessary to determine performance criteria against which to compare the IVD under evaluation. A methodical, detailed and documented approach to the state-of-the-art literature review will result in a well-evidenced and robust claim of scientific validity.</p>
  <p><b>Need further information on producing a Scientific Validity Report? <a href="/contact">Contact Mantra Systems</a> for a free, impartial and no obligation discussion with a member of our team. </b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Justifying scientific validity is the first step in proving compliance with the IVDR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2023</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2023" /><published>2023-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023"><![CDATA[<p>Mantra Systems is looking forward to attending <a href="https://www.medica-tradefair.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MEDICA 2023</a> - a prestigious international medical trade fair held on 13th - 16th November in Düsseldorf, Germany.</p>
  <p>With over 5,500 exhibitors from 66 countries and more than 81,000 visitors worldwide, MEDICA stands as one of the largest medical B2B trade fairs in the world. The event presents the entire spectrum of innovations from various companies and organisations for outpatient and clinical care.</p>
  <p>As the global medical device landscape continues to evolve, staying at the forefront of medical device innovation is paramount for companies committed to advancing healthcare solutions.</p>
  <p>The event will showcase innovation in the 5 spheres of MEDICA; these are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Medical Technology and Devices</li>
    <li>Digital Health</li>
    <li>Lab &amp; Diagnostics</li>
    <li>Physio Tech</li>
    <li>Disposables &amp; Consumables</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Alongside MEDICA, <a href="https://www.compamed-tradefair.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COMPAMED</a>, an international trade fair for the medical technology supplier sector will also be happening in Düsseldorf.</p>
  <p>COMPAMED offers a comprehensive range of high-quality medical technology components, services and production equipment for the medical industry. There will be over 800 exhibitors presenting the latest innovations in components, modules, OEM equipment, electrical and electronic components, microtechnology, raw materials, materials and adhesives, manufacturing of components, manufacturing of finished products, services and manufacturing equipment.</p>
  <h2 id="the-significance-of-medica-a-global-hub-for-medical-innovation">The significance of MEDICA: A global hub for medical innovation</h2>
  <p>MEDICA serves as a melting pot of innovation, bringing together leading minds, cutting-edge technologies, and groundbreaking solutions in the medical field. This year’s event promises to showcase a diverse array of products and services spanning medical imaging, laboratory technology, diagnostics, health IT, mobile health, physiotherapy/orthopaedic technology, and medical consumables. With a staggering number of exhibitors and visitors, the trade fair provides an unparalleled platform to explore the latest trends and developments shaping the future of healthcare.</p>
  <p>Each year, distinguished figures from the realms of business, research, and politics grace the prestigious event with their attendance, alongside tens of thousands of industry experts and decision-makers from both national and international spheres, making MEDICA an excellent opportunity to exchange with experts from all over the world.</p>
  <h2 id="why-medical-innovation-matters-a-glimpse-into-the-future">Why medical innovation matters: A glimpse into the future</h2>
  <p>In the dynamic realm of healthcare, innovation plays a pivotal role in improving patient outcomes, enhancing diagnostics, and revolutionizing treatment modalities. As medical technology continues to advance, it opens new frontiers for personalized and more effective healthcare solutions. From state-of-the-art imaging technologies to cutting-edge health IT systems, the innovations showcased at MEDICA 2023 will underscore the transformative power of technology in the medical sector.</p>
  <h2 id="our-presence-at-medica-2023">Our presence at MEDICA 2023</h2>
  <p>For those attending MEDICA 2023, we invite you to connect with our representatives during the event. As a specialised medical device regulatory consultancy, we are eager to share insights, discuss regulatory challenges, and explore collaborative opportunities.</p>
  <p>Whether you are navigating the complexities of market entry, compliance, or Post-Market Surveillance, our team is here to assist in ensuring your medical devices meet the highest regulatory standards. Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> to arrange a free consultation.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shen-may-khoo</name></author><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mantra Systems is going to MEDICA 2023, the largest medical trade fair in the world. We hope to see you there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1" /><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T12:23:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3"><![CDATA[<p>With the transition to the EU MDR, legacy devices with certificates issued under the old EU directives (Directive 93/42/EEC on medical devices, MDD, and Directive 90/385/EEC on active implantable medical devices, AIMDD) can stay on the market under the transitional provisions set out in Article 120(3) of the MDR, provided they do not undergo any <b>significant changes</b>.</p>
  <p>In this article, we explain the concept of a ‘significant change’ and, using examples, help you understand whether you can still take advantage of the transitional arrangements in MDR Article 120(3).</p>
  <h2 id="transition-periods">Transition periods</h2>
  <p>The transition periods in Article 120(3) MDR as per Regulation (EU) 2023/607 are as follows:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Class III and IIb implants: new transition period until 31 December 2027</li>
    <li>Class IIb and lower: new transition period until 31 December 2028</li>
    <li>Class III custom-made products: new transition period until 31 December 2026</li>
    <li>No ‘sell-off’ deadline</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="what-does-significant-change-mean">What does significant change mean?</h2>
  <p>A significant change in the design or intended purpose consists of two cumulative elements:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>There is a change in the design or intended purpose, <b>and</b></li>
    <li>The change is significant</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Therefore, changes that do not concern the design or intended purpose are out of scope of Article 120(3) of the MDR. Changes that concern the design or intended purpose only fall under Article 120(3) if they are considered ‘significant’.</p>
  <h2 id="responsibilities-of-medical-device-manufacturers-regarding-significance-of-changes">Responsibilities of medical device manufacturers regarding ‘significance’ of changes</h2>
  <p>Medical device manufacturers have two primary responsibilities regarding changes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>provide evidence and justification that a change does not affect the design or intended purpose, or</li>
    <li>in cases where the change affects the design or intended purpose of the device, that it is non-significant.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The outcome of this assessment should be documented and made available to a competent authority when requested.</p>
  <p>If a change to a legacy device is not a significant change in design or intended purpose, it can be implemented using the above transitional arrangement. In these instances, manufacturers must adhere to the documentation criteria of AIMDD/MDD, meaning that the revised technical documentation must enable the evaluation of the product’s compliance with the relevant standards.</p>
  <h2 id="determining-a-significant-change-to-the-design-or-intended-purpose">Determining a significant change to the design or intended purpose</h2>
  <p>The <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a> guidance document sets out whether a change in the design or intended purpose of a device is considered ‘significant’ within the meaning of EU MDR Article 120(3c), point (b).</p>
  <p><b>Examples of changes in design and/or intended purpose that are ‘non-significant’:</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Changes related to corrective actions assessed and accepted by the competent authority</li>
    <li>Correction of spelling mistakes or merely editorial changes of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label or instructions for use)</li>
    <li>Clarifications of intended purpose, population, or clinical application in the information to be supplied with the device in line with the original certification</li>
    <li>Updates of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label, instructions for use or implant card) if they are required by EU legislation other than the MDR, are mere clarifications and do not adversely affect the devices’ safety and performance in relation to existing or new risks</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The following diagram, taken from the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a>, helps understand when <b>changes in design and/or intended purpose may be considered ‘significant’</b>:</p>
  <figure class="inline">
    <div class="image bordered">
      <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/significant-changes-main-chart.png" alt="Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart" loading="lazy" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart taken from <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a></figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>Charts A to E in the MDCG guideline contain specific areas where changes in the intended purpose, device design, device software, changes related to a substance or material or changes related to sterilisation are likely to be held to be significant. It’s vital to consult these charts when understanding whether a change will be significant and, by extension, whether your device can make use of the transitional arrangement.</p>
  <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
  <p>The definition of a “significant change” involves two cumulative elements: a change in design or intended purpose that is deemed significant. Manufacturers bear the responsibility of determining and justifying whether a change in their medical device is significant or not, and therefore whether relevant technical documents require updating in line with the changes. The MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1 guidance document provides guidance on determining the significance of changes in design or intended purpose.</p>
  <p>For further information regarding how we can meet your MDR requirements, including advice on whether changes are likely to be significant, <b>please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free and confidential discussion.</b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shen-may-khoo</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand what changes to your medical device are considered 'significant' under EU MDR (2017/745).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?" /><published>2023-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T12:23:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry"><![CDATA[<p>Medical devices and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices are like twin cities on different continents - both serving the needs of modern medicine, both highly regulated and, following the advent of updated legislation in Europe, governed by parallel legislation. However, sometimes the distinction between the two is less clear than might be thought.</p>
  <p>In this article, we unpick the differences between these two categories of product and explore requirements for gaining and maintaining market access for these device types.</p>
  <h2 id="is-my-product-regulated-by-the-mdr-or-the-ivdr">Is my product regulated by the MDR or the IVDR?</h2>
  <p>The now well-known <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745 (MDR)</a> and the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746&amp;qid=1698152662286" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i>In Vitro</i> Diagnostic Medical Devices Regulation (EU) 2017/746 (IVDR)</a> were developed to improve the regulatory framework which oversees products placed on the market in the EU.</p>
  <p>There are many similarities between the two Regulations in terms of quality management, risk management, risk based classification and post market surveillance. Despite the areas of overlap between them, it is essential for manufacturers to correctly categorise their product as a medical device or as an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (IVD) in order to demonstrate the applicable compliance with EU rules.</p>
  <h2 id="basic-definitions">Basic definitions</h2>
  <p>The definition of a medical device (Article 2 (1) MDR):</p>
  <blockquote class="standard">
    <p>'medical device' means any instrument, apparatus, appliance, software, implant, reagent, material or other article intended by the manufacturer to be used, alone or in combination, for human beings for one or more of the following specific medical purposes:</p>
    <ul class="disc">
      <li>diagnosis, prevention, monitoring, prediction, prognosis, treatment or alleviation of disease,</li>
      <li>diagnosis, monitoring, treatment, alleviation of, or compensation for, an injury or disability,</li>
      <li>investigation, replacement or modification of the anatomy or of a physiological or pathological process or state,</li>
      <li>providing information by means of <i>in vitro</i> examination of specimens derived from the human body, including organ, blood and tissue donations,</li>
    </ul>
    <p>and which does not achieve its principal intended action by pharmacological, immunological or metabolic means, in or on the human body, but which may be assisted in its function by such means.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>Examples of medical devices include surgical implants, wheelchairs, disposable gloves, pacemakers and infusion pumps.</p>
  <p>Indent 4 of the definition above includes medical devices which <i>‘provide information by means of in vitro examination of specimens.’</i> However, Article 1(6) MDR specifically states that the Regulation <strong>does not apply</strong> to <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices covered by Regulation (EU) 2017/746. Therefore, an IVD can be seen as a subset of the medical device family, but with its own governing Regulation IVDR (EU) 2017/746.</p>
  <p>The definition of an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (Article 2 (2) IVDR):</p>
  <blockquote class="standard">
    <p>'<i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device' means any medical device which is a reagent, reagent product, calibrator, control material, kit, instrument, apparatus, piece of equipment, software or system, whether used alone or in combination, intended by the manufacturer to be used <i>in vitro</i> for the examination of specimens, including blood and tissue donations, derived from the human body, solely or principally for the purpose of providing information on one or more of the following:</p>
    <ol class="lower-alpha">
      <li>concerning a physiological or pathological process or state</li>
      <li>concerning congenital physical or mental impairments</li>
      <li>concerning the predisposition to a medical condition or a disease</li>
      <li>to determine the safety and compatibility with potential recipients</li>
      <li>to predict treatment response or reaction</li>
      <li>to define or monitor therapeutic measures</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Specimen receptacles are also deemed to be <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>Examples of IVDs include laboratory machines which screen for infectious agents, compatibility for blood or tissue such as ABO or Rhesus and genetic tests. Self-tests for pregnancy, blood sugar and cholesterol are included in the definition. Companion diagnostics, where a device is specifically linked to a medicinal product to evaluate therapeutic response, are also categorised as IVDs.</p>
  <h2 id="patient-vs-sample">Patient vs Sample</h2>
  <p>An exclusion of the IVDR is any <i>‘invasive sampling products or products which are directly applied to the human body for the purpose of obtaining a specimen’</i>. Patients are not directly in contact with an IVD, other than a self-test IVD, which is not considered invasive. A sample of urine, blood or saliva which is collected from the patient, is then prepared and analysed by an IVD, either as a self-test, near-patient test (such as a hospital room) or in a laboratory. The results are then used for the management of the patient along with other therapeutic options.</p>
  <p>A device which obtains a sample from the patient in an invasive way such as a spinal needle for CSF collection or a punch biopsy for a tissue sample, falls under the medical device umbrella.</p>
  <h2 id="blurred-lines">Blurred lines</h2>
  <p>Of course, there may be cases where a product is a combination of a medical device and an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device. Both regulations are clear in this situation (as stated in Article 1 (4) IVDR and Article 1 (7) MDR).</p>
  <p>Any medical device which incorporates, as an integral part, an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device, shall be governed by the MDR, while the IVDR will apply to the <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic part of the device. The manufacturer will then have to meet both regulatory requirements in order to gain a CE mark for the combined device.</p>
  <h2 id="in-a-nutshell">In a nutshell</h2>
  <p><i>In vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices are a subcategory of medical devices with their own regulatory framework IVDR (EU) 2017/746. Although there is considerable overlap with the MDR (EU) 2017/745, it is imperative to categorise the product correctly from the beginning of the EU market access journey.</p>
  <p><b>For further information regarding compliance with the EU MDR or IVDR, <a href="/contact">contact Mantra Systems</a> for a FREE and open discussion.</b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A guide to easily understanding whether your device is a medical device or an in vitro diagnostic medical device (IVD).]]></summary></entry></feed>