<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-28T14:14:07+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">From IVDD to IVDR: Ensuring Compliance During the Transitional Period</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From IVDD to IVDR: Ensuring Compliance During the Transitional Period" /><published>2025-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-28T14:08:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period"><![CDATA[<p>The European Union <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng">In Vitro Diagnostic Regulation (EU IVDR 2017/746)</a> has transformed the medical device industry. Replacing the In Vitro Diagnostic Directive (IVDD 98/79/EC), <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/ivdr-consulting">the IVDR</a> establishes more rigorous standards to enhance the safety, performance, and quality of in vitro diagnostic medical devices (IVDs).</p>
      <p>However, the transition from IVDD to IVDR can be complex and manufacturers of legacy devices must navigate a range of considerations to ensure compliance while adapting to the new regulatory landscape.</p>
      <h2 id="maintaining-regulatory-compliance-during-the-ivdd-to-ivdr-transition">Maintaining Regulatory Compliance During the IVDD-to-IVDR Transition</h2>
      <p>To facilitate a smooth transition, IVDD-compliant legacy devices may continue to be placed on the market until the following deadlines:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Class D devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2027</strong>.</li>
        <li><strong>Class C devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2028</strong>.</li>
        <li><strong>Class B and Class A sterile devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2029</strong>.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>These <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/dfd7a1c6-f319-4682-9bac-77bef1165818_en">extended timelines</a> aim to provide manufacturers with the opportunity to adjust to the IVDR. However, continuing to market legacy devices during this period is conditional upon strict adherence to specific requirements.</p>
      <h2 id="conditions-for-placing-ivdd-compliant-devices-on-the-market">Conditions for Placing IVDD-Compliant Devices on the Market</h2>
      <p>Legacy devices may remain on the market during the transition period only if the following conditions are met:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>The device must remain fully compliant with the IVDD.</li>
        <li>There are no significant changes to device design or intended purpose.</li>
        <li>The device does not present an unacceptable risk to patient or user health and safety, nor to public health.</li>
        <li>By <strong>26 May 2025</strong>, the manufacturer must have implemented a Quality Management System (QMS) in accordance with Article 10(8) of the IVDR.</li>
        <li>A formal application must have been lodged with a notified body (as per section 4.3, Annex VII) for conformity assessment no later than the 26 May 2025 for Class D devices, <strong>26 May 2026</strong> for Class C devices, and 26 May 2027 for Class B and Class A sterile devices.</li>
        <li>The manufacturer must have written agreement with the Notified Body by <strong>26 September 2025</strong> for Class D devices, <strong>26 September 2026</strong> for Class C devices, and <strong>26 September 2027</strong> for Class B and Class A sterile devices.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Failure to meet these conditions will negate compliance under transitional provisions.</p>
      <h2 id="implementing-an-ivdr-compliant-qms">Implementing an IVDR-Compliant QMS</h2>
      <p>Having an IVDR complaint QMS in place is not just about meeting regulatory requirements; it is a proactive strategy to ensure the continuous safety and performance of an IVD in a competitive market. To meet IVDR requirements, the QMS must include the following elements:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A strategy for regulatory compliance, including management of modifications to devices.</li>
        <li>Identification of safety and performance requirements and strategies to address them.</li>
        <li>Clear management responsibility and accountability.</li>
        <li>Resource management, including oversight of suppliers and subcontractors.</li>
        <li>Comprehensive risk management in line with Annex I, Section 3.</li>
        <li>Performance evaluation, including Post-Market Performance Follow-up (PMPF) per Article 56 and Annex XIII.</li>
        <li>Processes for product realisation, from design and development to production and service.</li>
        <li>Verification of <strong>Unique Device Identifier (UDI)</strong> assignments and consistent device information management under Articles 24(3) and 26.</li>
        <li>A robust <strong>Post-Market Surveillance (PMS)</strong> system, as outlined in Article 78.</li>
        <li>Effective communication with stakeholders, including authorities, notified bodies, and customers.</li>
        <li>Processes for reporting serious incidents and implementing corrective and preventive actions (CAPA).</li>
        <li>Monitoring, measurement, and continuous product improvement.</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 id="an-ivdr-compliant-qms-for-legacy-devices">An IVDR-Compliant QMS for Legacy Devices</h2>
      <p>Manufacturers must ensure their QMS is aligned with IVDR regulatory requirements. However, for certain aspects outlined in Article 10(8), such as points (b), (e), and (f), a distinction must be made for “legacy devices”. For these devices, manufacturers are not required to have identified all relevant safety and performance requirements, implemented comprehensive risk management, or conducted a full performance evaluation. However, it is important to note that from the 26 May 2025, manufacturers must ensure that their QMS addresses how compliance with these requirements will be achieved for legacy devices, ensuring full alignment with IVDR standards.</p>
      <p>Manufacturers have a few strategic options for updating to an IVDR-compliant QMS. One approach is to establish a parallel QMS. This approach enables clear reference to the appropriate procedures and highlights the transition to the new system. For companies with complex, long-standing QMS, it offers the chance to streamline and enhance efficiency. However, this approach demands considerable effort to develop and eventually replace the old procedures.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, companies whose existing QMS already aligns closely with the new IVDR requirements might prefer to update their current system. While this option can be more efficient, it may present challenges in ensuring that certain QMS elements are applied consistently across all products.</p>
      <p>Despite the chosen approach, documenting the transition is critical, clearly defining which procedures apply, when they take effect, and which products they impact. This can be done either within the procedures themselves or through a separate project plan. In addition, comprehensive training is key to ensuring everyone involved understands and implements the new requirements effectively.</p>
      <h2 id="the-time-to-act-is-now">The Time to Act Is Now</h2>
      <p>As the transition deadlines approach, manufacturers of legacy IVDs need to act swiftly to remain competitive and compliant in the evolving European market. The IVDR represents a major overhaul of IVD regulation in the EU, but it aims to ensure medical devices are safer, more effective, and of higher quality. Manufacturers who embrace these changes and take proactive steps to comply will be better positioned to navigate the evolving regulatory environment, ensuring continued market access and patient safety.</p>
      <p>Struggling with your IVDD to IVDR transition? Mantra Systems is here to help! Our expertise can guide you through the complexities of achieving IVDR compliance and ensure your QMS is up to date with the latest regulatory requirements. <a href="/contact">Contact us today</a>.</p>
      ]]></content><author><name>shona-richardson</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating this shift presents unique challenges. Legacy device manufacturers must manage timelines, ensure adherence to transitional provisions and update QMS.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Overview of the UK’s 2024 Post-Market Surveillance Update</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Overview of the UK’s 2024 Post-Market Surveillance Update" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T17:13:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/medical-devices-post-market-surveillance-requirements/the-medical-devices-post-market-surveillance-requirements-amendment-great-britain-regulations-2024-guidance-on-implementation">UK’s Medical Devices (Post-market Surveillance Requirements) (Amendment) Regulations 2024</a> introduce significant changes to the Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) landscape for medical devices. These changes aim to strengthen the PMS system in the UK, ultimately improving patient safety. In this article, we will provide a detailed breakdown of these changes and what they mean for you.</p>
    <h2 id="introduction-to-the-mandatory-pms-plan">Introduction to the Mandatory PMS Plan</h2>
    <p>One of the most significant changes is the mandatory requirement for manufacturers to <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">have a PMS plan in place</a>. This plan, which outlines the methods for gathering and analysing device performance and safety data throughout the device’s lifecycle, is a crucial component of the updated regulations.</p>
    <p>The PMS plan should include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Objectives of the PMS system</li>
      <li>Processes to gather information, ensuring comprehensive real-world data is obtained</li>
      <li>Methods of data analysis</li>
      <li>Processes for fulfilling <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/vigilance">vigilance reporting</a> obligations</li>
      <li>Links to preventive and corrective action as part of a risk management process</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Manufacturers must review the actions taken according to the PMS plan at regular intervals and document the review in a Post-Market Surveillance Report (PMSR) or Periodic Safety Update Report (PSUR), as appropriate.</p>
    <h2 id="enhancing-patient-and-public-engagement">Enhancing Patient and Public Engagement</h2>
    <p>The regulations underscore the significance of gathering feedback directly from patients and the public. This inclusive approach ensures that their experiences and perspectives are considered.</p>
    <p>This includes obtaining feedback on the device’s usability and the adequacy of the instructions for use. Depending on the device type, manufacturers need to assess and document the extent to which this is relevant and achievable.</p>
    <h2 id="focusing-on-similar-devices">Focusing on Similar Devices</h2>
    <p>To improve signal detection, manufacturers must collect data on their devices across all markets and review publicly available information on the safety of similar devices offered by competitors.</p>
    <p>The regulations define similar devices as those based on the same or similar technology and with the same or similar intended purpose.</p>
    <h2 id="taking-preventive-and-corrective-actions">Taking Preventive and Corrective Actions</h2>
    <p>The regulations require manufacturers to take preventive and corrective actions to address potential safety or conformity issues with their devices. This includes cooperating with the Medicines &amp; Healthcare products Regulatory Agency (MHRA) on any actions taken.</p>
    <p>Preventive actions should be taken before the manufacturing process is completed, while corrective actions should be taken after the devices have been manufactured.</p>
    <h2 id="understanding-reporting-requirements">Understanding Reporting Requirements</h2>
    <p>Manufacturers must submit PMSRs or PSURs to the MHRA, depending on the device classification. The PSURs must follow a standardised format and be updated at set intervals.</p>
    <p>The PMSR or PSUR should provide a comprehensive and critical analysis of the device’s risk-benefit balance and include a summary of the analysis and conclusions from the review of the PMS data gathered since the last report.</p>
    <h2 id="incorporating-vigilance-reporting">Incorporating Vigilance Reporting</h2>
    <p>The regulations outline the requirements for reporting serious incidents, Field Safety Corrective Actions (FSCAs), and adverse trends to the MHRA. This includes specific timelines for reporting and the use of the MHRA’s Manufacturer’s Incident Report (MIR) form.</p>
    <p>A serious incident is defined as one that directly or indirectly led to, or could have led to, death or serious deterioration in the state of health of a patient, user, or another person.</p>
    <h2 id="communicating-field-safety-notices-fsns">Communicating Field Safety Notices (FSNs)</h2>
    <p>Manufacturers must communicate FSCAs to affected customers using FSNs. The FSNs must include Unique Device Identifier (UDI) information where available and be sent in a searchable format. The MHRA encourages manufacturers to host a copy of the FSN on their website for transparency.</p>
    <p>The FSN should clearly communicate the risk and the actions taken to mitigate it. Manufacturers should take reasonable steps to ensure that all affected end-users receive and understand the FSN.</p>
    <h2 id="fscas-outside-great-britain">FSCAs Outside Great Britain</h2>
    <p>If a manufacturer undertakes an FSCA outside Great Britain that affects the same type of devices supplied in Great Britain, they must notify the MHRA within three UK working days of the FSN being circulated, even if the devices in Great Britain are not affected.</p>
    <p>This requirement is in place to provide transparency and avoid confusion by clarifying why the FSCA does not affect the UK.</p>
    <h2 id="additional-important-changes">Additional Important Changes</h2>
    <p>The update also amends the following:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Clarification of Important Terms:</strong> The regulations define key terms, such as “lifetime” and “PMS period,” to ensure consistency and clarity.</li>
      <li><strong>Reportable Side Effects:</strong> The regulations clarify the definition of reportable side effects to include any negative impact on the health of the patient, their care, or wider public health.</li>
      <li><strong>Self-Administered Treatment:</strong> The regulations clarify that interventions to prevent serious deterioration in health include self-administered treatment.</li>
      <li><strong>Use Errors:</strong> The regulations specify that use errors do not need to result in serious deterioration in health to be reportable; the risk of occurrence is sufficient.</li>
      <li><strong>UDI Information:</strong> The regulations require the inclusion of Unique Device Identifier (UDI) information in incident reports and FSNs where available.</li>
      <li><strong>Trend Reporting:</strong> The regulations require manufacturers to submit trend reports for incidents that are reportable individually, as well as those that do not meet the criteria for individual reporting.</li>
      <li><strong>Custom-Made Devices:</strong> The regulations clarify that trend reports are not required for custom-made devices.</li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
    <p>The UK’s Medical Devices (Post-market Surveillance Requirements) (Amendment) Regulations 2024 represent a significant step towards strengthening the PMS system for medical devices. By clarifying requirements, enhancing patient engagement, and focusing on proactive risk mitigation, these regulations aim to improve patient safety and ensure the continued effectiveness of medical devices in the UK market.</p>
    <p>If you need to speak to an expert to understand more about what this update might mean for you, <a href="/contact">contact us to arrange a free, no-obligation discussion</a>.</p>
    ]]></content><author><name>ron-sangal</name></author><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What might mandatory PMS plans - which emphasise enhanced patient engagement and proactive risk management - mean for the industry?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Clinical Evidence Requirements with MDCG 2020-6</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Clinical Evidence Requirements with MDCG 2020-6" /><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-15T12:40:25+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6"><![CDATA[<p>As legacy devices transition to compliance with the new Medical Device Regulation (MDR), manufacturers face the challenge of meeting updated clinical evidence requirements. <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/40904/">MDCG 2020-6 offers essential guidance</a> on how to assess and demonstrate sufficient clinical evidence to ensure legacy devices meet MDR General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</p>
  <h2 id="what-constitutes-a-legacy-device-and-what-are-the-clinical-evidence-requirements">What constitutes a ‘legacy device’ and what are the clinical evidence requirements?</h2>
  <p>Legacy devices include all <a href="/articles/keeping-medical-devices-in-market-maintaining-ce-marks">devices previously CE marked</a> under the European Medical Devices Directive 93/42/EEC (MDD) or the <a href="https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/european-standards/harmonised-standards/implantable-medical-devices_en">Active Implantable Medical Devices Directive 90/385/EEC (AIMDD)</a>.</p>
  <p>The MDR states that for legacy devices “sufficient” clinical evidence is required to demonstrate conformity with the relevant General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</p>
  <p>MDCG 2020-6 offers guidance on demonstrating sufficient clinical evidence for legacy devices. It states that both MDD and MDR require the quantity and quality of clinical data to be sufficient to demonstrate safety, performance and the acceptability of the benefit-risk ratio: both the Directives and the MDR require clinical evidence to be robust and the conclusions derived from this evidence to be scientifically valid. The guidance also reports that “the level of clinical evidence required for the device under evaluation needs to be determined by the manufacturer and verified by the notified body. The level of clinical evidence shall be appropriate in view of the characteristics of the device and its intended purpose.”</p>
  <h2 id="clinical-evaluation-for-legacy-devices">Clinical evaluation for legacy devices</h2>
  <p>The clinical evaluation process under EU MDR 2017/745 requires clinical data to:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Demonstrate conformity with the applicable GSPRs set out in MDR Annex I under the normal conditions of the intended use of the device</li>
    <li>Assess undesirable side effects and the acceptability of the benefit-risk ratio.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>For legacy devices, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">the MDR clinical evaluation process</a> relies on post-market clinical data and clinical data generated during conformity assessments under MDD/AIMDD. Devices previously CE marked under MDD/AIMDD are expected to have continuously collected evidence in line with evolving regulatory requirements and guidance. However, MDCG 2020-6 clarifies that clinical data from conformity assessments under the MDD may not necessarily provide sufficient clinical evidence to meet MDR requirements. Therefore, manufacturers should assess whether additional evidence is needed to comply with MDR standards.</p>
  <p>Sections of the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/17522/attachments/1/translations/">MEDDEV 2.7/1 rev. 4</a> that remain relevant under the MDR are listed in Appendix I of the document. Additionally, if clinical data from an equivalent device has been used, manufacturers must verify that these devices still meet the <a href="/articles/five-tips-for-making-a-medical-device-equivalence-claim-under-the-mdr">MDR’s equivalence criteria</a>.</p>
  <p>During the transitional period, legacy devices are not exempt from the MDR’s additional requirements, including those related to Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) and <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf">Post-Market Clinical Follow-Up (PMCF)</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="how-can-mdcg-2020-6-help-with-the-mdr-conformity-assessment">How can MDCG 2020-6 help with the MDR conformity assessment?</h2>
  <p>MDCG 2020-6 provides guidance on establishing or updating a Clinical Evaluation Plan for legacy devices; the minimum content for the Clinical Evaluation Plan is described in Appendix II of the guidance document.</p>
  <p>Guidance is also described for the identification of available clinical data including pre-market and post-market sources, appraisal of the clinical data with respect to the overall clinical evaluation, generation of new clinical data to bridge gaps and analysis of the clinical data to demonstrate conformity with relevant GSPRs.</p>
  <p>A list of the suggested hierarchy of clinical evidence is documented in Appendix III of MDCG 2020-6, ranked from strongest to weakest level of evidence.</p>
  <p>Listed as number 1 are “results of high-quality clinical investigations covering all device variants, indications, patient populations, duration of treatment etc”; however, it is acknowledged that clinical investigations may not be feasible or necessary for legacy devices with a wide range of indications.</p>
  <h2 id="when-must-my-legacy-device-conform-to-the-updated-mdr-assessment">When must my legacy device conform to the updated MDR assessment?</h2>
  <p>Under the timelines established by the MDR, the deadline for manufacturers to apply to a Notified Body for a conformity assessment and to have a compliant Quality Management System (QMS) in place was 26 May 2021. Additionally, manufacturers were required to have a formal, written agreement with the Notified Body by 26 September 2024.</p>
  <p>Transition deadlines for legacy devices depend on their classification:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>For <strong>Class III custom-made implantable devices</strong>, the deadline for full MDR compliance is <strong>26 May 2026</strong>.</li>
    <li>For <strong>Class III and Class IIb implantable devices that are non-WET (Well-Established Technologies)</strong>, the deadline for MDR compliance is <strong>31 December 2027</strong>.</li>
    <li>For all other <strong>Class IIb, Class IIa, Class Is, and Class Im devices</strong>, the deadline for MDR compliance is <strong>31 December 2028</strong>.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The recent release of MDCG 2021-25 Rev. 1 provides crucial insights into applying MDR requirements to ‘legacy’ and ‘old’ devices in light of the extended transitional period from MDD to MDR.</p>
  <p><strong>If you need to speak to an expert to understand more about potential need for clinical evidence for a legacy device, <a href="/contact">contact us to arrange a free, no obligation discussion</a>.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>clare-dixon</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can manufacturers ensure legacy devices meet MDR's stringent requirements? Discover how MDCG 2020-6 guidance simplifies the path to compliance.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clinical benefits of an in vitro diagnostic medical device</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-benefits-of-an-in-vitro-diagnostic-medical-device" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clinical benefits of an in vitro diagnostic medical device" /><published>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T11:00:58+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-benefits-of-an-in-vitro-diagnostic-medical-device</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-benefits-of-an-in-vitro-diagnostic-medical-device"><![CDATA[<p>The ‘clinical benefit’ of an IVD differs from that of pharmaceuticals or therapeutic devices, offering vital diagnostic insights that help to guide clinical decisions. Understanding this concept under <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/ivdr-consulting">the IVDR</a> is essential for compliance and plays a pivotal role in advancing patient care and outcomes.</p>
  <h2 id="how-does-the-mdr-define-a-clinical-benefit">How does the MDR define a ‘clinical benefit’?</h2>
  <p>‘Clinical benefit’ of a medical device under <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0745">EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR) 2017/745</a> is well understood. Article 2(53) defines ‘clinical benefit’ as the positive impact of a device on the health of an individual expressed in terms of a meaningful, measurable, patient-relevant clinical outcome(s). This ‘clinical benefit’ is the improvement that the patient is expected to experience as a result of the device when used as intended, either directly or indirectly.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-the-clinical-benefit-of-an-in-vitro-diagnostic-medical-device">What is the ‘clinical benefit’ of an in vitro diagnostic medical device?</h2>
  <p>The ‘clinical benefit’ of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostic medical devices (IVDs), as defined by <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746">the EU In Vitro Diagnostic Regulation (IVDR) 2017/746</a>, differs significantly from that of pharmaceuticals or therapeutic medical devices. However, it remains crucial to accurately understand the concept of ‘clinical benefit’ for regulatory compliance.</p>
  <p>Unlike pharmaceuticals or therapeutic medical devices, which directly impact a patient’s health by treating or managing a condition, IVDs provide critical diagnostic information that supports clinical decisions. For example, IVDs include tools like blood tests or sputum analyses that help healthcare professionals understand a patient’s condition. These results are combined with data from other diagnostic tools, such as physical exams or imaging, to guide decisions about the patient’s care. Therefore, the outcome depends on a combination of diagnostic and therapeutic interventions included in the broader management plan.</p>
  <p>As per the EU IVDR Article 2(37), ‘clinical benefit’ means the positive impact of a device related to its function, such as that of screening, monitoring, diagnosis or aid to diagnosis of patients, or a positive impact on patient management or public health.</p>
  <h2 id="how-to-provide-evidence-of-an-ivd-clinical-benefit">How to provide evidence of an IVD ‘clinical benefit’?</h2>
  <p>A ‘clinical benefit’ of an IVD can be evidenced through its clinical performance by the gathering of <a href="/articles/scientific-validity-reports-foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation">performance data (both analytical and clinical)</a>. Through performance data, it can be shown how the use of the IVD within the diagnostic or management plan, can assist in the final outcome of the patient.</p>
  <p>An example of a ‘clinical benefit’ provided by an IVD could be the early detection of a disease. This allows treatment to be administered more promptly and effectively e.g. the detection of tuberculosis will accelerate the initiation of treatment, thus preventing or aiding the management of complications.</p>
  <p>An IVD can prevent the spread of disease by identifying patients with a disease which may have the potential to spread throughout the population. IVDs such a companion diagnostic will enable the identification of patients who are most likely to benefit from a particular therapeutic product. They can also monitor the treatment with a particular therapeutic product for the purpose of treatment adjustment for safety or efficacy.</p>
  <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
  <p>The ‘clinical benefit’ of an IVD is its ability to provide accurate medical information that directly influences clinical decisions, whether for detection, diagnosis, or treatment monitoring. This value can be clearly evidenced through clinical performance data presented in the Clinical Performance Report (CPR) and Performance Evaluation Report (PER). By effectively showcasing how an IVD enhances patient management and public health, manufacturers can meet the EU IVDR 2017/746 requirements while reinforcing the vital role these devices play in improving healthcare outcomes.</p>
  <p><strong>For further information regarding how we can meet your IVDR requirements, <a href="/contact">please contact us today</a>.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to determine the clinical benefit of an IVD and successfully incorporate it into regulatory documentation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2024</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2024" /><published>2024-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-03T16:32:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2024"><![CDATA[<p>Mantra Systems is looking forward to attending <a href="https://www.medica-tradefair.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MEDICA 2024</a> - a prestigious international medical trade fair held in Düsseldorf, Germany.</p>
  <p>A team from Mantra Systems will be attending this year’s trade fair on the 12th &amp; 13th of November, so if you are attending, we would love to connect.</p>
  <p>Our CEO Paul Hercock, Operations Director Richard Jones, Chief Medical Writer Dr. Gayle Louise Buchel, Chief Regulatory Officer Sandra Gopinath, and Senior Lead Medical Writer Simon Cumiskey will be present, ready to engage with industry leaders, share insights, and explore the latest breakthroughs in medical device technology.</p>
  <p>For those attending MEDICA 2024, <a href="/contact">we invite you to connect</a> with our representatives during the event. As a specialised medical device market access consultancy, we are eager to share insights, discuss regulatory challenges, and explore collaborative opportunities.
    <!-- prod. test --></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>richard-jones</name></author><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mantra Systems is going to MEDICA 2024, the largest medical trade fair in the world. We hope to see you there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 - Its impact on EU MDR and IVDR</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 - Its impact on EU MDR and IVDR" /><published>2024-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-19T16:02:26+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/regulation-EU-2024-1860-its-impact-on-eu-mdr-and-ivdr"><![CDATA[<p>The European Parliament and the Council of the European Union recently amended the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR) and the EU <i>in vitro</i> Diagnostic Medical Device Regulation (IVDR) with <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=OJ:L_202401860&amp;qid=1720500341754" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Regulation (EU) 2024/1860</a>.</p>
  <p>In this article, we explain how in two key areas these amendments reinforce important elements of the previously published regulatory framework, helping maintain the high quality and safety standards of medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices.</p>
  <h2 id="1-gradual-roll-out-of-the-european-database-on-medical-devices-eudamed">1. Gradual roll-out of the European database on medical devices (EUDAMED)</h2>
  <p>This update requires that the Commission set up, maintain, and manage <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">EUDAMED</a>, a framework comprising seven interconnected electronic systems. EUDAMED aims to provide better transparency and traceability of medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices among EU member states. Four systems are complete to date, and two more are expected to be finished in 2024. The European Commission recently updated the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/04ce2012-97df-4dd0-8a39-d4f6993b9e16_en?filename=md_eudamed_roadmap_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EUDAMED roadmap</a>, outlining key roll-out dates.</p>
  <p>However, the complexity of clinical investigations and performance studies poses a significant challenge, leading to delays in implementing EUDAMED across member states. As a result, EUDAMED will gradually roll out as individual electronic systems, with each system being implemented after thorough verification by the Commission.</p>
  <h2 id="2-ensuring-a-smooth-transition-to-the-ivdr">2. Ensuring a smooth transition to the IVDR</h2>
  <p>The transition from the EU Medical Devices Directive (IVDD) to the IVDR poses a challenge for <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers</a>, as shown by comparing conformity assessment applications and certificates issued by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Bodies</a>. With the transitional period ending on 26 May 2025, there is a high risk of shortages of critical <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices, especially high-risk (Class D) devices.</p>
  <p>Thus, the transitional period has been extended to prevent device shortages, protect patient health, and mitigate market disruption. This extension aims to provide manufacturers and notified bodies with the time necessary to complete the necessary conformity assessments. 
    As part of this, manufacturers must inform the relevant authorities of any perceived disruptions or discontinuation of medical devices that could harm patients or public health.</p>
  <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>
  <p>These changes collectively aim to strengthen the regulatory framework for medical and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices, improve safety and transparency, prioritise public health and foster medical device innovation.</p>
  <p><b>At Mantra Systems, we are medical device regulatory experts with a track record of successful regulatory submissions.</b> Please contact <a href="mailto:shona&#64;mantrasystems.com">shona@mantrasystems.com</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to to find out how we can help you overcome regulatory challenges and gain approval for your device.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shona-richardson</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How does the recent Regulation (EU) 2024/1860 amendment affect the EU MDR &amp; IVDR?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDCG 2024-10 - Orphan medical devices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDCG 2024-10 - Orphan medical devices" /><published>2024-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-09T16:14:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2024-10-orphan-medical-devices"><![CDATA[<p>With the introduction of the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR), there has been an increased emphasis on clinical evidence requirements. Manufacturers of medical devices indicated for rare diseases found these new obligations burdensome, potentially impacting patient access to these devices.</p>
  <p>Released in June 2024, the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/daa1fc59-9d2c-4e82-878e-d6fdf12ecd1a_en?filename=mdcg_2024-10_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2024-10 guidance</a> introduces and defines new terms to the MDR regulatory landscape and aims to address these challenges faced by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers of medical devices</a> indicated for use in rare diseases.</p>
  <p>In this article, we explore the impact of MDCG 2024-10 on clinical evidence requirements, shedding light on its key considerations and implications.</p>
  <h2 id="orphan-device-classification">Orphan device classification</h2>
  <p>An “orphan device” is defined as a medical device specifically intended to benefit patients in the treatment, diagnosis, or prevention of a disease or condition that affects no more than 12,000 individuals in the European Union per year. To qualify as an orphan device, at least one of the following criteria must be met:</p>
  <ol>
    <li><strong>Insufficiency of alternatives</strong>: There are no adequate alternative treatment, diagnostic, or preventive options available for the specific disease or condition.</li>
    <li><strong>Clinical benefit</strong>: The device offers an expected clinical benefit compared to existing alternatives or the current state of the art. This assessment considers both device-specific factors and the patient population.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Manufacturers seeking orphan device classification must provide a justification based on epidemiological data to the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Body</a>. Additionally, this information should be summarised in the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-report-cer">Clinical Evaluation Report</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="orphan-subpopulation-and-orphan-indication">Orphan subpopulation and orphan indication</h2>
  <p>In addition to the classification of orphan devices, the MDCG 2024-10 provides guidance for devices that serve specific patient sub-populations or have multiple indications.</p>
  <h3 id="orphan-subpopulation">Orphan subpopulation</h3>
  <p>This guidance applies to devices intended for use in the treatment, diagnosis, or prevention of a disease or condition within a clinically valid patient sub-population. Specifically, the sub-population should not exceed 12,000 individuals in the European Union per year (within a disease or condition with an annual incidence of more than 12,000 in the EU).</p>
  <h3 id="orphan-indication">Orphan indication</h3>
  <p>Sometimes, a medical device may have a specific intended purpose or indication for an orphan population (or orphan subpopulation) in addition to another intended purpose or indication in larger patient populations. In such cases, the MDCG 2024-10 outlines clinical evidence requirements specifically for the component of the intended purpose related to the orphan population.</p>
  <h2 id="clinical-vs-non-clinical-data-for-orphan-devices">Clinical vs. non-clinical data for orphan devices</h2>
  <p>When evaluating an orphan device, both clinical and non-clinical data play crucial roles.</p>
  <h3 id="clinical-data-considerations">Clinical data considerations</h3>
  <ol>
    <li><strong>Substantial evidence</strong>: If non-clinical data provide substantial high-quality evidence supporting the safety and performance of the orphan device, it can reduce the burden of pre-market clinical data requirements. This evidence can help justify CE marking, even when there are limitations in clinical data that can be addressed through <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf">Post-Market Clinical Follow-up (PMCF) activities</a>.</li>
    <li><strong>Acceptable limitations</strong>: Limitations in pre-market clinical data are acceptable under certain conditions:
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Expected clinical benefit</strong>: There must be sufficient clinical evidence demonstrating the expected clinical benefit, and the device must perform as intended with an acceptable level of safety.</li>
        <li><strong>Compliance with GSPRs</strong>: The device must meet all relevant General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</li>
        <li><strong><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf-plan">PMCF plan</a></strong>: A well-defined PMCF plan should generate additional clinical data within an appropriate time-frame, fully addressing any remaining limitations.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <h3 id="clinical-data-sources">Clinical data sources</h3>
  <p>Sources of clinical data must relate to either the subject or equivalent devices, and include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Clinical investigations</strong>: Studies involving human subjects and undertaken to assess the safety or performance of a device.</li>
    <li><strong>Peer-reviewed scientific literature</strong>: Relevant research published in reputable journals.</li>
    <li><strong>PMCF</strong>: Data collected during post-market follow-up.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="useful-non-clinical-data">Useful non-clinical data</h3>
  <p>Non-clinical data can complement clinical evidence. Useful sources include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Laboratory and animal tests</strong>: Results from in vitro and animal studies.</li>
    <li><strong>Computer modelling and simulated testing</strong>: Data from software-based models, 3D printed models, and other physical simulations.</li>
    <li><strong>Ex vivo and cadaveric studies</strong>: Insights gained from studies using tissue samples or cadavers.</li>
    <li><strong>Similar devices</strong>: Data from devices similar to the orphan device (when equivalence is not demonstrated).</li>
    <li><strong>State of the Art information</strong>: Understanding the technology landscape.</li>
    <li><strong>Health datasets</strong>: Previously collected patient health information, often used for software validation without exposing patients.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>MDCG 2024-10 offers guidance on the classification and clinical evidence requirements for orphan devices. Importantly, manufacturers of orphan devices may use non-clinical data, in combination with a rigorous <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf-plan">PMCF plan</a>, to supplement clinical evidence to address pre-market clinical data limitations.</p>
  <p>Please email <a href="mailto:simon&#64;mantrasystems.com">simon@mantrasystems.com</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to understand <strong>how Mantra Systems can help you meet your MDR requirements</strong>.</p>
  <p>Alternatively, for any general regulatory questions you need a quick answer to, have you tried our <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</a>? — it’s free and will answer your queries around the clock.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to apply MDR pre-market clinical evidence requirements to medical devices intended for limited usage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A medical device’s intended purpose - what is the point?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A medical device’s intended purpose - what is the point?" /><published>2024-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-14T12:56:38+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-devices-intended-purpose-what-is-the-point"><![CDATA[<p>A clear idea of your medical device’s intended purpose is crucial in meeting the EU MDR regulatory requirements. Getting it right early in the development process is important, as it provides inputs to:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Objectives of the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>,</li>
    <li>Defining the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">SOTA</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="/articles/keeping-medical-devices-in-market-maintaining-ce-marks">Design of clinical investigations</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="/articles/five-tips-for-making-a-medical-device-equivalence-claim-under-the-mdr">Equivalence claims</a>,</li>
    <li>Evidence for conformity to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxyKV003WaY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relevant GSPRs</a>.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>A clinical evaluation should, according to its definition in Article 2(44) of the EU MDR, <q>“verify the safety and performance, including clinical benefits, of the device when used as intended by the manufacturer.”</q></p>
  <p>But what is the intended purpose, and how does it interact with indications for use, claims, and intended clinical benefits? <b>For each term, we will consider a fictional hip implant device.</b></p>
  <h2 id="intended-purpose">Intended purpose</h2>
  <p>‘Intended purpose’ should describe <b>what the device is used for and the effect of the device</b>. Article 2(12) of the EU MDR defines ‘intended purpose’ as <q>“the use for which a device is intended according to the data supplied by the manufacturer on the label, in the instructions for use or in promotional or sales materials or statements and as specified by the manufacturer in the clinical evaluation.”</q></p>
  <p>All medical devices will have an intended purpose. In the case of a hip implant, the intended purpose could be for the replacement of native hip joints in adult patients with moderate to severe hip osteoarthritis.</p>
  <h2 id="indication-for-use">Indication for use</h2>
  <p>‘Indication for use’ should describe <b>the clinical condition that the device targets</b>. MDCG 2020-6 defines the indication for use as <q>“the clinical condition that is to be diagnosed, prevented, monitored, treated, alleviated, compensated for, replaced, modified or controlled by the medical device.”</q></p>
  <p>Some devices, therefore, may not have an indication for use. An example would be a medical device intended to sterilise equipment. In the case of a hip implant, the indication for use could be hip osteoarthritis with an Oxford Hip Score less than 29.</p>
  <h2 id="clinical-benefit">Clinical benefit</h2>
  <p>‘Clinical benefit’ should describe <b>the benefit to the patient from using the device in a quantifiable manner</b>. Article 2(53) of the EU MDR defines clinical benefit as <q>“the positive impact of a device on the health of an individual, expressed in terms of a meaningful, measurable, patient-relevant clinical outcome(s), including outcome(s) related to diagnosis, or a positive impact on patient management or public health.”</q></p>
  <p>All devices will have a clinical benefit, but these can be either direct or indirect. In the case of a hip implant, the intended clinical benefit could be the reduction in pain VAS score by 25%. An example of a medical device with an indirect clinical benefit would be the scalpel used during the operation; a scalpel will not reduce pain in patients with osteoarthritis, but will facilitate insertion of the hip replacement and therefore lead to an improvement in pain VAS score.</p>
  <h2 id="claims">Claims</h2>
  <p>‘Claims’ are not defined in the EU MDR, but Article 7 prohibits any information supplied by the manufacturer that may mislead the user with regard to the intended purpose, safety, or performance. Claims, therefore, can be <b>derived from any manufacturer documents</b> and should be supported by clinical evidence in the clinical evaluation.</p>
  <p>Claims will encompass all of the intended use, indications for use, clinical benefits, as well as other terms not discussed in this article such as intended user, use environment, etc.</p>
  <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
  <p>To briefly summarise each of the points above:</p>
  <table class="simple">
    <tr>
      <th>Intended purpose</th>
      <td>Is the use and effect of the device.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Indications for use</th>
      <td>Is the clinical condition that the device targets.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Clinical benefit</th>
      <td>Is the measurable impact on the patient.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th>Claims</th>
      <td>Derived from the above, plus any other claims made in marketing materials, IFU, etc.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  <p>For further information on how we can help you meet your MDR requirements please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free and confidential discussion.</p>
  <p>Alternatively, for any general regulatory questions you need a quick answer to, have you tried our <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</a>? — it’s free and will answer your queries around the clock.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><category term="PMCF" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How do you define intended purpose, indication for use, intended clinical benefits, and claims?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR and MDCG chatbot</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR and MDCG chatbot" /><published>2024-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T16:04:02+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/enablechat-your-ai-powered-mdr-mdcg-chatbot"><![CDATA[<p>A deep understanding of the MDR and associated MDCG documents is crucial for achieving compliance with the EU Medical Device Regulations.</p>
  <p>However, the MDR itself is 175 pages long and the MDCG documents, at the time of writing, number over 100 files. With so much information available it can sometimes be difficult to find the relevant information.</p>
  <p>To solve this problem we have developed EnableChat, <a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat">your AI-powered regulatory chatbot</a>.</p>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="Mej0nkKHP7M"></div>
    <p class="video-caption">About EnableChat - Your AI-powered MDR &amp; MDCG chatbot</p>
  </div>
  <h2 id="the-solution">The Solution</h2>
  <p>EnableChat is, in simple terms, a question and answer service. Ask any question related to MDR compliance and, like magic, EnableChat will search the MDR and MDCG documents and find the answer you are looking for. It will even list the most relevant documents and provide a link, connecting you directly with them.</p>
  <p>More specifically, EnableChat is a retrieval-augmented generative question and answering web application that finds the most relevant MDCG documents or MDR pages, before using a large language model to answer the user’s question based on the relevant documents. This method ensures high accuracy while maintaining a friendly, conversational style.</p>
  <p>EnableChat is free to use (no sign-up required) and searches all the latest MDCG documents as well as the MDR text.</p>
  <p class="align-center"><a href="/medical-device-regulation-resources/enablechat" class="button">Try EnableChat</a></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Search the MDR and MDCG documents in seconds by asking EnableChat your questions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying vigilant - A guide to searching for adverse events data</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying vigilant - A guide to searching for adverse events data" /><published>2024-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-23T00:32:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/staying-vigilant-a-guide-to-searching-for-adverse-events-data"><![CDATA[<p>Searching for and analysing adverse events data relating to subject and similar devices is essential in any medical device MDR submission. Although intended to be a future major component of adverse events reporting, the EUDAMED database is not yet fully functional and does not currently allow for the searching of <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/vigilance">vigilance data</a>.</p>
  <p>In this article, we outline what other adverse event databases are available, along with the pros and cons of each.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-adverse-events-data-used-for">What is adverse events data used for?</h2>
  <p>Data gathered by the manufacturer’s <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">Post-Market Surveillance (PMS)</a> system, including adverse events, is used for the following purposes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>To detect and report types and frequencies of adverse events</li>
    <li>To identify any new risks not currently considered in <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk Management</a> files</li>
    <li>To determine trends of adverse events over time</li>
    <li>To understand side-effects and their potential impact on the benefit-risk analysis.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>PMS activities should include an analysis of adverse events relating to both the subject device and similar devices, as those relating to similar devices are likely to apply to the subject device.</p>
  <h2 id="sources-of-adverse-events-data">Sources of adverse events data</h2>
  <p>The monitoring of post-market surveillance data will be possible through the EUDAMED Vigilance module, which is under development and will be released when EUDAMED is declared fully functional. Use of this module will become mandatory from Q4 2027.</p>
  <p>Until then, adverse event report searches will rely on country-specific vigilance databases. Even following the deployment of the EUDAMED Vigilance module, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">manufacturers</a> will still need to monitor other vigilance databases “in a manner that is proportionate to the risk class and appropriate for the type of device”. (EU MDR Chapter VII, Section 1, Article 83).</p>
  <p>The following databases are all commonly used by medical device manufacturers for Post-Market Surveillance activities:</p>
  <h3 id="us-maude"><a href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfmaude/search.cfm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US MAUDE</a></h3>
  <p>The largest database of vigilance data and an excellent resource to utilise. MAUDE offers the ability to search for adverse event reports received from healthcare professionals, patients, and manufacturers, as well as Field Safety Notices. It’s an extremely comprehensive database that can result in thousands of results, meaning that reviewers need a plan and some dedicated time to review and analyse. The site also contains a disclaimer that, because of the risk of duplicate entries, MAUDE shouldn’t be used to assess frequency of events.</p>
  <h3 id="uk-mhra"><a href="https://www.gov.uk/drug-device-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UK MHRA</a></h3>
  <p>The MHRA allows searches for Field Safety Notices, National Patient Safety Alerts, and device safety information. Search functionality is limited, however, and the format that results are presented in can take up a lot of time. Outputs are as PDF files only, further limiting functionality.</p>
  <h3 id="swissmedic"><a href="https://fsca.swissmedic.ch/mep/#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Swissmedic</a></h3>
  <p>Swissmedic provides an easy to use website with the ability to search for Field Safety Notices only. With excellent search functionality and easy to review results this is a great resource to utilise. Outputs are as PDF files only.</p>
  <h3 id="australian-daen"><a href="https://www.tga.gov.au/safety/safety/safety-monitoring-daen-database-adverse-event-notifications/database-adverse-event-notifications-daen-medicines" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Australian DAEN</a></h3>
  <p>The DAEN database allows searching of adverse event reports. The search function, however, can sometimes be difficult to use. Results can be output into an easy to read PDF document.</p>
  <h3 id="french-ansm"><a href="https://ansm.sante.fr/informations-de-securite/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">French ANSM</a></h3>
  <p>The ANSM website is in French, so an online translator may be helpful here. With a simple to use search function showing Field Safety Notices and device alert information, the French database can provide useful outputs.</p>
  <h3 id="german-bfarm"><a href="https://www.bfarm.de/EN/Medical-devices/Tasks/Risk-assessment-and-research/Field-corrective-actions/_node.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">German BfArM</a></h3>
  <p>The BfArM website is user friendly and responsive, showing predominantly Field Safety Notices. A great resource to utilise for your vigilance searches.</p>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>Adverse event data is a vital component of a clinical evaluation and post market surveillance. With such a wide range of sources available to collect this information from, appropriate planning and time should be allocated to this task.</p>
  <p>Need further information on vigilance database searches? Interested to hear more about Mantra Systems’ Clinical Evaluation Report Writing service, which includes a vigilance database search as standard? <a href="/contact">Contact us</a> for a free, impartial and no obligation discussion with a member of our team.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>simon-cumiskey</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We discuss the pros and cons of existing adverse event databases for vigilance data searching.]]></summary></entry></feed>