<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-12T10:59:40+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?" /><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T10:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp"><![CDATA[<p>In this article, we provide a brief overview of the Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP) process, a regulatory requirement applicable for high-risk implantable and class III devices under the EU MDR.</p>
      <h2 id="what-is-summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">What is Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)?</h2>
      <p>The <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">Summary of Safety and Clinical Performance (SSCP)</a> is an entirely new document requirement introduced by the MDR. According to article 32 of the MDR regulation (MDR (EU) 2017/745), manufacturers are required to produce an SSCP for high risk implantable and class III medical devices (except custom-made or investigational devices).</p>
      <p>An SSCP is unique in its structure and format. It is written specifically for medical device end users, including both healthcare professionals and, if applicable, patients. If the SSCP contains information for both healthcare professionals and patients, the document should include distinct and easily identifiable sections for each audience.</p>
      <p>All SSCPs are required to be submitted to a recognised notified body for validation. Unlike other technical documents, the SSCP will be published for public access in the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">EUDAMED</a> database by the notified body after validation.</p>
      <h2 id="when-do-you-need-an-sscp-and-what-are-its-objectives">When do you need an SSCP and what are its objectives?</h2>
      <p>If you are a manufacturer of high-risk implantable devices, such as an arterial stent or vitreous implant, or class III devices such as breast implants or total or partial joint replacements, and wish to comply with the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:02017R0745-20170505" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDR (EU) 2017/745</a>, you must produce an SSCP for your devices.</p>
      <p>The main objective of the SSCP is to provide clinical data and other information concerning the safety and clinical effectiveness of the medical device and to make it accessible to the general public in an appropriate form. This will allow healthcare professionals to make more informed decisions about patient treatment, and enable the patients to look into the devices recommended by their healthcare providers.</p>
      <p>The SSCP must summarise both favourable and unfavourable data regarding the safety and clinical effectiveness of the device; that is, it is meant not only to demonstrate that the device is safe and effective, but also to highlight residual risks and potential safety or performance concerns and how these have been mitigated.</p>
      <p>However, the SSCP is not intended to be used in place of the IFU or implant cards associated with the medical device. It is also not meant to provide comprehensive advice on the diagnosis and treatment of specific medical conditions. The public access of SSCP via EUDAMED will also enable users to form a direct comparison of the subject device and similar alternative devices based on available clinical evidence.</p>
      <h2 id="what-support-is-available-when-writing-an-sscp">What support is available when writing an SSCP?</h2>
      <p>Being a publicly available document and an entirely new requirement under the MDR, the SSCP may present challenges to the manufacturers. It is important to become familiar with official guidance such as that published in <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2022-03/md_mdcg_2019_9_sscp_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG-2019-9 Rev 1</a>.</p>
      <p>However, as a new document type, it is also advisable to consider seeking professional advice and consulting support. <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/summary-of-safety-and-clinical-performance-sscp">Mantra Systems offers a complete SSCP service</a> (including writing and readability testing), alongside a range of training resources and templates through the <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE platform</a>.</p>
      <p><b>If you have any questions about SSCPs and our range of support services, <a href="/contact">contact our team</a> for a free, no obligation discussion.</b></p>
      ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="SSCP" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We explain what the SSCP is, when you'll need it and what its objectives are.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Validity Reports – Foundation of the IVDR Performance Evaluation</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports-foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Validity Reports – Foundation of the IVDR Performance Evaluation" /><published>2023-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T13:13:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports%E2%80%93foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/scientific-validity-reports-foundation-of-the-ivdr-performance-evaluation"><![CDATA[<p>A Performance Evaluation Report (PER) is a cornerstone of any submission under the IVDR. In this series of articles, we break down the three major components of a PER and outline their purpose and requirements, starting with the Scientific Validity Report.</p>
    <h2 id="what-is-scientific-validity">What is scientific validity?</h2>
    <p>Scientific validity is defined as the <q>“association of an analyte with a clinical condition or a physiological state”</q>. It is a component of clinical evidence collection which is required for the performance evaluation of an <i>in vitro</i> medical device under the IVDR.</p>
    <p>The evidence to prove scientific validity is presented in the Scientific Validity Report (SVR), a supporting document for the PER.</p>
    <p><b>‘Performance evaluation’</b> of an <i>in vitro</i> medical device is an assessment and analysis of data to establish or verify the scientific validity, analytical and, where applicable, the clinical performance of a device (Source: <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746&amp;qid=1698152662286" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EU IVDR 2017/746. Section 1, Article 2 (44)</a>).</p>
    <p>Establishing the scientific validity of an analyte is the first and most important step when generating the argument as to why an IVD is considered to be state of the art and suitable to fulfil its intended purpose.</p>
    <h2 id="what-type-of-evidence-is-required-to-establish-scientific-validity">What type of evidence is required to establish scientific validity?</h2>
    <p>In order to demonstrate scientific validity, <a href="https://www.imdrf.org/sites/default/files/docs/ghtf/final/sg5/technical-docs/ghtf-sg5-n7-2012-scientific-validity-determination-evaluation-121102.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">guidance has been provided</a> on the potential sources of source(s) of information to be used:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Information on IVD medical devices that measure the same analyte and with the same intended use that have marketing history (e.g. Instructions for Use).</li>
      <li>Systematic literature review: peer reviewed articles, regulatory guidance documents, conference proceedings, etc.</li>
      <li>Review of expert opinions: textbooks, clinical guidance documents, position statements from academic and professional organisations.</li>
      <li>Results from proof of concept studies: smaller scale scientific studies to identify the fundamental association of the analyte with the clinical condition/physiological state.</li>
      <li>Results from clinical performance studies.</li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="what-should-be-included-in-the-systematic-literature-review">What should be included in the systematic literature review?</h2>
    <p>A state-of-the-art literature review, according to MedDev 2.7/1 Rev 4, describes what is currently and generally considered to be standard of care or best practice for the medical condition or treatment for which the device is used. The systematic literature review will be used to find data to evidence the state of the art, in accordance with the intended purpose of the IVD under evaluation.</p>
    <p>This literature search should include information on the medical conditions associated with the test, the alternative diagnostic options available, the target populations for the test as per the intended purpose, any risks associated with the technology used and specific details about the analyte and the test.</p>
    <p>A systematic literature search for competitor devices is also necessary in order to determine performance outcomes which can be used to determine acceptance criteria, against which the subject device will be compared.</p>
    <p>The evidence for scientific validity has to be appraised for its relevance and quality, with references, justifications and conclusions and presented in a Scientific Validity Report (SVR).</p>
    <h2 id="what-if-my-analyte-or-assay-has-a-well-established-connection-to-a-clinical-condition">What if my analyte or assay has a well-established connection to a clinical condition?</h2>
    <p>The definition of performance evaluation given above mentions the requirement to <i>‘establish <b>or verify</b>’</i> the scientific validity. This means that if the analyte has a well-established and recognised association with a clinical condition (e.g. the association of haemoglobin levels with anaemia), there will be no need to provide as much evidence as perhaps a new analyte, or a new intended purpose.</p>
    <p><a href="https://www.bsigroup.com/globalassets/localfiles/en-th/Medical%20devices/whitepapers/performance-evaluation-under-ivdr-th.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to guidance from the notified body BSI</a>, for well-established assays, a description of clinical guidelines or published evidence will be enough. However, with a newly developed analyte which perhaps has limited published evidence, there may be a need for the manufacturer to provide their own evidence, such as proof-of-concept studies or clinical performance studies.</p>
    <h2 id="do-all-ivds-require-scientific-validity-to-support-clinical-evidence">Do all IVDs require scientific validity to support clinical evidence?</h2>
    <p>If the device under evaluation is Class A or a calibrator, it may not require the demonstration of scientific validity. If the device does not perform the test itself, it will be necessary to explain and justify, in the Performance Evaluation Plan (PEP), why scientific validity is not applicable for this specific device. It will, however, be necessary to explain that the scientific validity of the associated assay is valid. Therefore, an SVR is needed to describe the association of the analyte for the assay(s) it is supporting.</p>
    <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
    <p>Scientific Validity is a crucial component of the clinical evidence required under the IVDR. It provides the clinical background and context for the environment in which the IVD operates and is necessary to determine performance criteria against which to compare the IVD under evaluation. A methodical, detailed and documented approach to the state-of-the-art literature review will result in a well-evidenced and robust claim of scientific validity.</p>
    <p><b>Need further information on producing a Scientific Validity Report? <a href="/contact">Contact Mantra Systems</a> for a free, impartial and no obligation discussion with a member of our team. </b></p>
    ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Justifying scientific validity is the first step in proving compliance with the IVDR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2023</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mantra Systems at MEDICA 2023" /><published>2023-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mantra-systems-at-medica-2023"><![CDATA[<p>Mantra Systems is looking forward to attending <a href="https://www.medica-tradefair.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MEDICA 2023</a> - a prestigious international medical trade fair held on 13th - 16th November in Düsseldorf, Germany.</p>
  <p>With over 5,500 exhibitors from 66 countries and more than 81,000 visitors worldwide, MEDICA stands as one of the largest medical B2B trade fairs in the world. The event presents the entire spectrum of innovations from various companies and organisations for outpatient and clinical care.</p>
  <p>As the global medical device landscape continues to evolve, staying at the forefront of medical device innovation is paramount for companies committed to advancing healthcare solutions.</p>
  <p>The event will showcase innovation in the 5 spheres of MEDICA; these are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Medical Technology and Devices</li>
    <li>Digital Health</li>
    <li>Lab &amp; Diagnostics</li>
    <li>Physio Tech</li>
    <li>Disposables &amp; Consumables</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Alongside MEDICA, <a href="https://www.compamed-tradefair.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COMPAMED</a>, an international trade fair for the medical technology supplier sector will also be happening in Düsseldorf.</p>
  <p>COMPAMED offers a comprehensive range of high-quality medical technology components, services and production equipment for the medical industry. There will be over 800 exhibitors presenting the latest innovations in components, modules, OEM equipment, electrical and electronic components, microtechnology, raw materials, materials and adhesives, manufacturing of components, manufacturing of finished products, services and manufacturing equipment.</p>
  <h2 id="the-significance-of-medica-a-global-hub-for-medical-innovation">The significance of MEDICA: A global hub for medical innovation</h2>
  <p>MEDICA serves as a melting pot of innovation, bringing together leading minds, cutting-edge technologies, and groundbreaking solutions in the medical field. This year’s event promises to showcase a diverse array of products and services spanning medical imaging, laboratory technology, diagnostics, health IT, mobile health, physiotherapy/orthopaedic technology, and medical consumables. With a staggering number of exhibitors and visitors, the trade fair provides an unparalleled platform to explore the latest trends and developments shaping the future of healthcare.</p>
  <p>Each year, distinguished figures from the realms of business, research, and politics grace the prestigious event with their attendance, alongside tens of thousands of industry experts and decision-makers from both national and international spheres, making MEDICA an excellent opportunity to exchange with experts from all over the world.</p>
  <h2 id="why-medical-innovation-matters-a-glimpse-into-the-future">Why medical innovation matters: A glimpse into the future</h2>
  <p>In the dynamic realm of healthcare, innovation plays a pivotal role in improving patient outcomes, enhancing diagnostics, and revolutionizing treatment modalities. As medical technology continues to advance, it opens new frontiers for personalized and more effective healthcare solutions. From state-of-the-art imaging technologies to cutting-edge health IT systems, the innovations showcased at MEDICA 2023 will underscore the transformative power of technology in the medical sector.</p>
  <h2 id="our-presence-at-medica-2023">Our presence at MEDICA 2023</h2>
  <p>For those attending MEDICA 2023, we invite you to connect with our representatives during the event. As a specialised medical device regulatory consultancy, we are eager to share insights, discuss regulatory challenges, and explore collaborative opportunities.</p>
  <p>Whether you are navigating the complexities of market entry, compliance, or Post-Market Surveillance, our team is here to assist in ensuring your medical devices meet the highest regulatory standards. Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> to arrange a free consultation.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shen-may-khoo</name></author><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mantra Systems is going to MEDICA 2023, the largest medical trade fair in the world. We hope to see you there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1" /><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T12:23:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3"><![CDATA[<p>With the transition to the EU MDR, legacy devices with certificates issued under the old EU directives (Directive 93/42/EEC on medical devices, MDD, and Directive 90/385/EEC on active implantable medical devices, AIMDD) can stay on the market under the transitional provisions set out in Article 120(3) of the MDR, provided they do not undergo any <b>significant changes</b>.</p>
  <p>In this article, we explain the concept of a ‘significant change’ and, using examples, help you understand whether you can still take advantage of the transitional arrangements in MDR Article 120(3).</p>
  <h2 id="transition-periods">Transition periods</h2>
  <p>The transition periods in Article 120(3) MDR as per Regulation (EU) 2023/607 are as follows:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Class III and IIb implants: new transition period until 31 December 2027</li>
    <li>Class IIb and lower: new transition period until 31 December 2028</li>
    <li>Class III custom-made products: new transition period until 31 December 2026</li>
    <li>No ‘sell-off’ deadline</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="what-does-significant-change-mean">What does significant change mean?</h2>
  <p>A significant change in the design or intended purpose consists of two cumulative elements:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>There is a change in the design or intended purpose, <b>and</b></li>
    <li>The change is significant</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Therefore, changes that do not concern the design or intended purpose are out of scope of Article 120(3) of the MDR. Changes that concern the design or intended purpose only fall under Article 120(3) if they are considered ‘significant’.</p>
  <h2 id="responsibilities-of-medical-device-manufacturers-regarding-significance-of-changes">Responsibilities of medical device manufacturers regarding ‘significance’ of changes</h2>
  <p>Medical device manufacturers have two primary responsibilities regarding changes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>provide evidence and justification that a change does not affect the design or intended purpose, or</li>
    <li>in cases where the change affects the design or intended purpose of the device, that it is non-significant.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The outcome of this assessment should be documented and made available to a competent authority when requested.</p>
  <p>If a change to a legacy device is not a significant change in design or intended purpose, it can be implemented using the above transitional arrangement. In these instances, manufacturers must adhere to the documentation criteria of AIMDD/MDD, meaning that the revised technical documentation must enable the evaluation of the product’s compliance with the relevant standards.</p>
  <h2 id="determining-a-significant-change-to-the-design-or-intended-purpose">Determining a significant change to the design or intended purpose</h2>
  <p>The <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a> guidance document sets out whether a change in the design or intended purpose of a device is considered ‘significant’ within the meaning of EU MDR Article 120(3c), point (b).</p>
  <p><b>Examples of changes in design and/or intended purpose that are ‘non-significant’:</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Changes related to corrective actions assessed and accepted by the competent authority</li>
    <li>Correction of spelling mistakes or merely editorial changes of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label or instructions for use)</li>
    <li>Clarifications of intended purpose, population, or clinical application in the information to be supplied with the device in line with the original certification</li>
    <li>Updates of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label, instructions for use or implant card) if they are required by EU legislation other than the MDR, are mere clarifications and do not adversely affect the devices’ safety and performance in relation to existing or new risks</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The following diagram, taken from the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a>, helps understand when <b>changes in design and/or intended purpose may be considered ‘significant’</b>:</p>
  <figure class="inline">
    <div class="image bordered">
      <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/significant-changes-main-chart.png" alt="Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart" loading="lazy" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart taken from <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a></figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>Charts A to E in the MDCG guideline contain specific areas where changes in the intended purpose, device design, device software, changes related to a substance or material or changes related to sterilisation are likely to be held to be significant. It’s vital to consult these charts when understanding whether a change will be significant and, by extension, whether your device can make use of the transitional arrangement.</p>
  <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
  <p>The definition of a “significant change” involves two cumulative elements: a change in design or intended purpose that is deemed significant. Manufacturers bear the responsibility of determining and justifying whether a change in their medical device is significant or not, and therefore whether relevant technical documents require updating in line with the changes. The MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1 guidance document provides guidance on determining the significance of changes in design or intended purpose.</p>
  <p>For further information regarding how we can meet your MDR requirements, including advice on whether changes are likely to be significant, <b>please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free and confidential discussion.</b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shen-may-khoo</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand what changes to your medical device are considered 'significant' under EU MDR (2017/745).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?" /><published>2023-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T12:23:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry"><![CDATA[<p>Medical devices and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices are like twin cities on different continents - both serving the needs of modern medicine, both highly regulated and, following the advent of updated legislation in Europe, governed by parallel legislation. However, sometimes the distinction between the two is less clear than might be thought.</p>
  <p>In this article, we unpick the differences between these two categories of product and explore requirements for gaining and maintaining market access for these device types.</p>
  <h2 id="is-my-product-regulated-by-the-mdr-or-the-ivdr">Is my product regulated by the MDR or the IVDR?</h2>
  <p>The now well-known <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745 (MDR)</a> and the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746&amp;qid=1698152662286" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i>In Vitro</i> Diagnostic Medical Devices Regulation (EU) 2017/746 (IVDR)</a> were developed to improve the regulatory framework which oversees products placed on the market in the EU.</p>
  <p>There are many similarities between the two Regulations in terms of quality management, risk management, risk based classification and post market surveillance. Despite the areas of overlap between them, it is essential for manufacturers to correctly categorise their product as a medical device or as an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (IVD) in order to demonstrate the applicable compliance with EU rules.</p>
  <h2 id="basic-definitions">Basic definitions</h2>
  <p>The definition of a medical device (Article 2 (1) MDR):</p>
  <blockquote class="standard">
    <p>'medical device' means any instrument, apparatus, appliance, software, implant, reagent, material or other article intended by the manufacturer to be used, alone or in combination, for human beings for one or more of the following specific medical purposes:</p>
    <ul class="disc">
      <li>diagnosis, prevention, monitoring, prediction, prognosis, treatment or alleviation of disease,</li>
      <li>diagnosis, monitoring, treatment, alleviation of, or compensation for, an injury or disability,</li>
      <li>investigation, replacement or modification of the anatomy or of a physiological or pathological process or state,</li>
      <li>providing information by means of <i>in vitro</i> examination of specimens derived from the human body, including organ, blood and tissue donations,</li>
    </ul>
    <p>and which does not achieve its principal intended action by pharmacological, immunological or metabolic means, in or on the human body, but which may be assisted in its function by such means.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>Examples of medical devices include surgical implants, wheelchairs, disposable gloves, pacemakers and infusion pumps.</p>
  <p>Indent 4 of the definition above includes medical devices which <i>‘provide information by means of in vitro examination of specimens.’</i> However, Article 1(6) MDR specifically states that the Regulation <strong>does not apply</strong> to <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices covered by Regulation (EU) 2017/746. Therefore, an IVD can be seen as a subset of the medical device family, but with its own governing Regulation IVDR (EU) 2017/746.</p>
  <p>The definition of an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (Article 2 (2) IVDR):</p>
  <blockquote class="standard">
    <p>'<i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device' means any medical device which is a reagent, reagent product, calibrator, control material, kit, instrument, apparatus, piece of equipment, software or system, whether used alone or in combination, intended by the manufacturer to be used <i>in vitro</i> for the examination of specimens, including blood and tissue donations, derived from the human body, solely or principally for the purpose of providing information on one or more of the following:</p>
    <ol class="lower-alpha">
      <li>concerning a physiological or pathological process or state</li>
      <li>concerning congenital physical or mental impairments</li>
      <li>concerning the predisposition to a medical condition or a disease</li>
      <li>to determine the safety and compatibility with potential recipients</li>
      <li>to predict treatment response or reaction</li>
      <li>to define or monitor therapeutic measures</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Specimen receptacles are also deemed to be <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <p>Examples of IVDs include laboratory machines which screen for infectious agents, compatibility for blood or tissue such as ABO or Rhesus and genetic tests. Self-tests for pregnancy, blood sugar and cholesterol are included in the definition. Companion diagnostics, where a device is specifically linked to a medicinal product to evaluate therapeutic response, are also categorised as IVDs.</p>
  <h2 id="patient-vs-sample">Patient vs Sample</h2>
  <p>An exclusion of the IVDR is any <i>‘invasive sampling products or products which are directly applied to the human body for the purpose of obtaining a specimen’</i>. Patients are not directly in contact with an IVD, other than a self-test IVD, which is not considered invasive. A sample of urine, blood or saliva which is collected from the patient, is then prepared and analysed by an IVD, either as a self-test, near-patient test (such as a hospital room) or in a laboratory. The results are then used for the management of the patient along with other therapeutic options.</p>
  <p>A device which obtains a sample from the patient in an invasive way such as a spinal needle for CSF collection or a punch biopsy for a tissue sample, falls under the medical device umbrella.</p>
  <h2 id="blurred-lines">Blurred lines</h2>
  <p>Of course, there may be cases where a product is a combination of a medical device and an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device. Both regulations are clear in this situation (as stated in Article 1 (4) IVDR and Article 1 (7) MDR).</p>
  <p>Any medical device which incorporates, as an integral part, an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device, shall be governed by the MDR, while the IVDR will apply to the <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic part of the device. The manufacturer will then have to meet both regulatory requirements in order to gain a CE mark for the combined device.</p>
  <h2 id="in-a-nutshell">In a nutshell</h2>
  <p><i>In vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices are a subcategory of medical devices with their own regulatory framework IVDR (EU) 2017/746. Although there is considerable overlap with the MDR (EU) 2017/745, it is imperative to categorise the product correctly from the beginning of the EU market access journey.</p>
  <p><b>For further information regarding compliance with the EU MDR or IVDR, <a href="/contact">contact Mantra Systems</a> for a FREE and open discussion.</b></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A guide to easily understanding whether your device is a medical device or an in vitro diagnostic medical device (IVD).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What the latest Brexit U-turn means for CE Marking of medical devices in Great Britain</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the latest Brexit U-turn means for CE Marking of medical devices in Great Britain" /><published>2023-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain"><![CDATA[<p>The UK Department for Business and Trade (DBT) announced on 1st August 2023 that <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-government-announces-extension-of-ce-mark-recognition-for-businesses">CE safety marking of products for businesses is to continue indefinitely in the UK</a>, beyond the 2024 deadline.</p>
  <p>Following the departure of the UK from the European Union in 2016, UKCA marking was to replace the CE mark, along with changes to the process of medical device regulation. Several extensions to the transitional arrangements have already been made, with the latest deadline for mandatory use of the UKCA mark being the 30th June 2024.</p>
  <p>Due to issues surrounding the burden of these changes on businesses and impact on economic growth, the DBT has consulted with industry professionals and will now allow the continued use of the CE mark alongside the UKCA. For the time being, this update refers to 18 regulations it will apply to (that fall under the DBT), of which medical devices has not been included.</p>
  <p><b>The regulations stated are as follows:</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>toys</li>
    <li>pyrotechnics</li>
    <li>recreational craft and personal watercraft</li>
    <li>simple pressure vessels</li>
    <li>electromagnetic compatibility</li>
    <li>non-automatic weighing instruments</li>
    <li>measuring instruments</li>
    <li>measuring container bottles</li>
    <li>lifts</li>
    <li>equipment for potentially explosive atmospheres (ATEX)</li>
    <li>radio equipment</li>
    <li>pressure equipment</li>
    <li>personal protective equipment (PPE)</li>
    <li>gas appliances</li>
    <li>machinery</li>
    <li>equipment for use outdoors</li>
    <li>aerosols</li>
    <li>low voltage electrical equipment</li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Whether medical device regulation will be impacted is yet to be confirmed</b>, although given the current trend in extensions made to the transition deadline, it would not be a surprise if it were to follow suit. To date, no update has been provided by the MHRA regarding this matter.</p>
  <p>Keep an eye out for an article regarding an update on this topic.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss how we can help you with your CE &amp; UKCA certification in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>hanna-gul</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Will Great Britain continue to allow the use of the CE mark for medical devices beyond the 2024 deadline?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gain confidence, reassurance and control over your EU MDR strategy</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gain confidence, reassurance and control over your EU MDR strategy" /><published>2023-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy"><![CDATA[<p>What if there was a way to save a portion of your regulatory budget by writing your own MDR technical documents? What if you could build your own technical file using proven frameworks and detailed templates, with step-by-step guidance from EU MDR experts?</p>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE from Mantra Systems</a> is a product suite created for medical device manufacturers who would like to take control of their own regulatory processes but are in need of training, support or guidance from regulatory specialists.</p>
  <p>By building your own technical files within a guided framework, unnecessary financial outlays for comprehensive regulatory consulting packages can be minimised.</p>
  <h2 id="the-cost-of-compliance">The cost of compliance</h2>
  <p>With increasing costs across the industry, the requirements to become EU MDR compliant can add significant expense to an already tight balance sheet. Afterall, transitioning to the MDR is costly — <a href="https://www.ukri.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/IUK-171221-UK-SME-MDR-ReadinessFinalReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MedTech Europe estimates</a> compliance costs of 8-15% of revenue from certified devices, which translates into £800K - £1.5M for an SME with revenues of £10M.</p>
  <p>In the MedTech Europe report (commissioned by Innovate UK in September 2019), the readiness of UK small and medium size enterprise (SME) medical device companies for the Regulation (EU) 2017/745, commonly referred to as the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR), was investigated.</p>
  <p>In response to the survey, with less than one year to go to the date of application of the MDR, 60% of medical device manufacturers had not yet budgeted for the MDR. Of the 40% who had, only 12% had provisioned between 8-15% of their impacted sales revenues.</p>
  <p>Regardless of the device classification, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">EU MDR compliance</a> is a labour-intensive and expensive exercise. It requires significantly more in terms of clinical evidence, risk assessments, post market surveillance, supply chain obligations and data for the Unique Device Identification (UDI) system and the new EU Eudamed database.</p>
  <h2 id="enablece--saving-you-time-and-money">EnableCE – saving you time and money</h2>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE</a> was built to give the control of timelines and regulatory budgets back to the medical device manufacturer. Regardless of the degree of assistance you require, there is an EnableCE product for everyone.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-training-courses/">EnableCE Learn</a> provides on-demand training courses by experts, for expert training on driving your own EU MDR strategy.</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/">EnableCE Build</a> provides validated templates, documents and tools to enable you to build your own EU-MDR compliant file, tailor-made for your business.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Mantra Systems is well positioned to be your regulatory partner for <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, guiding and supporting you while you complete your own MDR compliant technical file.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Find out how to build your own technical files within a guided framework while minimising financial outlays.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Still racing to achieve MDR compliance? A transition period update</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Still racing to achieve MDR compliance? A transition period update" /><published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods"><![CDATA[<p>At the EPSCO Board meeting on December 9, 2022, the EU Health Minister urged the European Commission to extend the transition period for the Medical Device Regulation. The proposal was under consideration of the European Parliament and the Council.</p>
  <p><strong>On January 6th 2023, the EU commission has adopted the proposal to extend the transition rules of Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745 (MDR)</strong> to allow more time for certification and to alleviate the foreseeable shortage of medical devices.</p>
  <h2 id="status-quo">Status quo</h2>
  <p>Under transitional arrangements, medical devices are allowed to enter the EU market under CE certifications issued according to Directive 93/42/EEC (MDD) or 90/385/EEC (AIMDD). The previously extended MDR transition time was due to end on 26 May 2024, meaning that after this time devices would require a recertification under MDR.</p>
  <p>Numerous industry stakeholders and key opinion leaders had expressed concerns in recent months that this deadline is unrealistic and that its implementation could have an impact on the continuous availability of different medical devices required by patients and healthcare providers in the EU.</p>
  <p>Moreover, opinions were that the suggested transitional time range could jeopardise research and innovation in addition to availability issues by delaying access to cutting-edge medical devices in EU nations.</p>
  <p>In addition to the strong backlash from stakeholders, limitations in Notified Body capacity was also a significant factor in calls for an extension to the transition period.</p>
  <h2 id="the-proposal">The proposal</h2>
  <p>In order to address the concerns and mitigate foreseeable risks associated with device shortage, the EU commission proposed a longer transition period with new deadlines depending on the medical device’s risk class.</p>
  <p>It is worth noting that the proposal does not alter any of the existing performance and safety standards outlined in the Medical Device Regulation 2017/745. It only amends the transitional provisions to provide additional time to transfer from the formerly applicable norms.</p>
  <h3 id="key-elements-of-the-proposal">Key elements of the proposal:</h3>
  <p class="notice info">The transition periods for medical devices authorised under Directive 93/42/EEC (Medical Device Directive) will now last until 31 December 2027 for high risk (Class III and IIb) devices, until 31 December 2028 for medium and low risk (Class IIa and I) devices and until 26 May 2026 for class III implantable custom-made devices.</p>
  <p>It is important to note that <strong>these extensions are subject to certain conditions</strong>. They are only applicable to devices:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>that are “safe”, that do not pose an unacceptable risk to health &amp; safety</li>
    <li>which have not undergone any significant changes in its intended purpose or design</li>
    <li>those for which manufacturers have already taken steps to transition to the rules provided by MDR</li>
  </ol>
  <p>In case of custom-made devices, the transition period is also subject to the application of the manufacturer for a conformity assessment of the device before 26 May 2024.</p>
  <p class="notice info"><b>Elimination of the "sell-off" date</b> of 26 May 2025 that is currently established in the Medical Device Regulation. The "sell-off" date designates the time after which products that have already been sold and are still on the market should be withdrawn.</p>
  <p>Removing the “sell-off” date will, it is argued, prevent safe medical devices from being removed from the market.</p>
  <h2 id="what-this-means">What this means</h2>
  <p>While it will be warmly welcomed by many, the proposal to delay the transitional period now has to be approved by the European Parliament and the Council through an expedited co-decision process. For this reason, manufacturers are still encouraged to continue working towards compliance with the MDR as soon as possible, as the extension is not a “free pass”.</p>
  <p>Notified Bodies will be still monitoring and auditing compliance during the extension period, and as outlined above, the transition period only applies to devices “for which manufacturers have already taken steps to transition to the rules provided by MDR.” Additionally, for Class III devices, the transition period is subject to the application of the manufacturer for a conformity assessment before 26 May 2024.</p>
  <p>So, whether approved by the European Parliament and Council or not, it’s not time to forget about MDR certification. It may, however, take off some of the pressure.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On January 6th 2023, the EU commission has adopted the proposal to extend the transition rules of the EU MDR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A medical device regulations guide for start-up companies</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A medical device regulations guide for start-up companies" /><published>2023-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups"><![CDATA[<p>Navigating medical device regulatory requirements is a challenge even for established companies. For start-ups, gaining regulatory approval can be a major hurdle, arguably meaning that many promising device concepts fail to reach the market.</p>
  <p>In this article, we present 7-steps for navigating regulatory requirements on a budget. While aimed at pre-revenue companies, these steps may also be useful for established companies seeking to bring new products to market or reduce their regulatory spend.</p>
  <h2 id="step-1---plan-ahead">Step 1 - Plan ahead</h2>
  <p>The worst - but perhaps most common - mistake made by medical device start-ups is to neglect regulatory requirements until the later stages of product development. With some justification, many companies assume that regulatory documents and processes can only meaningfully be compiled once the device design has been finalised.</p>
  <p>The truth is that while some tasks (such as <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>) are better left until the device has reached a level of maturity, others need to be performed from the earliest possible stages of device development. These can be considered foundational systems that form the bedrock of all successful regulatory strategies.</p>
  <h2 id="step-2---build-foundational-systems">Step 2 - Build foundational systems</h2>
  <p>Foundational systems and activities are:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Establishing and maintaining a Quality Management System (QMS)</li>
    <li>Establishing a Risk Management System</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Let’s consider each in turn.</p>
  <h3 id="1-qms---control-quality-from-the-earliest-stages">1. QMS - Control quality from the earliest stages</h3>
  <p>When it comes to obtaining final approval for your devices, you will be required to produce evidence that device design was conducted according to an established quality framework. It is essentially impossible to do this in retrospect, so it’s vital to set up a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">Quality Management System (QMS)</a> as early as possible. While often thought of as expensive and complex, the truth is that an early-stage QMS can be relatively simple if it incorporates important building blocks that will enable it to grow as the company nears market entry.</p>
  <p>Basic principles include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Adopting a process-driven framework</li>
    <li>Documenting processes and maintaining records</li>
    <li>Controlling documents and records</li>
    <li>Establishing a Quality Policy and Quality Objectives</li>
    <li>Defining roles and responsibilities</li>
    <li>Writing a Quality manual</li>
    <li>Having an effective <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-document-management/">Document Management System</a></li>
    <li>Ensuring that suppliers and third parties operate in accordance with your QMS</li>
  </ul>
  <p>ISO 13485:2016 is the international standard for Quality Management Systems for medical devices and, ultimately, your QMS will almost certainly need to adhere to its requirements. It’s advisable to obtain a copy as early as possible and begin structuring your activities accordingly. If nothing else, basic considerations are to set objectives, keep records, allocate responsibilities, monitor outcomes and, where necessary, conduct corrective actions. Good habits from the earliest stages will make the development of a definitive QMS much easier as the company matures.</p>
  <h3 id="2-risk-management---the-key-to-successful-product-design">2. Risk Management - The key to successful product design</h3>
  <p>It is easy to think of medical device Risk Management as just another administrative burden standing between you and regulatory approval. However, the truth is that an effective approach to <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk Management</a> has, amongst other benefits, a direct bearing on successful medical device design, helping your product differentiate from competitors through a unique (and commercially successful) solution.</p>
  <p>An effective approach to Risk Analysis may indicate that changes to the device’s design are necessary to mitigate identified risks. While this is relatively easy during the early stages of device design, it may be extremely difficult later on - especially if manufacturing infrastructure has been established for the design and if user tests or clinical trials will need to be repeated following changes.</p>
  <p>For these reasons, it’s imperative to begin Risk Management as early as possible. Odds are that the correct approach (based on ISO 14971:2019) will reveal risks that hadn’t previously been considered. Furthermore, you may uncover disadvantages to existing solutions, enabling additional innovation to further differentiate your product.</p>
  <p>Correct conduct of Risk Management - especially in the early stages - needn’t be expensive or complex. The Mantra Systems <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE Toolkit</a> offers a complete, easy to follow start-to-finish guide to building an ISO 14971:2019-compliant risk management system from scratch. The course is suitable for anyone and is complemented by a full package of <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/risk-management-templates">Risk Management document templates</a> to ensure correct documentation and traceability.</p>
  <h2 id="step-3---know-your-objectives">Step 3 - Know your objectives</h2>
  <p>When building a successful regulatory strategy, it’s vital to know what your objectives are. In other words, you need to define what you are hoping to demonstrate compliance with, which in turn will inform how compliance will be achieved and demonstrated.</p>
  <p>Key considerations are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Specifying a clear intended purpose for the device</li>
    <li>Understanding which legislative requirements apply (GSPRs or ERs, depending on framework)</li>
    <li>What risks need to be mitigated or avoided (an output from Risk Management activities)</li>
    <li>The Quality Policy and Quality Objectives that must be addressed by the device</li>
  </ul>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="RxyKV003WaY"></div>
    <p class="video-caption"><b>Video 1:</b> How to work with Annex I from the EU MDR</p>
  </div>
  <p>While legislative requirements (such as GSPRs) are imposed by law, the intended purpose is (within reason) entirely down to the manufacturer’s preference. It is therefore vital to think about intended purpose very early in the device’s development. A <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">systematic literature review</a> of the clinical field may help define scope of the intended purpose, as well as further defining weaknesses in competing solutions.</p>
  <p>Performing an early analysis of legislative requirements (such as the EU MDR Annex I GSPRs) for relevance to the product will define what additional requirements must be met; in turn, this will help define what pre-clinical and clinical testing needs to be conducted to demonstrate compliance. Please watch our video which explains <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxyKV003WaY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how to analyse the MDR Annex I GSPRs for relevance</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="step-4---get-technical">Step 4 - Get technical</h2>
  <p>MDR Annexes II and III set out requirements for a range of additional technical documents that must be produced for each device. In outline, Annex II technical documents include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>General device description &amp; specification</li>
    <li>Information to be supplied by the manufacturer</li>
    <li>Design &amp; manufacturing information</li>
    <li>General Safety &amp; Performance Requirements (GSPRs)</li>
    <li>Verification &amp; Validation information</li>
    <li>Risk assessment</li>
    <li>Declaration of Conformity</li>
  </ul>
  <p>If you follow the framework in this article, you will already have addressed section 4 and much of section 6. For the others, the key is to start early and keep contemporaneous records of document updates and revisions.</p>
  <p>Section 7 (Declaration of Conformity) is the only one that should be left until the end. To ensure correct structuring of Annex II technical documents (and to avoid excluding vital information), the <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/annex-ii-templates">EnableCE Annex II template pack</a> includes everything you need.</p>
  <p>MDR Annex III primarily concerns <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) activities</a>. While a new device won’t have any PMS data, it’s imperative that you specify how PMS activities will be conducted in a PMS Plan.</p>
  <h2 id="step-5---prove-it">Step 5 - Prove it</h2>
  <p>Securing regulatory approval ultimately comes down to one thing: evidence. Can you demonstrate through suitable evidence that your device:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Is suitable for its intended purpose?</li>
    <li>Demonstrates conformity with relevant GSPRs / ERs?</li>
    <li>Has a favourable benefit-risk profile?</li>
    <li>Compares favourably with safety and performance of similar (comparable alternative) devices?</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Because these four questions form the heart of <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, a vital stage in device approval, it’s necessary from foundational stages to consider how you will generate suitable evidence. Depending on the device and the individual requirement, such evidence may include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Proof of adherence to recognised standards (such as ISO 10993 - Biocompatibility)</li>
    <li>Conduct of pre-clinical studies (e.g. on materials properties, packaging integrity, sterility, etc)</li>
    <li>Usability studies</li>
    <li>Clinical studies</li>
  </ul>
  <p>When planning clinical studies, ensure you align with requirements in MDR Annex XV and ISO 14155:2020. Also consider that conduct of clinical studies takes considerable time and, often, money. Which leads us to the next major consideration…</p>
  <h2 id="step-6---budget">Step 6 - Budget</h2>
  <p>There’s no getting away from the fact that gaining regulatory approval will cost money and failure to adequately budget is a common failure point. Contrary to popular belief, investors may be encouraged by a proper consideration of expenses relating to regulatory requirements, since it demonstrates a proper consideration of go-to-market costs.</p>
  <p>The bottom line is: ensure you have enough money set aside. While costs will vary according to device class and complexity, they may run anywhere from £25,000 to £250,000 and beyond, especially if the device requires complex clinical trials.</p>
  <p>The <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE Toolkit</a> offers an innovative supported do-it-yourself approach that can really help to control budget. The toolkit combines training resources, document templates and a full document management system, enabling you to develop a full technical document portfolio without the added costs of outsourcing. It’s a unique resource that is perfect for cash-strapped start-ups, alongside established companies looking to reduce outsourcing requirements.</p>
  <h2 id="step-7---get-in-the-queue">Step 7 - Get in the queue</h2>
  <p>One final consideration is that <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Bodies</a> (and UK Approved Bodies) are currently stretched beyond capacity, meaning that gaining access for conformity assessments is taking much longer than would be preferred. While there’s no shortcut to this, the message is to start conversations early, seeing if you can get ‘in the queue’ ahead of time. Note, however, that you do need to be ready should availability arise, so play it carefully.</p>
  <h2 id="further-help">Further help</h2>
  <p>Mantra Systems offers a range of products and services to support start-ups on their journey through regulatory compliance. These include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/mdready-starter-guide">MDReady</a> - A free starter guide to MDR compliance</li>
    <li><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">EU MDR Compliance Guide</a> - A free compendium of all aspects of working with the EU MDR</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-training-courses/">EnableCE Training Courses</a> providing detailed guidance on key aspects of regulatory compliance</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/">EnableCE Document Templates</a> for Annex II technical documents, Risk Management, CERs, CEPs and more</li>
    <li>A <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/gap-analysis-tool">Gap Analysis tool</a> helping you identify key deficiencies in your regulatory system</li>
    <li>A cost-effective <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-document-management/">Document Management System</a> for effective version control, access control and secure document storage</li>
    <li>A range of consulting services including <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/post-market-clinical-follow-up">PMCF</a> and <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">systematic literature reviews</a> giving you access to our worldwide network of clinical and regulatory specialists</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>paul-hercock</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We present a 7-step guide to navigating regulatory requirements on a budget.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UKCA Marking of Medical Devices – An update on the status quo</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices-an-update-on-the-status-quo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UKCA Marking of Medical Devices – An update on the status quo" /><published>2022-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:23:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices%E2%80%93an-update-on-the-status-quo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices-an-update-on-the-status-quo"><![CDATA[<p>UKCA (United Kingdom Conformity Assessed) marking of medical devices was due to become mandatory in July 2023, placing medical device manufacturers under real pressure to ensure they were in alignment with UK requirements.</p>
  <p>However, due to delays in processing applications and introducing the new medical device regulatory framework, the MHRA have just announced that they will be <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementation-of-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-and-extension-of-standstill-period/implementation-of-the-future-regulations">extending the UKCA implementation deadline to July 2024</a>. This comes as a welcome relief to medical device manufacturers, who now have more time to ensure that they are adequately prepared for this transition.</p>
  <p>The availability of more time is not a reason to put UKCA to the back of collective minds however. Rather, it’s an opportunity to take stock and ensure that a UKCA strategy is properly developed and implemented well before the new deadline.</p>
  <p>In this article, we review updated requirements for UKCA marking and what they mean for manufacturers.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-a-ukca-mark">What is a UKCA mark?</h2>
  <p>Following Great Britain’s exit from the EU single market in December 2020, CE (Conformité Européenne) marking was to be replaced by the UKCA mark for medical devices marketed in the territory. The UKCA mark is a mandatory mark on a product which indicates that it conforms to the new GB legislation and operates in much the same way as a CE mark in Europe.</p>
  <p>The manufacturer or, if mandated, their authorised representative is responsible for affixing a UKCA mark to the product, assuming they are authorised to do so following a conformity process.</p>
  <h2 id="where-will-it-apply">Where will it apply?</h2>
  <p>The UKCA mark only applies in Great Britain (England, Scotland and Wales). CE marking will continue in Northern Ireland (NI) as it remains aligned with the EU single market for goods. Products that will be placed on the market in both GB and NI will therefore need both UKCA and CE marking unless they are “Qualifying Northern Ireland Goods”, in which case they can be sold in GB with a CE mark and do not need a UKCA mark.</p>
  <h2 id="are-there-any-differences-between-ukca-and-ce-marking">Are there any differences between UKCA and CE marking?</h2>
  <p>As of today, two different legal frameworks exist to obtain UKCA/CE marking for a product, dependent on whether it is marketed in the UK or the EU, respectively. In the UK, the regulations are based on the old Medical Device Directive (MDD), implemented into domestic law by the UK Medical Device Regulations 2002 (UK MDR 2002). Prior to the end of the transition period, this gave effect in UK law to the following Directives:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01990L0385-20071011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 90/385/EEC</a> on active implantable medical devices (EU AIMDD)</li>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01993L0042-20071011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 93/42/EEC</a> on medical devices (EU MDD)</li>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01998L0079-20120111" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 98/79/EC</a> on in vitro diagnostic medical devices (EU IVDD)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Because the Brexit transition period ended before the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:02017R0745-20170505" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745</a> came into effect, the European MDR has not been adopted in the UK, unlike in Europe where it is now mandatory to comply with MDR 2017/745 to obtain a medical device CE mark. This means that the Great Britain route to market and UKCA marking requirements are still officially based on the requirements in the MDD.</p>
  <p>Moving forwards, this means in principle that companies will need two parallel frameworks to be able to market products in both the UK and EU, hence the need for a transition period. The extended transition period outlined by the MHRA will hopefully lessen the burden of becoming compliant with both systems.</p>
  <h2 id="can-a-product-have-both-ukca-and-ce-marks">Can a product have both UKCA and CE marks?</h2>
  <p>Providing a product fulfils the necessary requirements, it may carry both a UKCA and CE mark. The presence of multiple conformity marks is common on internationally sold products.</p>
  <h2 id="what-uk-legislation-needs-to-be-followed">What UK legislation needs to be followed?</h2>
  <p>The UK government has issued several Statutory Instruments to amend current legislation, including <a href="https://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2019/696/contents/made" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Product Safety and Metrology etc. (Amendment etc.) (EU Exit) Regulations 2019</a> and has now <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-in-the-united-kingdom" target="_blank" rel="noopener">concluded consultation on the UK MDR 2022</a>. The specific details of the new UK medical device framework are yet to be published following the UK government consultation on the proposed changes, which started in 2021. However, the government response in June 2022 highlighted that the new GB medical device regulations will be closely aligned with the 2017 EU Medical Device Regulations.</p>
  <h2 id="when-will-ukca-marking-come-into-force">When will UKCA marking come into force?</h2>
  <p>As previously stated, UKCA marking was due to be enforced from July 2023, in-line with the UK Medical Device Regulations 2022 (UK MDR 2022). However, due to understandable delays with regard to publishing the new regulatory framework and the backlog of applications submitted to notified bodies, the MHRA issued a statement on 21st October 2022 indicating that this will be delayed until July 2024. Since this has not yet been confirmed by law, further updates are expected from the MHRA and will be announced via the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementation-of-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-and-extension-of-standstill-period" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MHRA website</a> in the near future. The UK MDR 2022 will also be updated to reflect these changes.</p>
  <p>It is important to highlight that current and valid CE marks will continue to be accepted in Great Britain until this time point. New legislation on medical device regulation highlighting the transitional arrangements is due to be released by the government in Spring 2023. This will also include new Post-Market Surveillance requirements.</p>
  <p>Manufacturers will be able to continue to place CE marked devices on the GB market after 1 July 2023. From July 2024, the transitional arrangements will apply for CE and UKCA marked devices placed on the GB market. Where third party conformity assessment is required, a UK Approved Body is needed. However, manufacturers of non-sterile and non-measuring Class I devices and general IVDs can self-certify against the UKCA marking.</p>
  <p>The government’s June 2022 response has indicated that there will be generous transitional periods in the new medical device framework. These arrangements would allow products to be placed on the market as follows:</p>
  <ol>
    <li><b>General medical devices</b> - until either the certificate expires or for three years after the new regulations take effect (whichever occurred sooner) and</li>
    <li><b>In-vitro Diagnostics (IVDs)</b> - until either the certificate expires or five years after the new regulations take effect (whichever is sooner)</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Transitional provisions would not apply if there were significant changes in the design or intended purpose of the device. Furthermore, all products that will benefit from transitional arrangements will need to comply with post-market requirements. The below schematic illustrates the updated timeline for UKCA marking.</p>
  <h2 id="updated-ukca-timline">Updated UKCA timline</h2>
  <div class="general-wrap">
    <ul class="information row tile info-process">
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b2 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>January 2021</span></h3>
          <p>UKCA marking comes into force.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b3 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>January 2021 to June 2024</span></h3>
          <p>Medical devices &amp; IVD devices can be either CE or UKCA marked (or both).</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b4 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>30th June 2024</span></h3>
          <p>Deadline for medical device &amp; IVD device manufacturers to replace existing CE marks with UKCA mark.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b0 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>1st July 2024</span></h3>
          <p>UKCA mark will be mandatory for all medical devices &amp; IVD devices on the GB market. CE marking will not be recognised.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </div>
  <p class="small-text align-center"><strong>Note:</strong> Current timeline in-line with the MHRA update on 21st October 2022 (maybe subject to change)</p>
  <h2 id="what-needs-immediate-action">What needs immediate action?</h2>
  <p>To ensure that manufacturers are prepared for a smooth transition, in-line with the new timescales for UKCA marking, the following are key requirements for placing a device on the GB market:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>All medical devices, including in-vitro diagnostic medical devices (IVDs), custom-made devices and systems or procedure packs, need to be registered with the MHRA before they are placed on the Great Britain market</li>
    <li>If you are a medical device manufacturer based outside the UK and wish to place a device on the GB market, you need to appoint a single <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/person-responsible-for-regulatory-compliance-prrc">UK Responsible Person</a> for all of your devices, who will act on your behalf to carry out specified tasks, such as registration.</li>
    <li>CE marking will continue to be recognised in Great Britain until 30 June 2024</li>
    <li>Certificates issued by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">EU-recognised Notified Bodies</a> will continue to be valid for the GB market until 30 June 2024</li>
    <li>The EU no longer recognises UK Notified Bodies</li>
    <li>UK Notified Bodies are not able to issue CE certificates - and have become <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/approved-bodies-for-medical-devices" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UK Approved Bodies</a></li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="the-bottom-line">The bottom line</h2>
  <p>The bottom line is – don’t panic! The delay in enforcing UKCA marking is a great opportunity to prepare and re-assess your regulatory strategy so that you are ahead of the game of other competitors in the field. Investing time to get things correct, in-line with new regulations will ensure that your medical devices can continue to be sold and used where they are required most, ultimately leading to improved health outcomes.</p>
  <p>If you require further information you may wish to visit the ‘Useful resources’ section below.</p>
  <p>If you have any concerns about your regulatory strategy that have been brought up in this article, you can <a href="mailto:contact&#64;mantrasystems.co.uk">email us</a> or call <a href="tel:+441142992599">+44(0)114 299 2599</a> to speak directly with our experienced team. <strong>We promise: no phone menus, no waiting, no obligation and complete confidence.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>hanna-gul</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We review recently updated requirements for UKCA marking and what it means for your regulatory strategy.]]></summary></entry></feed>