<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-03T12:47:44+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">Navigating CAPA Terminology: Key Terms for Medical Device Professionals</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-capa-terminology-key-terms-for-medical-device-professionals" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating CAPA Terminology: Key Terms for Medical Device Professionals" /><published>2025-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-03T12:43:18+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-capa-terminology-key-terms-for-medical-device-professionals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-capa-terminology-key-terms-for-medical-device-professionals"><![CDATA[<p>The Corrective and Preventive Action (CAPA) process is a central component of <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">Quality Management Systems</a> (QMS) and is a mandatory requirement for ISO 13485, MDSAP, <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32017R0745#anx_%C2%A0VIII">Regulation MDR (EU) 2017/745</a>, and the <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/fda-510k-consulting">US FDA</a>. It is a systematic approach used to identify, address, and prevent the recurrence of problems.</p>
      <p>A CAPA is a structured process used to identify, resolve, and prevent the recurrence of issues within a system or product. It is essential for ensuring quality, compliance, and continuous improvement in various industries such as healthcare, manufacturing, and pharmaceuticals in the UK. The CAPA process is typically broken down into three main phases: <strong>Identify Problems</strong>, where issues are first recognised and thoroughly assessed; <strong>Address Problems</strong>, where corrective actions are formulated and implemented to fix the immediate problems; and <strong>Prevent Recurrence</strong>, where long-term solutions and preventive measures are established to ensure that the issue does not happen again, ultimately enhancing the reliability and quality of operations.</p>
      <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/capa-process-in-quality-management.svg" alt="CAPA Process in Quality Management diagram." loading="lazy" width="520" height="416" />
        <figcaption>CAPA Process in Quality Management</figcaption>
      </figure>
      <h2 id="key-terms">Key terms</h2>
      <p>Here are some key terms that all medical device professionals should acquaint themselves with:</p>
      <h3 id="nonconformity--a-deviation-from-a-specification-standard-or-an-expectation">Nonconformity = A deviation from a specification, standard, or an expectation</h3>
      <p>Nonconformity is the recognition of an issue that deviates from the expected outcome or requirement. These typically appear at the beginning of the process, during identification and investigation stages.</p>
      <h3 id="capa-trigger--a-predefined-condition-that-leads-to-a-corrective-or-preventative-measure">CAPA Trigger = A predefined condition that leads to a corrective or preventative measure</h3>
      <p>CAPA triggers can arise from various sources, both internal and external, and typically highlight areas where a product, process, or system does not meet specified standards or expectations. Examples of CAPA triggers include: customer complaints, audit findings, and adverse events or near misses.</p>
      <h3 id="root-cause-analysis-rca--a-method-to-identify-the-cause-of-a-problem">Root Cause Analysis (RCA) = A method to identify the cause of a problem</h3>
      <p>The goal of RCA is not just to address the immediate symptoms of a problem, but to discover and resolve the root cause(s) to prevent recurrence. It’s a critical component of the CAPA process, especially in regulated industries like manufacturing, healthcare, and quality control. Tools such as the 5 Whys, Fishbone Diagram, and Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA) can be used to facilitate RCA.</p>
      <h3 id="root-cause--the-main-reason-why-a-problem-has-arisenoccurred">Root Cause = The main reason why a problem has arisen/occurred</h3>
      <p>In any quality management or problem-solving process, identifying the root cause is critical because it allows an organisation to focus its efforts on eliminating the source of the problem, rather than just addressing its symptoms.</p>
      <h3 id="field-corrective-action-fca--actions-to-address-issues-identified-after-distribution">Field Corrective Action (FCA) = Actions to address issues identified after distribution</h3>
      <p>FCAs are typically initiated after a product defect, safety concern, or performance failure has been identified in the field, often through customer complaints, product recalls, or post-market surveillance data. They form an important part of the product lifecycle and help in protecting both the end users and the manufacturer’s reputation.</p>
      <h3 id="supplier-corrective-action-request-scar--a-request-to-a-supplier-to-address-the-problem">Supplier Corrective Action Request (SCAR) = A request to a supplier to address the problem</h3>
      <p>The SCAR process is used to communicate nonconformities, initiate corrective actions, and ensure that suppliers address the underlying issues causing defects or quality problems. It’s an essential tool in quality management systems. The purpose of SCAR is to improve supplier performance and prevent recurrence of issues that may affect the quality and safety of the end product.</p>
      <h3 id="capa-plan--a-documented-plan-for-actions-to-address-a-specific-issue">CAPA Plan = A documented plan for actions to address a specific issue</h3>
      <p>It begins with identifying a problem, conducting a root cause analysis, and implementing corrective actions to resolve the issue. Preventive actions are then put in place to reduce the risk of future occurrences. The plan also includes verifying the effectiveness of these actions, documenting the process, and ensuring continuous monitoring for improvement.</p>
      <h3 id="capa-review-board--a-group-that-is-responsible-for-overseeing-the-capa-process">CAPA Review Board = A group that is responsible for overseeing the CAPA process</h3>
      <p>The board ensures that identified issues are appropriately investigated, root causes are thoroughly analysed, and corrective and preventive actions are effectively implemented.</p>
      <h3 id="risk-assessment--the-process-of-identifying-and-analysing-the-impact-of-potential-issues">Risk Assessment = The process of identifying and analysing the impact of potential issues</h3>
      <p>In the context of CAPA, risk assessment helps determine the severity and likelihood of an issue reoccurring, allowing companies to implement appropriate actions to mitigate or control these risks. It plays a critical role in ensuring that corrective and preventive measures are effective and proportionate to the identified risks.</p>
      <h3 id="correction--action-to-fix-a-nonconformity-without-addressing-the-root-issue">Correction = Action to fix a nonconformity without addressing the root issue</h3>
      <p>Unlike corrective actions, which are aimed at preventing recurrence, corrections focus on resolving the current issue.</p>
      <h3 id="preventative-action-pa--actions-that-address-the-causes-of-a-potential-nonconformity">Preventative Action (PA) = Actions that address the causes of a potential nonconformity</h3>
      <p>This process involves analysing trends, risks, or weak points in the system and making improvements to avoid future problems, ensuring ongoing compliance and quality.</p>
      <h3 id="corrective-action-ca--actions-that-address-the-causes-of-an-existing-nonconformity">Corrective Action (CA) = Actions that address the causes of an existing nonconformity</h3>
      <p>This process involves investigating the issue, implementing changes to eliminate the cause, and ensuring that similar issues do not arise in the future.</p>
      <h3 id="verification--checking-that-a-solution-works-as-intended">Verification = Checking that a solution works as intended</h3>
      <p>Verification is the process of confirming that a product, process, or system meets specific requirements and functions as intended. It involves checking and testing against predetermined criteria to ensure accuracy and compliance before implementation or release.</p>
      <h3 id="validation--ensuring-that-a-product-or-a-process-meets-its-intended-use">Validation = Ensuring that a product or a process meets its intended use</h3>
      <p>Validation ensures that a product, process, or system consistently meets its intended purpose and regulatory requirements. It involves testing and documentation to confirm reliability and compliance with standards, ensuring product quality and safety.</p>
      <h3 id="effectiveness-check-voe--evaluation-to-confirm-the-success-of-a-capa">Effectiveness Check (VoE) = Evaluation to confirm the success of a CAPA</h3>
      <p>After implementing corrective actions, an Effectiveness Check ensures that the changes have successfully resolved the problem and that the same issue does not reoccur. This check typically involves monitoring the results over a set period, reviewing data, and evaluating the impact of the actions on product quality, performance, or process improvements.</p>
      <h3 id="disposition--decision-on-how-to-handle-a-nonconforming-product-or-situation">Disposition = Decision on how to handle a nonconforming product or situation</h3>
      <p>Disposition refers to the decision made regarding nonconforming products, determining whether they should be reworked, used as-is, scrapped, or returned to the supplier. These decisions are based on the severity of the nonconformity and are crucial for maintaining product quality and compliance.</p>
      <h2 id="mastering-capa-turning-terminology-into-action">Mastering CAPA: Turning Terminology into Action</h2>
      <p>In conclusion, understanding and navigating CAPA terminology is essential for ensuring compliance and driving continuous improvement within a quality management system. Familiarity with key terms such as root cause analysis, corrective actions, preventive actions, and effectiveness checks will help professionals make informed decisions, streamline processes, and avoid common pitfalls.</p>
      <p>By staying up-to-date with these critical terms, organisations can strengthen their CAPA processes, improve product quality, and enhance overall regulatory compliance. Empowering teams with the knowledge of CAPA terminology is a key step toward maintaining high-quality standards and ensuring the safety and efficacy of medical devices in the marketplace.</p>
      <p>Ready to navigate the regulatory process with confidence? With our expert team and 100% notified body approval, we’re here to help you ensure compliance and streamline your medical device journey. <a href="/contact">Contact us today to get started!</a></p>
      ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We define and explain the language required to work within a Quality Management System (QMS).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clinical Evaluation Masterclass: Overcoming Non-conformities - Episode 1</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-evaluation-masterclass-1-overcoming-non-conformities" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clinical Evaluation Masterclass: Overcoming Non-conformities - Episode 1" /><published>2025-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-01T17:44:46+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-evaluation-masterclass-1-overcoming-non-conformities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/clinical-evaluation-masterclass-1-overcoming-non-conformities"><![CDATA[<div class="video-wrap full">
      <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="3iOgkFyk-hc"></div>
    </div>
    <p>Clinical Evaluation Plans (CEPs) and Clinical Evaluation Reports (CERs) are critical components of medical device regulatory compliance. However, the reality is that meeting requirements isn’t always plain sailing.</p>
    <p>Based on our experience with over 250 successful submissions, we’ve identified that overcoming clinical evaluation non-conformities is one of the major challenges manufacturers face during the device approval journey.</p>
    <h2 id="what-is-a-non-conformity-in-clinical-evaluation">What is a Non-Conformity in Clinical Evaluation?</h2>
    <p>A non-conformity arises when a CEP or CER fails to meet MDR requirements. Non-conformities signal that the evaluation does not yet adequately demonstrate a medical device’s safety and performance or that full alignment with regulatory obligations has not been shown, requiring correction before approval.</p>
    <h2 id="the-impact-of-non-conformities-on-manufacturers">The Impact of Non-Conformities on Manufacturers</h2>
    <p>Non-conformities significantly disrupt the approval process, leading to extended review timelines, increased costs, and mandatory revision cycles. Since notified bodies (NBs) cannot accept a CEP or CER with unresolved non-conformities, addressing them is critical for market access.</p>
    <h2 id="a-helping-hand">A helping hand</h2>
    <p>Our new video series applies our deep experience to help manufacturers proactively identify and fix these issues for smoother audits and faster certifications. This series breaks down the most common clinical evaluation non-conformities, explains <em>why</em> they keep happening, and most importantly, shows you <em>how to fix them</em> for good. Each episode provides step-by-step guidance to help you avoid these pitfalls in your CER submissions.</p>
    <h2 id="episode-1-safety-and-performance-objectives-lack-specific-and-measurable-acceptance-criteria">Episode 1: “Safety and Performance Objectives Lack Specific and Measurable Acceptance Criteria”</h2>
    <p>This frequently cited regulatory observation typically reflects not an actual safety or performance deficiency, but rather insufficiently defined evaluation parameters. The episode will address:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Fundamental concepts of safety and performance objectives</li>
      <li>Deriving safety and performance objectives using weighted values</li>
      <li>Defining “specific” and “measurable” objectives</li>
      <li>Practical approaches to establishing and implementing acceptance criteria</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Coming in Episode 2: We’ll tackle another frequent non-conformity, “<em>Appraisal of literature articles has not been conducted appropriately</em>” showing you how to strengthen your literature review process. <a href="/newsletter">Sign up to our newsletter now so you don’t miss out</a>.</p>
    <hr />
    <div class="small-text">
      <strong>Transcript follows:</strong>
      <p>Okay, hi everyone, it’s Paul here from Mantra Systems. Welcome to a brand new series that we’re running on how to fix <strong>clinical evaluation non-conformities</strong>.</p>
      <p>The idea behind this series is to equip you with the capability to, first of all, avoid common non-conformities that are seen in medical device clinical evaluations. And then secondly, if you have been unfortunate enough to receive one, by the end of the series you should hopefully have a powerful strategy for correcting them and moving on to full acceptance of your CE.</p>
      <p>So, just for this first episode, we’re going to cover a few basics, and it’s worth starting with the question: <em>What is a clinical evaluation non-conformity?</em></p>
      <p>Well, obviously, apart from Class I devices, clinical evaluation plans and clinical evaluation reports need to be submitted for review by a notified body. And a non-conformity — or NC for short — is when conformity with requirements has not been adequately demonstrated. A non-conformity requires correction and then resubmission of the CEP and CER. Resolution — certainly of major non-conformities — is necessary in order for the clinical evaluation to be accepted.</p>
      <p>So, it is a really important topic, and non-conformities under MDR are quite common. But the problem with non-conformities is that sometimes the questions — which is how they’re often manifest, it’s a question from a reviewer — they can be difficult to interpret. Sometimes it’s not clear exactly what a reviewer means, and it may be unclear how to fully address them as well.</p>
      <p>A failure to resolve non-conformities in full may lead to a further round of review following yet another resubmission, which is just multiplying costs, losing time, and it leads to stress and worry — because it is anxiety-inducing trying to get a clinical evaluation through approval.</p>
      <p>Okay, so the aim of the series is to work through common non-conformities one at a time, and to dig deep into what they mean and how to solve or avoid them. The series and the principles within it link over to general principles for optimal conduct of clinical evaluation under the MDR.</p>
      <p>So, let’s start with our first example non-conformity. This one is a really common one, and it states:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p><em>“Safety and performance objectives do not appear to have specific and measurable acceptance criteria.”</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Breaking that down, we need to understand exactly what the question means and how to address it. It’s possible to break it down into the following bullet points:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>What actually are safety and performance objectives?</li>
        <li>What in this context does “specific and measurable” mean?</li>
        <li>What are acceptance criteria?</li>
      </ul>
      <p>And importantly, of course, it needs to go beyond just knowing what they are but: <strong>How do we derive and analyse them?</strong></p>
      <p>So, let’s begin with safety and performance objectives. What are safety and performance objectives?</p>
      <p>Well, these ultimately are benchmark values against which the device under evaluation will be compared. They are derived from the state-of-the-art literature review, which is an essential component of clinical evaluation.</p>
      <p>Technically speaking, objectives have two components. They’re derived of a clinical outcome parameter — which is a qualitative concept or type of outcome — and then attached to that, there will be a quantitative value that forms the actual objective.</p>
      <p>As per the non-conformity, safety and performance objectives must be specific and measurable. Now, that covers a lot of ground, so let’s take an example and break this down.</p>
      <p>An example might be of a completed safety — or in this case a performance — objective:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“Increasing walking distance in meters at six weeks post-procedure of 61.46m.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>You can see within this the two components: the “increase in walking distance in meters at six weeks” — that’s not a value, okay? It contains a number, but that’s just because we need to compare like with like. That’s not the actual objective.</p>
      <p>The clinical outcome parameter is a thing, a concept, something you might measure, something to which you might attach a value. And then the second part of it is the actual performance outcome, which is quantitative.</p>
      <p>These two things together constitute a specific and measurable safety or performance objective.</p>
      <p>So, how are these derived? Well, they’re derived during the analysis stage of a state-of-the-art literature review. We’re going to go on to a working example in a moment to show exactly how they are derived.</p>
      <p>Remember, a clinical outcome parameter is a “thing,” and you decide upon those by looking for outcomes that are seen in a comparable form across multiple sources within the state-of-the-art literature review. If you have four, five, six sources all reporting the same type of outcome, it’s a strong candidate for a clinical outcome parameter.</p>
      <p>In the state-of-the-art protocol, there should be a method for determining what constitutes a clinical outcome parameter. That, of course, would feed into the clinical evaluation plan.</p>
      <p>Safety and performance objectives then are weighted mean values attached to those parameters. As we’ve seen before, you need both parts.</p>
      <p>It’s worth at this point just reflecting on the principles of an effective state-of-the-art literature review. Because there’s no point producing state-of-the-art safety or performance outcomes that have not been derived properly.</p>
      <p>We’ll go into this in another video, but a state-of-the-art literature review requires:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>a detailed protocol</li>
        <li>use of a validated method to define research questions and search terms (one such method is PICCO)</li>
        <li>a well-documented literature extraction process with recording and justification of all excluded sources,</li>
        <li>a structured appraisal — which is where we get to be very specific to the production of safety and performance objectives, and</li>
        <li>the analysis — which is where the actual objectives are produced.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>But we cover that in a lot more detail in a separate video.</p>
      <p>So, let’s look at a working example of how safety and performance objectives are derived.</p>
      <p>Here is fictional data. Let’s say we’ve done a state-of-the-art literature review, and sticking with the same example, we found four publications that all reported a mean increase in walking distance at six weeks, and they all did it in a comparable way. Here are the mean values from each of those sources.</p>
      <p>How do we produce a weighted mean?</p>
      <p>You can see in the table that the way we’re going to weight it is by a representation of the quality of each of these studies, to ensure that greater weighting or prominence is given to results from higher quality studies. In order to do that, we need to produce an appraisal score.</p>
      <p>Appraisal scores — there are lots of different ways to do this. On the next slide we’ve got, again, a simplified fictional example of how to calculate an appraisal score. You might look at different aspects of the study: you might consider study type, sample size, the use of statistical tests and whether they were appropriate, and the length of follow-up. You’d probably in reality consider other factors as well, but for the purpose of this, this will suffice.</p>
      <p>You’ve perhaps seen this — usually these manifest as an alphanumeric code, and again, the meaning behind this code should be expressed in the literature search protocol, in the appraisal plan section. So this will all be mapped out.</p>
      <p>Ultimately, this enables the calculation of a numerical appraisal score for each paper, with a higher number representing a higher quality study. Then those values can be imputed back into the original table with all the other values being the same.</p>
      <p>Now we have an appraisal score by which we can weight the results from each study. That’s done fairly simply just by multiplying the actual result by the appraisal score. We do that for all of them to produce a weighted value for each study.</p>
      <p>But we’re not quite done there, because we need to calculate a weighted mean. That’s done by taking the sum of all the weighted values and dividing that by the sum of the appraisal scores.</p>
      <p>What we’re doing there is making the appraisal scores the denominator — they are the weighting factor that’s being applied across all studies. This means we achieve our objective of moving the weighted mean closest to the values of the highest quality studies.</p>
      <p>In this case, that means: 3872 / 63, which gives a weighted mean of 61.46.</p>
      <p>It’s always worth sanity checking these, but if you look at the plain mean values from each study and the appraisal scores, you’d expect it to land around the 60 mark — and that’s where it falls: 61.46.</p>
      <p>So, that’s a simplified example of how to calculate a weighted mean for the quantitative component of a safety and performance objective.</p>
      <p>Don’t forget, the non-conformity required that we produce safety and performance objectives that are specific and measurable.</p>
      <p>Let’s just reflect on what that means:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Specific means unambiguous, clear, and would be consistently interpreted as meaning the same thing.</li>
        <li>Measurable means it contains a value — a quantitative value — against which another value from another device can be measured.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>So we have this in this case. It’s clear that that is both specific and measurable, and that’s why we included reference to six weeks — to ensure we’re comparing like with like.</p>
      <p>That leaves us to consider the final aspect of the non-conformity, which was reference to acceptance criteria.</p>
      <p>An acceptance criteria basically defines when safety or performance of the device under evaluation are acceptable in comparison to state-of-the-art.</p>
      <p>What we’re doing here is setting out a means for comparing the device-under-evaluation outcomes with the state-of-the-art objectives for specified clinical outcome parameters. By now, all of these terms should have a meaning attached to them.</p>
      <p>So, the clinical evaluation plan needs to contain an analysis plan for how this comparison will be done. Suffice to say that the outcomes for the device under evaluation are calculated by weighted means using a very similar method that we used for the state-of-the-art objectives.</p>
      <p>And acceptance — this is the key part — acceptance can be defined as showing (statistically) that the outcomes for the device under evaluation are non-inferior to objectives derived from the SOA. We don’t need to show superiority — we’re just showing non-inferiority. That’s a key distinction.</p>
      <p>Let’s take a final example, then, working this through.</p>
      <p>We can see:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Increasing walking distance (spelled correctly this time) of 61.46,</li>
        <li>and in this example there were some other clinical outcome parameters as well:
          <ul>
            <li>improvement in pain (VAS, a measure of pain score),</li>
            <li>and range of motion at six months.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>We have values attached to all of those. Then we also have weighted mean values for the device under evaluation.</p>
      <p>Remember, the job here is to determine whether the device under evaluation is non-inferior to SOA objectives.</p>
      <p>For the top one, it’s very easy, because a plain number comparison shows that the device under evaluation did better than the SOA objective. We don’t need to do any fancy tests — it’s obviously non-inferior. That’s a straightforward conclusion.</p>
      <p>But with the others, on a plain number comparison, the device under evaluation actually looks like it’s done less well than the state-of-the-art objectives. The important thing to understand here is whether that represents true inferiority, or whether these values are statistically non-different.</p>
      <p>For that reason, conducting a statistical test is relevant. Often a t-test is an appropriate test because it’s a comparison of means, and it generates a p-value denoting significance or non-significance of the difference between these values.</p>
      <p>Let’s say we conducted a t-test in this case, and these were the p-values that were derived. Generally, significance requires a value of less than 0.05 for the p-value. That’s not what we’re seeing here, and so these differences were non-inferior.</p>
      <p>According to our acceptance criteria, the device under evaluation has been shown to have appropriate performance in reference to state-of-the-art.</p>
      <p>So let’s go back to the original non-conformity:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>“Safety and performance objectives do not appear to have specific and measurable acceptance criteria.”</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>We covered:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>what safety and performance objectives are,</li>
        <li>how to derive them using weighted values following a state-of-the-art literature review,</li>
        <li>what “specific and measurable” means and how the outlined process generates specific and measurable objectives,</li>
        <li>and what acceptance criteria are and how to apply them — including through use of statistical testing.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If you need any further support in relation to clinical evaluation or working through non-conformities, Mantra Systems are clinical evaluation specialists. You’re free to contact our team at any time.</p>
      <p>If you’ve just got some general questions, don’t worry — it’s absolutely fine. More than happy to speak at any time. So feel free to reach out to us if you need any additional support.</p>
      <p>That concludes the first episode of the Clinical Evaluation Non-Conformity series. I’d like to thank you very much, and if you have any questions or comments, please let me know below the video.</p>
      <p>Thank you very much.</p>
    </div>
    ]]></content><author><name>paul-hercock</name></author><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this series, we work step-by-step through common Non-Conformities to ensure you are always ahead of possible challenges on the way to MDR approval.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDCG 2020-16 Revision 4: Key Updates on IVDR Classification Rules</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2020-16-rev-4-key-updates-on-ivdr-classification-rules" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDCG 2020-16 Revision 4: Key Updates on IVDR Classification Rules" /><published>2025-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-28T10:50:34+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2020-16-rev-4-key-updates-on-ivdr-classification-rules</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdcg-2020-16-rev-4-key-updates-on-ivdr-classification-rules"><![CDATA[<p>The <strong>Medical Device Coordination Group (MDCG)</strong> has released <strong>MDCG 2020-16 rev.4 - Guidance on Classification Rules for in vitro Diagnostic Medical Devices under Regulation (EU) 2017/746</strong>.</p>
  <p>This update released in March 2025 provides comprehensive clarification on the classification rules outlined in <strong>Annex VIII</strong> of the <strong>IVDR</strong>, ensuring that manufacturers, notified bodies, and health institutions have a clear framework for classifying in vitro diagnostic (IVD) devices based on their intended purpose and inherent risk, prior to placing it on the market. Notably, the guidance addresses the classification of medical device software (MDSW) and emphasises the importance of considering devices used in combination.</p>
  <h2 id="summary-of-key-updates">Summary of Key Updates</h2>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: left">Rule</th>
        <th style="text-align: left">Changes</th>
        <th style="text-align: left">Details</th>
        <th style="text-align: left">Impact</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Rule 1 – Second Indent</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Revision of examples</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Updated examples to provide better clarity on the classification of IVD devices.</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Ensures more precise classification, reducing ambiguity for manufacturers.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Rule 3(m)</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Footnote 8 modified</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Footnote 8 modified to refine interpretation and applicability.</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Improves understanding of specific classification aspects.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Rule 4(a)</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Revision of examples</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Updated examples for self-testing devices, refining classifications based on biomarkers.</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Helps manufacturers align with IVDR requirements for self-testing IVDs.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Rule 6</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Minor modification of the rationale and revision of examples</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Minor updates to rationale and refined examples for Class B IVDs.</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Provides a clearer framework for determining Class B device classification.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Annex 1 and Annex 2</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Minor editorial changes</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Minor wording and structural refinements for improved readability.</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Enhances document clarity without changing regulatory requirements.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <h2 id="key-considerations-for-manufacturers">Key Considerations for Manufacturers</h2>
  <p>The <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/12f9756a-1e0d-4aed-9783-d948553f1705_en?filename=md_mdcg_2020_guidance_classification_ivd-md_en.pdf">MDCG 2020-16 rev.4 guidance</a> has significant implications for <strong>IVD manufacturers</strong> as it refines how devices should be classified under IVDR.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Accurate Classification Criteria</strong> – The revision of examples under <strong>Rules 1, 4(a), and 6</strong> helps manufacturers correctly classify their IVD devices, reducing uncertainty. Manufacturers must <strong>review and adapt</strong> classifications, ensuring conformity with <strong>IVDR and notified body requirements</strong>.</li>
    <li><strong>More Precise Risk Assessment</strong> – Manufacturers need to reassess whether their devices fall into a different risk class, impacting regulatory requirements.</li>
    <li><strong>Improved Compliance with IVDR</strong> – The minor changes provide clarity but do not fundamentally alter the classification process. However, manufacturers should review their classification decisions against the revised examples.</li>
    <li><strong>Potential Impact on Notified Body Review</strong> – If an IVD device’s classification is affected by the updated examples or rationale, additional <strong>notified body consultation</strong> may be required for conformity assessments.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
  <p>The MDCG has provided essential updates to support <strong>IVD manufacturers</strong> in <strong>correctly interpreting classification rules under the IVDR</strong>. By understanding and implementing these refinements, manufacturers can <strong>ensure accurate device classification, strengthen regulatory compliance, and streamline interactions with notified bodies</strong>.</p>
  <p>For more insights on IVDR compliance and regulatory transitions, you may find these articles helpful:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/articles/understanding-risk-based-classification-of-in-vitro-medical-devices-under-eu-ivdr">Understanding Risk-Based Classifications for IVDs Under the IVDR</a></li>
    <li><a href="/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period">Transitioning from IVDD to IVDR: Key Considerations</a></li>
  </ul>
  <p>Navigating IVDR classification can be challenging. <strong>Mantra Systems</strong> provides <strong>expert regulatory consulting, medical writing, and compliance support</strong> to help manufacturers <strong>interpret and implement</strong> the latest MDCG guidance seamlessly. <a href="/contact">Contact us today</a> for a free, confidential consultation on how we can support your IVDR compliance journey.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>chandini-vk</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We detail how this revision ensures manufacturers, notified bodies, and health institutions have a clearer regulatory framework.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Top 5 Common Pitfalls to Avoid During Risk Assessment</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/top-5-risk-assessment-pitfalls-how-to-avoid-them" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top 5 Common Pitfalls to Avoid During Risk Assessment" /><published>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T10:48:01+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/top-5-risk-assessment-pitfalls-how-to-avoid-them</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/top-5-risk-assessment-pitfalls-how-to-avoid-them"><![CDATA[<p>A medical device-specific risk assessment uses the <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72704.html">ISO 14971 standard</a>, which provides guidance for producing and maintaining a risk management file.</p>
  <p>A risk assessment is a process used to identify, analyse, and mitigate risk in the design and development process to enable the sale of safe and successful medical devices. <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk assessment</a> ensures that all potential hazards are identified and mitigated to protect patient safety. However, manufacturers often encounter mistakes along the way that can compromise the effectiveness of the assessment and delay product launch. To help you navigate the risk management process smoothly, here are the <strong>Top 5 Pitfalls</strong> to avoid during the risk assessment of your medical devices.</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/5-pitfalls-for-risk-assessment.svg" alt="Diagram highlighting the 5 pitfalls for risk assessment." loading="lazy" width="498" height="552" />
  </figure>
  <h2 id="1-failing-to-identify-all-potential-hazards">1. Failing to Identify All Potential Hazards</h2>
  <p>To begin a risk assessment, a comprehensive identification of potential hazards that could arise at any stage of the device’s lifecycle should be conducted. This involves documenting known and foreseeable hazards related to the medical device, considering its intended use, foreseeable misuse, and safety characteristics. A significant pitfall occurs here when manufacturers underestimate these hazards, in turn leading to an incomplete risk assessment.</p>
  <p><strong>How to avoid this:</strong></p>
  <p>Ensure cross-disciplinary teams are engaged (e.g., engineering, clinical, regulatory experts). This will ensure a thorough hazard analysis. Consider all potential risks, including those related to device malfunction, misuse, environmental factors, and human error.</p>
  <h2 id="2-insufficient-documentation-and-traceability">2. Insufficient Documentation and Traceability</h2>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/online-video-training-courses/risk-management">Clear documentation</a> of the risk management process is required for regulatory authorities, e.g., Notified Bodies, to review. <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32017R0745">Article 10 of the EU MDR</a> requires all manufacturers to establish, document, implement, and maintain a system for Risk Management. A frequent pitfall here is failing to maintain proper documentation of hazard identification, risk analysis, and control measures. This, in turn, will lead to non-compliance and delays.</p>
  <p><strong>How to avoid this:</strong></p>
  <p>Confirm that every step of the risk management process is documented in detail. Alongside this, you can use risk management tools, e.g., FMEA or risk matrices, to track the rationale behind each decision. This will allow for full traceability throughout the device lifecycle.</p>
  <p>Maintaining and updating a Risk Management strategy requires scheduled review and appraisal sessions to analyse system suitability. The clinical evaluation cycle offers an opportunity to assimilate Risk Management data collected and to re-perform a benefit-risk analysis of the device. Any updates or changes to the process must be reflected in documentation and disseminated across the organisation to ensure the changes are implemented.</p>
  <h2 id="3-underestimating-risk-acceptability-criteria">3. Underestimating Risk Acceptability Criteria</h2>
  <p>Determining whether a risk is acceptable or not is crucial in risk assessment. During risk evaluation, the manufacturer must assess estimated risks for each hazardous situation and check if they meet the criteria in the risk management plan.</p>
  <p>Setting inappropriate risk acceptance thresholds can directly impact both patient safety and product timelines. If the acceptable risk is set too high, the device may pose a significant threat to users, leading to potential harm or regulatory non-compliance. On the other hand, being too cautious and lowering the threshold could result in unnecessary design changes or delays in the approval process, even for risks that are statistically insignificant.</p>
  <p><strong>How to avoid this:</strong></p>
  <p>Risk acceptance should be based on both regulatory requirements and real-world clinical needs. The criteria should be proportional to the severity and likelihood of the identified risks. A low-risk device may have higher acceptable risk levels, while a high-risk device, such as a life-supporting medical device, must have stringent limits. Tools like risk matrices can help categorise and prioritise risks by their severity and probability, ensuring a rational and evidence-based approach to setting acceptability levels.</p>
  <h2 id="4-ignoring-post-market-risks">4. Ignoring Post-Market Risks</h2>
  <p>Many manufacturers place a significant emphasis on pre-market risks, neglecting the post-market risks that may arise once the device is in use by patients or healthcare professionals. The manufacturer must review all collected post-market information, focusing on safety relevance. This aims to identify unrecognised hazards not initially identified, hazardous situations with now-unacceptable estimated risks, and cases where the overall residual risk is no longer acceptable relative to intended use benefits.</p>
  <p><strong>How to avoid:</strong></p>
  <p>Ensure you incorporate a robust <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">post-market surveillance plan</a> into your risk management strategy. As well as this, make sure you set up systems to monitor and track device performance, adverse events, and potential hazards once the product is on the market.</p>
  <h2 id="5-neglecting-risk-control-and-mitigation-strategies">5. Neglecting Risk Control and Mitigation Strategies</h2>
  <p>The identification of hazards is just one part of the risk management process. The next critical phase is the implementation of effective risk controls, which is necessary to reduce identified risks to acceptable levels. Failing to implement effective controls or using controls that are impractical or inadequate is a common trap. This can lead to unresolved risks that may jeopardise patient safety, compromise device effectiveness, and increase the likelihood of regulatory non-compliance.</p>
  <p><strong>How to avoid:</strong></p>
  <p>To avoid neglecting risk control strategies, it’s essential to follow a structured approach that aligns with recognised best practices and regulatory standards. Here are some practical steps:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Start by prioritising the risks that need mitigation based on their severity and probability of occurrence.</li>
    <li>Evaluate the effectiveness of controls. This can include pre-market validation through clinical trials, in-vitro testing, and failure testing, as well as post-market monitoring to ensure that controls remain effective over time.</li>
    <li>For each identified risk, provide a rationale for the selected control, how it works to mitigate the hazard, and how its effectiveness will be measured.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="final-thoughts-mastering-risk-assessment">Final Thoughts: Mastering Risk Assessment</h2>
  <p>By carefully identifying all potential hazards, setting realistic risk acceptability criteria, and implementing robust mitigation strategies, you can significantly reduce the likelihood of regulatory setbacks and safety issues. A proactive and comprehensive approach to risk management not only protects patients but also streamlines the path to market, helping your device succeed in a competitive landscape. Remember, risk assessment is an ongoing process that requires constant vigilance and adaptation, so stay committed to continuous improvement. Please <a href="/contact">contact us if you need any help with risk assessment</a> or any medical device regulation issue.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn how to sidestep costly mistakes which manufacturers commonly make. From hazard ID to post-market surveillance, we help you improve safety and speed up approvals.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Labelling 101: A Comprehensive Overview for Medical Device Manufacturers</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/labelling-101-a-comprehensive-overview-form-medical-device-manufacturers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labelling 101: A Comprehensive Overview for Medical Device Manufacturers" /><published>2025-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T21:40:34+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/labelling-101-a-comprehensive-overview-form-medical-device-manufacturers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/labelling-101-a-comprehensive-overview-form-medical-device-manufacturers"><![CDATA[<p>Labelling is a crucial aspect of medical device compliance, ensuring that essential information is effectively communicated to users. Labelling includes written, printed, or graphic details on the device itself, its packaging, or accompanying materials such as Instructions for Use (IFU). Regulatory bodies require manufacturers to provide clear and accurate labelling to enhance patient safety, facilitate proper usage, and comply with international standards.</p>
  <h2 id="medical-device-labelling-standard-iso-15223-12021">Medical Device Labelling Standard: ISO 15223-1:2021</h2>
  <p><a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/77326.html">ISO 15223-1</a> sets out requirements for symbols used in medical device labelling to communicate information about the safe and effective use of devices. The latest version, ISO 15223-1:2021, includes additional symbols to comply with the requirements of <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=celex%3A32017R0745">EU MDR 2017/745</a>.</p>
  <p>According to the ISO 15223-1 standard, medical device labelling symbols are organised into seven categories:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Manufacturing:</strong> Symbols related to the manufacturing process of the device.</li>
    <li><strong>Storage:</strong> Symbols indicating specific storage conditions for the device.</li>
    <li><strong>Safe use:</strong> Symbols providing information on the safe and proper use of the device.</li>
    <li><strong>Sterility:</strong> Symbols indicating the sterile condition of the device or instructions related to sterility.</li>
    <li><strong>IVD specific:</strong> Symbols specific to in vitro diagnostic devices.</li>
    <li><strong>Transfusion/Infusion:</strong> Symbols related to transfusion or infusion procedures.</li>
    <li><strong>Others:</strong> Symbols that do not fall into the above categories but are still relevant to medical device labelling.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Standardised symbols help manufacturers effectively communicate vital information to users, enhancing safety and reducing risks of errors or misinterpretation.</p>
  <p>Regulatory requirements mandate that devices must be clearly identifiable as <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-product-medical-device-mantrasystems-fbjae/">medical devices</a>. The medical device symbol, in accordance with ISO 15223, can be displayed on the label to facilitate recognition and ensure regulatory compliance.</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/md-logo.svg" alt="Medical Device logo." loading="lazy" width="200" height="137" />
  </figure>
  <p>Additionally, manufacturers must adhere to labelling regulations outlined in <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/guide-general-performance-safety-requirements-gsprs-mantrasystems-f69fe/">GSPR</a> 23.1(a) and GSPR 20.1(a). These guidelines specify that certain label information must also be included in the Instructions for Use (IFU), and any symbols used on the label may require an explanation within the IFU.</p>
  <h2 id="substances-specific-information">Substances Specific Information</h2>
  <p>The label must also specify if the device contains or incorporates any of the following substances:</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/substances-for-device.svg" alt="Does the device contain specific substances? decision diagram." loading="lazy" width="556" height="264" />
  </figure>
  <h2 id="label-marking-requirements-iso-204172021">Label Marking Requirements (ISO 20417:2021)</h2>
  <p><a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/67943.html">ISO 20417:2021</a> defines a label as “written, printed, or graphic information appearing on the item itself, on the packaging of each item, or on the packaging of multiple items.” According to this standard, manufacturers must ensure that the device is marked with the relevant information, unless:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The size of the device does not allow for fixation of the information.</li>
    <li>The nature of the outer surface of the device does not allow for the information to be fixed.</li>
    <li>The omission of the markings does not negatively affect the benefit-risk balance as per <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72704.html">ISO 14971:2019</a>.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="packaging-and-sterility-requirements">Packaging and Sterility Requirements</h2>
  <p>Packaging plays an essential role in ensuring that medical devices remain protected during transport, storage, and handling. <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/70799.html">ISO 11607</a> specifies requirements for the development and validation of processes for packaging medical devices. Compliance with ISO 11607 helps demonstrate conformity with essential requirements. Similar to the FDA, the EU requires compliance with ISO 10993-1 for the biological evaluation of medical device packaging materials.</p>
  <p>EU MDR 2017/745 annex I GSPR, specifies the packaging requirements of medical devices. The requirements can be summarised as;</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The packaging must protect the device and maintain its integrity, ensuring it remains sterile if applicable.</li>
    <li>Non-sterile devices must be packaged in a way that maintains their cleanliness and integrity.</li>
    <li>The packaging must be designed to minimise contamination risks during transportation and storage.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>For sterile devices, the packaging must ensure the device remains sterile until the packaging is opened.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The sterile packaging of a device should include the following information:</li>
    <li>An indication to recognise the packaging as sterile.</li>
    <li>A declaration that the device is in a sterile condition.</li>
    <li>The method of sterilisation.</li>
    <li>Instruction to check the instructions for use on what to do if the sterile packaging is damaged or unintentionally opened before use.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="checklist-for-eu-mdr-medical-device-labelling">Checklist for EU MDR Medical Device Labelling</h2>
  <p>Avoid compliance pitfalls with this checklist of essential labelling requirements for medical devices:</p>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: left">Key Requirement</th>
        <th style="text-align: left">Yes/No</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Product name</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Product’s lot number or serial number</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">All details needed for a user to identify the device, the contents of its packaging and the intended purpose of the device</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Contact details of the manufacturer (e.g., name and address)</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">In the case of non-EU-based manufacturers, the name and address of their authorised representative</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Where relevant, information per Section 10.4.5. of the MDR</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">The <a href="/articles/decoding-udi-ultimate-guide-to-smarter-medical-device-labelling">UDI carrier</a> referred to in Part C of Annex VII of the MDR</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">An indication of any special storage or handling conditions</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">A clear indication of the time limit for using the device safely, or where this is not applicable – the date of manufacture</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">If the product is supplied in a sterile condition, an indication of its sterile state and method of sterilisation</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">An indication if the product is for single-use</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">An indication if the device is custom-made or intended for clinical investigation only</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Other warnings and precautions to be taken that need to be brought to the user’s immediate attention</td>
        <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <h2 id="why-is-medical-device-labelling-so-important">Why is medical device labelling so important?</h2>
  <p>For medical devices to be used safely and effectively, it is crucial that patients, caregivers, and healthcare providers receive clear and concise instructions, guidance, and warnings. Failure to follow these instructions, or mishandling the device, can result in malfunction, injury, or even death. While some mistakes may cause severe harm, even minor errors can impact patient outcomes in significant ways.</p>
  <p>The well-being of the user must always be the primary concern for those involved in the manufacturing and design of medical devices. Effective labelling is essential in preventing misuse and ensuring proper usage. Moreover, complying with labelling standards isn’t just about safety—it also helps manufacturers meet regulatory requirements, avoiding costly delays, recalls, or legal issues.</p>
  <h2 id="the-final-stamp-of-approval-on-labelling">The Final Stamp of Approval on Labelling</h2>
  <p>Labelling and packaging are critical aspects of medical device regulation, ensuring both compliance with the EU MDR and safety for patients and users. Medical device manufacturers must adhere to the extensive labelling requirements, including clear information on the device’s identity, use, storage, and associated risks. Failure to comply with these requirements can lead to regulatory challenges and safety concerns. By adhering to the EU MDR labelling and packaging guidelines, manufacturers can ensure their devices are compliant, safe, and ready for market entry.</p>
  <p>Need expert guidance on medical device labeling? Mantra Systems is here to help. Our tailored solutions ensure your devices meet all regulatory requirements while streamlining compliance processes. <a href="/contact">Reach out today for tailored solutions!</a></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Labelling and packaging are critical elements to ensuring safety, compliance, and ease of use.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">European Commission Guidelines on Prohibited Artificial Intelligence Practices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/european-commission-guidelines-on-prohibited-artificial-intelligence-practices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Commission Guidelines on Prohibited Artificial Intelligence Practices" /><published>2025-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-18T12:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/european-commission-guidelines-on-prohibited-artificial-intelligence-practices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/european-commission-guidelines-on-prohibited-artificial-intelligence-practices"><![CDATA[<p>The Regulation (EU) 2024/1689 artificial intelligence (AI) Act aims to promote innovation and uptake of AI while ensuring high protection of health, safety, and fundamental rights. It classifies AI systems into four risk categories which are unacceptable risk, high risk, transparency risk and minimal to no risk.</p>
  <p>On 4th February 2025, the European Commission issued guidelines on prohibited AI practices established by regulation (EU) 2024/1689 (AI Act). The guidelines are important to organisations and businesses with AI systems in the EU and detail which AI practices are unacceptable.</p>
  <p>A summary of the eight prohibited AI practices, examples of AI systems to which they apply and systems that are out of scope are listed below.</p>
  <h2 id="prohibited-ai-practices">Prohibited AI practices:</h2>
  <h3 id="1-harmful-manipulation-and-deception---article-5-1a">1. Harmful Manipulation and Deception - Article 5 (1)(a):</h3>
  <p>AI systems that employ subliminal, manipulative, or deceptive techniques that distort behaviour and cause significant harm are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Subliminal techniques:</strong> Examples include AI systems that use visual and auditory subliminal messages, subvisual and subaudible cueing and embedded images that can unconsciously influence users.</li>
    <li><strong>Manipulative techniques:</strong> Examples include AI systems that purposefully manipulate users through background audio or images to induce mood changes such as increased anxiety or mental suffering resulting in significant harm.</li>
    <li><strong>Deceptive techniques:</strong> Examples include an AI chatbot that impersonates a friend or relative with a synthetic voice leading to scams and significant harm.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="2-harmful-exploitation-of-vulnerabilities---article-51b">2. Harmful exploitation of vulnerabilities - Article 5(1)(b):</h3>
  <p>AI systems that exploit vulnerabilities due to age, disability, or socio-economic situations resulting in distortion of behaviour and significant harm are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>An example is an AI powered toy that encourages children to complete increasingly risky challenges for digital rewards and virtual praise, potentially leading to dangerous behaviour and physical harm.</li>
    <li>AI systems that use lawful persuasion rather than manipulation and that are not likely to cause significant harm are outside of the scope of Article 5(1)(a) and (b).
      <ul>
        <li>For example, an AI system that uses personalised recommendations based on transparent algorithms and user preferences engages in lawful persuasion.</li>
        <li>For example, a therapeutic chatbot that uses subliminal techniques to guide users towards a healthier lifestyle and to quit bad habits such as smoking is not likely to cause significant harm even if users experience physical discomfort and psychological stress because of the effort made to quit smoking.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="3-social-scoring---article-51c">3. Social Scoring - Article 5(1)(c)</h3>
  <p>AI systems that evaluate or classify individuals based on social behaviour or personal characteristics resulting in unjustified treatment are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>An example is an AI predictive tool that analyses taxpayers’ tax returns to select tax returns for closer inspection. The AI tool uses relevant variables such as yearly income as well as unrelated data such as a taxpayer’ social habits or internet connections to select individuals for closer inspection, leading to potential discrimination.</li>
    <li>Out of scope legitimate scoring practices include financial credit scoring systems which are used by creditors and credit information agencies to determine a customer’s ability to repay debts by analysing a range of financial data such as the customer’s income and expenses.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="4-individual-criminal-offence-risk-assessment-and-prediction---article-51d">4. Individual Criminal Offence Risk Assessment and Prediction - Article 5(1)(d)</h3>
  <p>AI systems that predict criminal behaviour based solely on profiling or personality traits, without objective human assessment are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>An example is a law enforcement authority that uses an AI system to predict criminal behaviour based on a personal characteristic such as age, nationality, address and marital status leading to unjust profiling.</li>
    <li>Out of scope AI systems include predictive policing systems which generate a score for the likelihood of criminality in different neighbourhoods based on previous criminality rates and other supporting information such as street maps, allowing law enforcement to identify areas that require additional police presence.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="5-untargeted-scraping-of-facial-images---article-51e">5. Untargeted Scraping of Facial Images - Article 5(1)(e)</h3>
  <p>Creating or expanding facial recognition databases through untargeted scraping from the internet or CCTV footage is prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>In terms of the internet, if a person has published facial images of themselves on social media it does not mean that the person has given permission for the images to be included in a facial recognition database. An example of scraping images from CCTV is an AI tool that uses images from surveillance cameras in public spaces like airports and streets without consent.</li>
    <li>Out of scope AI systems include databases that contain facial images but do not associate them with identifiable individuals e.g. datasets used solely for training or testing AI models without any intent to recognise or identify the persons in the images.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="6-emotion-recognition---article-51f">6. Emotion Recognition - Article 5(1)(f)</h3>
  <p>AI systems inferring emotions in workplaces and educational institutions, except for medical or safety reasons are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>An example of ‘emotion recognition’ is an AI system that infers that an employee is unhappy, sad or angry to customers using body gestures, a frown or the absence of a smile.</li>
    <li>Out of scope are AI systems that infer emotions not on the basis of biometric data e.g. from written text and AI systems that infer physical states e.g. pain and tiredness.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="7-biometric-categorisation---article-51g">7. Biometric Categorisation - Article 5(1)(g)</h3>
  <p>Categorising individuals based on biometric data to infer sensitive characteristics like race, political opinions, or sexual orientation are prohibited.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>An example is an AI system that categorises social media users by their presumed political orientation based on biometric data from uploaded photos to send them targeted political messages.</li>
    <li>Examples of permissible filtering include the categorisation of patients using images according to skin or eye colour which may be important for a medical diagnosis such as cancer.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="8-real-time-remote-biometric-identification-rbi---article-51h">8. Real-time Remote Biometric Identification (RBI) - Article 5(1)(h)</h3>
  <p>The use of real-time RBI systems in publicly accessible spaces for law enforcement is prohibited with exceptions only for serious threats and criminal investigations.</p>
  <p>Safeguards and conditions for the exceptions (Article 5(2)-(7) AI Act) are documented in the guidelines which aim to ensure the responsible and ethical use of AI technologies while safeguarding fundamental rights and promoting trust in AI systems.</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/8-prohibited-ai-practices-diagram.svg" alt="A diagram showing 8 prohibited AI practices.svg" loading="lazy" width="674" height="476" />
    <figcaption>Overview of Prohibited AI Practices</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <h2 id="enforcement-of-article-5-ai-act">Enforcement of Article 5 AI Act</h2>
  <p>The prohibitions in Article 5 AI Act became applicable after 2 February 2025 and penalties, governance and confidentiality will apply from 2 August 2025.</p>
  <p>Market Surveillance Authorities are responsible for the enforcement of rules in the AI Act for AI systems including prohibitions. The AI Act employs a tiered response to determine penalties for non-compliance. This system is designed to ensure that the severity of the infringement is appropriately matched with the corresponding penalty. Non-compliance with prohibitions in Article 5 AI Act are classified as the most serious infringement and subject to the highest fine which can be up to EUR 35,000,000 or up to 7% of worldwide turnover for the previous financial year, if the offender is an undertaking, whichever is higher.</p>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>AI in healthcare, such as software as a medical device (SaMD), must be developed with stringent ethical standards to ensure patient safety and protection of fundamental rights. The guidelines remind developers and regulators alike of the importance of maintaining transparency and safeguarding against AI misuse. As the healthcare sector continues to integrate AI into medical devices, these guidelines will serve as a key framework for ensuring that AI-driven solutions prioritise the well-being of patients while promoting innovation and trust in the healthcare system.</p>
  <p>If you need guidance on navigating AI challenges, <a href="/contact">contact us today to arrange a free, no-obligation discussion</a>.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>clare-dixon</name></author><category term="SaMD" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Summary of the 8 AI practices prohibited by the EU 2024/1689 artificial intelligence (AI) Act.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating Non-Conformities in Technical Documentation</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-non-conformities-in-technical-documentation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating Non-Conformities in Technical Documentation" /><published>2025-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-12T11:01:47+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-non-conformities-in-technical-documentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-non-conformities-in-technical-documentation"><![CDATA[<p>This article explores how to effectively manage non-conformities in technical documentation within the context of EU MDR compliance. Learn how to implement corrective and preventive actions (CAPAs) and best practices to enhance product quality and ensure regulatory adherence.</p>
  <p>In the highly regulated world of regulatory affairs, technical documentation serves as a cornerstone for ensuring product compliance, safety, and efficacy. Yet even the most meticulously prepared documents can face non-conformities during reviews.</p>
  <p>Let’s explore how to manage non-conformities effectively and implement corrective and preventive actions (CAPAs) to enhance the quality of technical documentation.</p>
  <h2 id="understanding-non-conformities">Understanding Non-Conformities</h2>
  <p>In the context of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/745/oj/eng">EU Medical Device Regulation</a> (EU MDR), a non-conformance refers to a situation where a medical device, process, or quality management system does not meet the requirements outlined in the regulation (<a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">ISO 13485</a>) and the organisation’s aligned procedures. Non-conformities can occur during numerous stages of the medical device lifecycle, including design, manufacturing, post-market surveillance, or quality management, and may include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Incomplete or inaccurate content:</strong> Missing critical details like device classifications or clinical data summaries.</li>
    <li><strong>Inconsistent formatting:</strong> Deviations from templates or submission requirements.</li>
    <li><strong>Outdated references:</strong> Use of superseded regulations or standards.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="the-pip-scandal-a-wake-up-call-for-managing-non-conformities">The PIP Scandal: A Wake-Up Call for Managing Non-Conformities</h2>
  <p>Poly Implant Prothese (PIP) was a French company which manufactured breast implants, and was once the world’s third biggest supplier. <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/20180929-french-pip-breast-implants-scandal">The issue arose in 2010</a>, when PIP implants were revealed to be made from cheaper, industrial-grade silicone (that was not approved for medical use), and were rupturing. The silicone gel was known to cause inflammation and possible scarring, and these implants raised concerns over harmful long-term effects. This posed significant risks to patient health, leading to thousands of women receiving defective implants. The scandal highlighted severe flaws in both the manufacturing process and the regulatory oversight of medical devices.</p>
  <p>For example, the PIP implants were not subjected to adequate safety testing, and documentation of these test results was either incomplete or absent. The absence of proper validation and testing records left significant gaps in the product’s safety profile. If there had been a comprehensive review of testing protocols and documented evidence of failures or deviations from safety standards, corrective actions could have been taken much earlier.</p>
  <p>The PIP scandal serves as a stark reminder of the importance of proper documentation, regulatory compliance, and risk management in the medical device industry. When non-conformities are not adequately identified, documented, or addressed, it can lead to catastrophic results for both patients and manufacturers. The technical documentation for a medical device, such as breast implants, includes crucial elements such as design specifications, materials used, testing procedures, and safety protocols.</p>
  <h2 id="a-structured-approach-to-corrective-and-preventive-actions">A Structured Approach to Corrective and Preventive Actions</h2>
  <p>When a non-conformance is identified, it is essential to implement appropriate Corrective and Preventive Actions (CAPAs). These actions must address the root cause, prevent recurrence, and ensure <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">compliance with EU MDR</a> requirements. Prompt and effective resolution of non-conformances is crucial to maintaining product quality, ensuring patient safety, and achieving regulatory compliance in the EU market.</p>
  <p>A CAPA is a systematic approach that organisations use to identify, investigate, and address issues or non-conformities within their processes, products or services. The goal of CAPA is to both correct problems and implement measures to prevent them from happening again in the future. CAPA is made up of two components:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Corrective Action (CA):</strong> Corrective Action addresses existing problems, non-conformities or deviations identified. It involves immediate or short-term actions to rectify the issue, mitigate any negative impacts, and prevent recurrence.</li>
    <li><strong>Preventive Action (PA):</strong> Preventive Action aims to identify and eliminate potential causes of problems or non-conformities before they occur. It is a proactive approach to prevent similar issues from arising in the future.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The CAPA process typically involves the following steps:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Identification and Reporting:</strong> Identifying the problem, non-conformity, or deviation, and reporting it.</li>
    <li><strong>Investigation and Analysis:</strong> Conducting a thorough investigation to determine the root cause of the issue.</li>
    <li><strong>Action Plan Development:</strong> Developing a corrective action plan to address the immediate issue. Then a preventive action plan to mitigate future occurrences.</li>
    <li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Implementing the corrective actions and preventive actions according to the action plans.</li>
    <li><strong>Verification:</strong> Verifying that the actions taken have effectively addressed the issues and prevented recurrence.</li>
    <li><strong>Monitoring and Review:</strong> Monitoring the implemented changes to ensure they are sustained. Reviewing the effectiveness of the corrective and preventive actions over time.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="completing-a-root-cause-analysis">Completing a Root Cause Analysis</h2>
  <p>Root cause analysis goes beyond surface symptoms to uncover the underlying reason for the non-conformance.</p>
  <p>There are several techniques that can be used for root cause analysis, such as:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>5 Whys:</strong> Ask “why” repeatedly. Look into the successive layers of cause and effect until reaching the fundamental reason.</li>
    <li><strong>Fishbone Diagram (Ishikawa or Cause and Effect Diagram):</strong> Identify potential causes categorised into different factors.</li>
    <li><strong>Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA):</strong>  Evaluate potential failure modes and their causes, effects, and severity. Prioritise corrective and preventive actions.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="best-practices-for-managing-non-conformities">Best Practices for Managing Non-Conformities</h2>
  <p>Implementing the following best practices can help organisations address issues proactively and prevent recurrence, including:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Conduct Regular Audits:</strong> Routinely review technical documentation to detect and resolve discrepancies before they escalate.</li>
    <li><strong>Foster Cross-Functional Collaboration:</strong> Encourage seamless cooperation between regulatory, quality assurance, and R&amp;D teams to enhance compliance and efficiency.</li>
    <li><strong>Strengthen Regulatory Knowledge:</strong> Equip teams with a deep understanding of regulatory requirements and quality standards to minimise errors and improve compliance.</li>
    <li><strong>Leverage Corrective Action Requests (CARs) for Improvement:</strong> View CARs as opportunities to refine processes. Analysing non-conformance trends can reveal systemic issues that require long-term solutions.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>In the fast-evolving regulatory landscape, maintaining robust processes for handling non-conformities is a critical skill for any regulatory professional. Let’s embrace these challenges as opportunities to build stronger, more compliant systems. <a href="/contact">Get in touch</a> for tailored solutions that ensure your technical documentation meets the latest standards.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We explore how to manage non-conformities effectively and implement Corrective and Preventive Actions (CAPAs).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastering the EU MDR: Essential Steps for Compliance-Ready Docs</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mastering-eu-mdr-essential-steps-for-compliance-ready-docs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastering the EU MDR: Essential Steps for Compliance-Ready Docs" /><published>2025-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-01T00:02:42+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mastering-eu-mdr-essential-steps-for-compliance-ready-docs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mastering-eu-mdr-essential-steps-for-compliance-ready-docs"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s ever-evolving Medical Device regulatory landscape, staying compliant with the <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/mdr-consulting">European Union Medical Device Regulations</a> (EU MDR) is crucial for businesses operating in or with the EU. However, navigating its complex and ever-changing framework can feel like a maze.</p>
  <p>If you’re uncertain about the readiness of your EU MDR documentation, this article provides an overview of the essential steps to ensure you’re on track, from understanding key regulations to identifying potential gaps in your compliance process.</p>
  <h2 id="grasping-the-essentials-key-eu-mdr-requirements-you-need-to-know">Grasping the Essentials: Key EU MDR Requirements You Need to Know</h2>
  <p>Compliance is accomplished by demonstrating conformity of your device with all relevant aspects of the EU MDR. Manufacturers are required demonstrate this compliance to gain regulatory approval for their medical devices.</p>
  <p>Medical devices must be designed, manufactured, distributed, and tracked according to EU MDR requirements, and manufacturers must develop a suite of compliant regulatory systems, processes, and documents to continually monitor the safety and performance of their products.</p>
  <p>This process <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance">begins with a detailed understanding of the regulation and the obligations it imposes upon manufacturers</a>. A key part of demonstrating compliance is ensuring that your technical file includes everything required under the regulation. This consists of clinical evaluations, risk management documentation, and information on manufacturing processes. Being thorough at this stage ensures you don’t run into roadblocks later.</p>
  <h2 id="conquering-your-technical-documentation-a-thorough-review-is-essential">Conquering Your Technical Documentation: A Thorough Review is Essential</h2>
  <p>One of the most essential aspects of EU MDR compliance is your technical documentation. The regulation requires manufacturers to maintain detailed files that provide evidence of the safety, performance, and risk management of their products. These files must be available for review by Notified Bodies during audits and inspections.</p>
  <p>Regulatory systems, processes, and documents required for compliance are more extensive than those necessary under the outgoing Medical Device Directive (MDD). Those required for MDR Compliance include the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Quality Management System (<a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">QMS</a>)</strong> covering the activities of the entire organisation</li>
    <li><strong>Post-Market Surveillance (<a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">PMS</a>)</strong> system monitoring safety and performance of each device following release onto the market</li>
    <li><strong>Post-Market Clinical Follow-up (<a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf">PMCF</a>)</strong> and <strong>Vigilance system</strong> for each device</li>
    <li><strong>Risk Management system</strong> to the standard in <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72704.html">ISO 14971:2019</a> or equivalent</li>
    <li><strong>Clinical Evaluation</strong> process for every medical device, documented as a State-of-the-Art Report (SOTA), Clinical Evaluation Report (CEP), and a Clinical Evaluation Report (CER) which must be continuously updated at appropriate intervals</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Carefully reviewing each section of your technical file is essential. Missing even a small piece of documentation can cause delays or, worse, non-compliance. Successful compliance is demonstrated by the application of a CE-mark to the device.</p>
  <p>Class I manufacturers (except for devices that are sterile or have a measuring function) may self-apply a CE-mark after producing a declaration of conformity. For all other classes of medical devices, a CE-mark may only be affixed once a Notified Body has issued a certificate of conformity following a regulatory review according to rules in Chapter IV of the MDR.</p>
  <h2 id="navigating-special-cases-ensuring-conformity-with-eu-mdr-requirements">Navigating Special Cases: Ensuring Conformity with EU MDR Requirements</h2>
  <p>Certain devices, particularly those that include medicinal substances or components of animal or human origin, have additional requirements under the EU MDR. These special cases require detailed documentation to ensure compliance with stricter regulations. It’s important to identify if your device falls under these categories and ensure that you are meeting the additional regulatory requirements.</p>
  <p>This can often be a challenging aspect of compliance. For example, if your device uses a medicinal substance or has biological components, it may be subject to additional testing and reporting obligations, e.g., a medicinal dossier. Understanding these specifics early on in the process can save you time and prevent future compliance hurdles.</p>
  <h2 id="stay-compliant-the-importance-of-regularly-updating-your-documentation">Stay Compliant: The Importance of Regularly Updating Your Documentation</h2>
  <p>EU MDR compliance is an ongoing process. It’s not enough to simply submit your documentation and wait for approval. Once your device is on the market, continuous monitoring through PMS and PMCF is required. You must regularly update your technical file to reflect any changes, including modifications to the device, new clinical data, or updates to regulatory requirements.</p>
  <p>Additionally, your clinical evaluations should be regularly reviewed to ensure that new evidence supports the ongoing safety and performance of your device.</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/mdr-technical-file.png" alt="MDR Technical file relationship diagram." loading="lazy" width="520" height="416" />
  </figure>
  <h2 id="ensuring-youre-ready-how-to-close-the-gaps">Ensuring You’re Ready: How to Close the Gaps</h2>
  <p>With so many requirements and details involved, it can be easy to feel unsure about whether your documentation is truly ready for submission. Even the most diligent teams can miss critical elements or overlook specific areas of compliance.</p>
  <p>This is where an automated tool can be a game-changer. An EU MDR compliance checker can help you quickly identify any gaps or discrepancies in your technical documentation. By conducting a comprehensive review of your files, you ensure that your submission is as complete and accurate as possible.</p>
  <h3 id="no-technical-file-no-ce-mark-no-access-to-the-eu-market">No Technical File, no CE mark, no access to the EU market.</h3>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/technical-document-templates/mdr-compliance-checker-gap-analysis-tool">Mantra Systems’ EU MDR Compliance Checker</a> is built to take the guesswork out of the process. It flags any discrepancies and offers a report card for compliance gaps, providing you with reassurance that your documentation is aligned with EU standards.</p>
  <p>It covers all key components, from General Requirements needed across documents to ensuring GSPR Conformity. The checker also supports robust Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) and Post-Market Clinical Follow-Up (PMCF) processes, ensuring your products remain compliant even after they hit the market. Additionally, it assists with Clinical Evaluation and Risk Management, two crucial elements of your compliance strategy. Our checker is also equipped to handle Other Regulatory Processes and the preparation of Annex II Technical Documents, ensuring no detail is overlooked. Plus, it can help navigate Special Cases, making it the ultimate tool for comprehensive EU MDR compliance. With all these components integrated into one solution, you can be confident in your ability to meet the ever-evolving regulatory standards.</p>
  <p>With <a href="/enable-ce-mark/technical-document-templates/mdr-compliance-checker-gap-analysis-tool">our free EU MDR Compliance Checker</a>, you can simplify the complexities of regulatory compliance and ensure your products meet the highest standards. Stay ahead of the curve and safeguard your business by making compliance effortless and efficient every step of the way. <a href="/enable-ce-mark/technical-document-templates/mdr-compliance-checker-gap-analysis-tool">Download it free today.</a></p>
  <h2 id="flat-monthly-fee-regulatory-consulting">Flat Monthly Fee Regulatory Consulting</h2>
  <p>With Mantra Systems’ flexible regulatory consulting options, we can tailor pricing to suit your MDR compliance needs. As well as traditional Fixed Fee Consulting, we also offer a <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-servicesfractional-regulatory-consulting">Fractional Regulatory Consulting</a> option for companies that would prefer lower initial costs and no long-term commitment.</p>
  <p><a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/fractional-regulatory-consulting#contact">Book a free consultation</a> to discuss this alongside your regulatory needs with our team.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you're uncertain about the readiness of your EU MDR documentation, this article provides an overview of the essential steps to ensure you’re on track.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Guide to Electronic Instructions for Use (eIFU)</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-guide-to-eifu-electronic-instructions-for-use" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Guide to Electronic Instructions for Use (eIFU)" /><published>2025-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-28T13:25:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-guide-to-eifu-electronic-instructions-for-use</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-guide-to-eifu-electronic-instructions-for-use"><![CDATA[<p>Electronic Instructions for Use (eIFUs) are set to revolutionise how medical device instructions are delivered. A recent EU survey has paved the way for significant expansion, enabling more devices to move away from traditional paper IFUs. This article breaks down the key changes and what they mean for you.</p>
  <p>The EU MDR establishes the general requirements for instructions for use (IFU). <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2021/2226/oj/eng">Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/2226</a> determines which devices can use Electronic Instructions for Use (eIFUs), and which must use physical IFUs. In this article, we will review its key information and how it affects the medical device industry and examine a new draft amendment to the legislation.</p>
  <p>The legislation defines instructions for use in electronic form as “<em>instructions for use displayed in electronic form by the device, contained in portable storage media supplied by the manufacturer together with the device, or made available through a software or a website.</em>” Essentially, eIFUs are digital instructions, accessible via the device, storage media, software, or a website.</p>
  <p>For a more detailed look at what needs to go in your IFU, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/eu-mdr-requirements-writing-ifu-what-you-need-know-mantrasystems-1wpee/">check out our recent article</a> on the topic.</p>
  <h2 id="which-devices-can-currently-have-an-eifu">Which devices can currently have an eIFU?</h2>
  <p>While all manufacturers must provide an electronic copy of the IFU on their website, they may currently only be provided instead of paper for the following categories of devices:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Implantable and active implantable devices and their accessories (e.g. pacemakers)</li>
    <li>Fixed medical devices and their accessories (e.g. MRI scanner)</li>
    <li>Medical devices and their accessories fitted with a built-in system for visually displaying the instructions for use (e.g. ultrasound equipment)</li>
    <li>If a device fits into one of these groups, it must also be intended for use only by professional users and have undergone a comprehensive risk analysis as discussed below.</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="eifu-and-software-as-a-medical-device-samd">eIFU and Software as a Medical Device (SaMD)</h3>
  <p>For SaMD covered by the MDR, eIFUs are permitted for devices intended for use by all user types, including lay persons. Manufacturers may provide eIFUs using the software itself instead of in paper form.</p>
  <h2 id="why-was-the-amendment-introduced">Why was the amendment introduced?</h2>
  <p>The Commission carried out a survey on replacing paper-based IFUs with eIFUs from 1st August to 10th October 2024. The survey results showed a clear preference among healthcare professionals for receiving IFUs electronically rather than on paper. They concluded that providing IFUs in electronic form helps the health sector deliver better and faster solutions.</p>
  <p>The amendment proposes broadening the scope of application of IR (EU) 2021/2226 to “all medical devices and their accessories covered by the EU MDR <strong><em>that are intended for professional users</em></strong>”.</p>
  <p>More significantly, the Commission are currently collecting feedback from stakeholders on the proposed amendment, so <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/better-regulation/have-your-say/initiatives/14470-Medical-devices-electronic-instructions-for-use_en">complete their survey</a> to have your say and make sure your voice is heard.</p>
  <h2 id="risk-assessment-and-eifus">Risk assessment and eIFUs</h2>
  <p>Devices utilising eIFUs must undergo the same comprehensive risk assessment as all devices under the EU MDR. IR 2021/22226 supplements this with additional areas which the risk assessment must cover:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>That the user has access, knowledge and experience of the hardware and software needed to display the instructions for use in electronic form.</li>
    <li>Safeguards are needed to ensure that the electronic data and content are protected from tampering, and that backup mechanisms are in place in case of a hardware or software fault.</li>
    <li>Foreseeable medical emergencies requiring the provision of information in paper form, and an evaluation of the period within which a paper IFU shall be provided upon request.</li>
    <li>The impact caused by the temporary unavailability of the specific website or the internet in general.</li>
    <li>Assessment of the website’s compatibility and usability, and its ability to display eIFUs of multiple different devices while minimising the risk of users looking at the wrong eIFU.</li>
    <li>The management of different versions of the eIFU.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Manufacturers can only proceed with an eIFU if this risk assessment demonstrates no decreased level of safety compared to a paper IFU.</p>
  <h2 id="further-requirements-for-manufacturers">Further requirements for manufacturers</h2>
  <p>If manufacturers provide only an eIFU, they must follow these obligations:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>They must have a system in place to provide a paper IFU at no additional cost to the user at the latest within 7 days of receiving a request from a user.</li>
    <li>The existence of an eIFU must be indicated on the label.</li>
    <li>eIFUs must be available on their website in any official language of the EU, as per the member state in which the device is used.</li>
    <li>All historical eIFUs shall be available on their website.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The new draft amendment to the regulation also stipulates that eIFUs must be available through a persistently accessible URL, which the manufacturer shall provide to the UDI database.</p>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>eIFUs offer many benefits to both manufacturers and users. They are often easier to access, reduce physical IFU production costs, and can be updated far more quickly than paper IFUs. They are, however, limited by poor internet access and user interface design challenges.</p>
  <p>The future of IFUs is digital, delivering cost savings, faster updates, and improved accessibility. Navigating the regulatory landscape can be challenging, but with Mantra Systems, you can move forward with confidence. <a href="/contact">Act now — partner with us</a> to ensure your eIFUs are compliant and your devices are approved without delay.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>william-brambley</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Electronic Instructions for Use (eIFUs) are set to revolutionise how medical device instructions are delivered. We explore what this means for you.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating Risk Management Requirements under the EU MDR</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-risk-management-requirements-under-eu-mdr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating Risk Management Requirements under the EU MDR" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T10:59:18+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-risk-management-requirements-under-eu-mdr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/navigating-risk-management-requirements-under-eu-mdr"><![CDATA[<p>Risk management is a cornerstone of EU MDR 2017/745, requiring a continuous, well-documented approach to ensure patient safety. This article unpacks the key requirements and provides actionable strategies for compliance.</p>
  <p><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk management</a> is a significant component of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/745/oj/eng">EU MDR 2017/745</a> and is vital to ensure the safety of patients and medical device users. A thorough approach to risk management activities is essential for medical device manufacturers to demonstrate conformity with the requirements of the EU MDR. In this article, we will explore the requirements placed on medical device manufacturers by the EU MDR and provide an overview on how to address them.</p>
  <h2 id="what-are-the-requirements">What are the requirements?</h2>
  <p>Article 10, point 2 of the EU MDR stipulates that manufacturers are required to establish, document, implement and maintain a system for risk management. It can therefore be clearly interpreted that risk management must be an ongoing process throughout the lifecycle of a device, rather than a ‘one-off’ exercise. A continuous approach to risk management is pivotal in ensuring compliance with regulatory complaints and, moreover, safeguarding patients and device users from avoidable harm.</p>
  <p>A more detailed breakdown of risk management requirements can be found in Annex I, points 2-8 of the EU MDR. In summary, the points stipulate that manufacturers must:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Reduce risks as far as possible without negatively affecting the benefit/risk profile of a device.</li>
    <li>Establish, document, implement and maintain a risk management system throughout the entire lifecycle of a device. This process includes:
      <ul>
        <li>Development of a risk management plan</li>
        <li>Identification of known and foreseeable hazards associated with the device</li>
        <li>Evaluation of risks associated with the device during intended and reasonably foreseeable misuse</li>
        <li>Implementation of measures to control or eliminate identified risks</li>
        <li>Incorporation of information gathered during device production and <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">post-market surveillance (PMS)</a> regarding the frequency of identified risks</li>
        <li>Implementation/amendment of risk control measures to address new risks, or risks with greater frequency than initially forecast, based on information obtained through PMS activities.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Manage risks to an extent that the residual risk associated with each hazard, and the overall residual risk of a device, is acceptable.</li>
    <li>Inform users of any residual risks</li>
    <li>Reduce or eliminate risks relating to user error</li>
    <li>Ensure that the safety of patients and device users is not affected by the impact of stresses and environmental factors on device performance under normal conditions of use throughout the lifetime of the device.</li>
    <li>Design, manufacture and package devices in a manner that ensures their characteristics and performance are not affected during storage and transport.</li>
    <li>Ensure that all foreseeable risks and undesirable side effects are reduced as far as possible and deemed acceptable when weighed against the benefit of a device to patients and users.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Annex I, point 9 refers to the requirement for devices without an intended medical purpose, as outlined in Annex XVI, to present no risk at all or a risk that is no greater than the maximum acceptable risk related to the device’s use. Interpretation of this statement would infer that, for devices without an intended medical purpose that remain governed by MDR, the level of acceptable risk is minimal. Devices falling under this bracket include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Contact lenses and other products intended to be introduced onto or into the eye</li>
    <li>Products intended to be totally or partially inserted into the body through surgically invasive means for modifying anatomy or the fixation of body parts, excluding tattooing products and piercings</li>
    <li>Facial, dermal or mucous membrane fillers</li>
    <li>Equipment for the destruction, reduction of removal of adipose tissue, such as those used in liposuction and lipolysis</li>
    <li>Equipment emitting high-intensity electromagnetic radiation for use on the human body, such as lasers and pulsed light equipment used in skin resurfacing, tattoo or hair removal</li>
    <li>Equipment intended to modify neuronal activity in the brain by applying electrical currents or magnetic or electromagnetic fields that penetrate the cranium</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="how-do-we-meet-the-requirements">How do we meet the requirements?</h2>
  <p>One approach to meeting the requirements for risk management is to align risk management procedures with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/quick-guide-iso-14971-risk-management-mantrasystems-xwtne/">BS EN ISO 14971</a>, since the standard is aligned with the General Safety and Performance Requirements of the EU MDR.</p>
  <p>BS EN ISO 14971 describes 6 distinct steps in the overall risk management process, as demonstrated below:</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/risk-management-processes.svg" alt="A diagram of a risk management process" loading="lazy" width="520" height="416" />
    <figcaption>A risk management process</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <h2 id="risk-management-plan">Risk Management Plan</h2>
  <p>It is essential that all activities conducted during risk management are planned and that this plan is documented. A robust risk management plan will describe the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Assignment of responsibilities and authorities for risk management processes.</li>
    <li>A roadmap for risk management activities to be conducted, based on the 6 defined process steps in BS EN ISO 14971.</li>
    <li>A procedure for the identification and analysis of risks associated with the device throughout its lifetime.</li>
    <li>Criteria for determination of risk acceptability.</li>
    <li>A procedure for the identification and implementation of appropriate risk control measures.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>A procedure for the evaluation of individual and overall residual risks following the implementation of risk control measures.</p>
  <p>A process for the collection and review of production and post-production information.</p>
  <h2 id="risk-assessment">Risk Assessment</h2>
  <p>Risk assessment involves the analysis of risks by identifying all relevant hazards, hazardous situations and harms, and estimating the probability and severity of identified risks. In order to provide a framework for the identification of risks, it is beneficial to consider the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Definition of intended use:
      <ul>
        <li>Intended medical indication and target medical condition</li>
        <li>Target patient population
          <ul>
            <li>Demographics</li>
            <li>Disease state and stage</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Part of body/type of tissue the device interacts with</li>
        <li>Device user profile
          <ul>
            <li>Age</li>
            <li>Medical professionals and/or laypersons</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Use environment</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Definition of reasonably foreseeable misuse:
      <ul>
        <li>Accidental use error</li>
        <li>Use under the wrong conditions</li>
        <li>Impact of intentional misuse</li>
        <li>Use for non-intended clinical indications</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Characteristics related to safety</li>
  </ul>
  <p>A comprehensive list of hazards, hazardous situations and associated harms can be identified following the definition of intended use, reasonably foreseeable misuse and characteristics related to safety. According to the definitions in BS EN ISO 14971, a hazard cannot result in harm until a sequence of events or circumstances (including normal use and reasonably foreseeable misuse) leads to a hazardous situation. Each hazard (e.g. device size too small) can be associated with several hazardous situations (e.g. pressure of device against skin), each associated with several potential harms (e.g. skin abrasion). Once a risk has been followed through from hazard to harm, it can be assessed by estimating both severity and probability of occurrence of harm that could result. A pre-determined criteria of risk acceptability, as documented in the risk management plan, can then be applied based on the estimated risk probability and severity.</p>
  <h2 id="risk-control">Risk control</h2>
  <p>The application of appropriate risk control measures to reduce the probability and/or severity of each identified potential harm, regardless of initial evaluation of acceptability, is required. This process ensures that each identified risk has been reduced as far as possible, without negatively affecting the overall benefit-risk profile of the device.</p>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/online-video-training-courses/risk-management">BS EN ISO 14971</a> sets out 3 broad risk control options for medical device manufacturers, in descending order of effectiveness, as described below:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Elimination of risk through design of the device. Examples include:
      <ul>
        <li>Design without sharp edges</li>
        <li>Make dangerous electrical equipment inaccessible</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Reduction of risk through the addition of protective measures in the medical device itself or in the manufacturing process. Examples include:
      <ul>
        <li>Alarms</li>
        <li>Protective covers</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Reduction of risk through the provision of information for the safety of device users/operators. Examples include:
      <ul>
        <li>Warnings/precautions</li>
        <li>Promotion of use of protective equipment</li>
        <li>Instructions for use</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="evaluation-of-residual-risk">Evaluation of Residual Risk</h2>
  <p>Following the implementation of control measures to each identified risk, the probability and severity of each individual risk can be re-estimated, and the previously documented risk acceptability criteria re-applied to determine individual residual risks.</p>
  <p>Risk management requirements under the EU MDR place an onus on manufacturers to also assess overall residual risk, whereby the acceptability of all residual risks taken together must be determined.  As is the case when determining the acceptability of individual risks, a pre-determined criteria of acceptability must be documented and followed when evaluating overall residual risk. The assessment of overall residual risk should consider the distribution of individual residual risks by acceptability category. For example, even in the absence of any unacceptable individual risks, if a significant proportion of individual risks are considered ‘borderline’ the overall residual risk associated with a device may be deemed unacceptable. If this is the case, manufacturers must implement additional risk control measures, consider modifying the device design and manufacturing process, or place restrictions on the intended use or users, before re-evaluating individual and overall residual risks.</p>
  <p>Manufacturers are required to disclose any significant residual risks by providing relevant information in the device labelling and Instructions for Use documentation. The disclosure of residual risks should not be confused with information for safety, which forms part of the risk control process. The disclosure of residual risk does not in itself provide information which can reduce the probability or severity of a given risk, instead providing users with an overview of the risks associated with a device that remain after risk control measures have been implemented. Further guidance on the disclosure of residual risk, and information for safety, can be found in ISO/TR 24971.</p>
  <h2 id="risk-management-review">Risk Management Review</h2>
  <p>Once all the risk management activities described above have completed, manufacturers are required to conduct a risk management review. The review must assess whether all procedures in the Risk Management Plan were adhered to and a robust conclusion that the overall residual risk of the device is acceptable must be made. Finally, practices for the collection and assessment of production and post-production information relating to the risk of the device must be decided on and documented. The processes and conclusions of the risk management review must be documented in a Risk Management Report.</p>
  <h2 id="production-and-post-production-activities">Production and Post-Production Activities</h2>
  <p>BS EN ISO 14971 describes the requirement for manufacturers to implement, document and maintain a system to collect and analyse information relating to the safety of a medical device during its production and post-production phases.</p>
  <p>The collection of relevant information should encompass feedback and data from a variety of sources, including:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Information from the supply chain relating to production and distribution of the device.</li>
    <li>Information gathered during the production process.</li>
    <li>Information from those responsible for installation and maintenance of the device.</li>
    <li>Information from users of the device.</li>
    <li>Information relating to the device or similar devices which is publicly available.</li>
    <li>Information regarding updates to the state of the art.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>When the relevant information has been collected, it must be subject to a formal review, with a focus on relevance of the information to the safety of the subject device. The review should identify the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Any hazards or hazardous situations that were not addressed during initial risk management procedures.</li>
    <li>Previously addressed hazardous situations which have become unacceptable due to the impact of collected information.</li>
    <li>If the overall residual risk remains acceptable or is now unacceptable.</li>
    <li>Updates to the acknowledged state of the art which may impact the safety profile of the device.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Following a review of information gathered during production and post-production activities, manufacturers must determine whether any action is required. This process should include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Review of the risk management file and reassessment of previously identified risks for appropriateness of the estimated severity and probability.</li>
    <li>Evaluation of new identified risks with a determination of risk acceptability, implementation of risk control measures and assessment of residual risk as previously carried out.</li>
    <li>Reassessment of overall residual risk of the device.</li>
    <li>Determination of whether actions related to already marketed devices, such as device recall, are required based on new information.</li>
    <li>Evaluation of the impact of new information on previous risk management activities.</li>
    <li>A determination of the suitability of risk management procedures by top management.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>The EU MDR places significant risk management requirements on manufacturers of all medical devices. In order to demonstrate compliance, a detailed, well-documented. procedure-driven approach to all aspects of risk management must be implemented. In addition, risk management procedures must be viewed as an ongoing process throughout the lifetime of a device, rather than a one-off exercise.</p>
  <p>Though risk management compliance may seem daunting for manufacturers, embracing the requirements is an opportunity for manufacturers to support the safety of their device, and to utilise the data gathered to adopt a strong position in the market.</p>
  <p>At Mantra Systems, we have a dedicated team of clinical and regulatory professionals ready to help you with all aspects of risk management for your medical device. Want to learn more? <a href="/contact">Why not book in a consultation with one of our experts today</a>?</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>peter-boxall</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a cornerstone of EU MDR 2017/745, requiring a continuous, well-documented approach. We unpack key requirements and provide actionable strategies.]]></summary></entry></feed>