<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-19T08:44:59+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">Extending the Validity of your IVDD Certificates – Key Dates</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/extending-validity-of-ivdd-certficates-key-dates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extending the Validity of your IVDD Certificates – Key Dates" /><published>2025-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T18:51:33+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/extending-validity-of-ivdd-certficates-key-dates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/extending-validity-of-ivdd-certficates-key-dates"><![CDATA[<p>The EU and the MHRA have extended the validity of IVDD certificates, allowing you more time to <a href="/solutions/mdd-mdr-transition-legacy-devices">transition to the IVDR</a>. In this article, Kamiya Crabtree explains what this means for you.</p>
      <p>Recently, <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/dfd7a1c6-f319-4682-9bac-77bef1165818_en">the EU has extended the validity of EU IVDD</a> (In Vitro Diagnostic Medical Device Directive) certificates and declarations. The EU has updated the timelines for IVD devices to align with the EU In Vitro Diagnostic Devices Regulation (2017/746) (EU IVDR). As a result, devices with EU IVDD certificates will now be allowed to remain on the EU market for a longer period of time.</p>
      <p>Previously, IVDD CE certificates and declarations of conformity were set to expire on 26th May 2025. Under the updated transitional provisions, the validity of certain certificates and declarations has been extended as follows:</p>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Device classification</th>
            <th>New deadline</th>
            <th>Applies as long as…</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <th>Annex II List A devices</th>
            <td rowspan="4">31st December 2027</td>
            <td rowspan="3">The CE certificate was issued after 25th May 2017 and was still valid on 26th May 2022.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Annex II List B devices</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Self-test devices</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>General IVD devices that have been upclassified to Class D IVD devices</th>
            <td rowspan="4">The declaration of conformity was drawn up before 26th May 2022.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>General IVD devices that have been upclassified to Class C IVD devices</th>
            <td>31st December 2028</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>General IVD devices that have been upclassified to Class B IVD devices</th>
            <td rowspan="2">31st December 2029</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Class A devices placed on the market in a sterile condition</th>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <p>Key points to note:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Notified Bodies are not required to change the date on the individual certificates</li>
        <li>The above dates are subject to meeting the relevant conditions under EU IVDR Article 110(3c)</li>
        <li>If your device is being placed on both the GB and NI markets, you should upload a single declaration confirming that the Article 110 extended CE certificate validity applies to both markets.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Unsure which IVDR classification applies to your product? <a href="/articles/understanding-risk-based-classification-of-in-vitro-medical-devices-under-eu-ivdr">Find out more about what the new classification system means for you</a>.</p>
      <h2 id="extended-validity-in-the-uk">Extended validity in the UK</h2>
      <p>The MHRA (Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency) <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/registration-of-in-vitro-diagnostic-devices-with-expiring-ce-certificates/registration-of-certain-in-vitro-diagnostic-devices">has issued new guidance on the impact of these new deadlines on the UK</a>.</p>
      <h3 id="great-britain-gb--england-wales-and-scotland">Great Britain (GB) – England, Wales, and Scotland</h3>
      <p>To support the safe supply of medical devices to GB and make the transition to the new regulatory framework smoother, the government has put in place legislation that extends the acceptance of CE-marked IVD devices. This means that CE-marked IVD devices, whether compliant with the EU IVDD or the EU IVDR, can continue to be placed on the GB market until the 30th June 2030 (or until the certificate expires).</p>
      <p>This is great news because it allows certain devices to stay on the market longer. However, there’s a key limitation: general IVD devices that were previously not required to involve a Notified Body under the EU IVDD will only be allowed on the GB market if they are upclassified (meaning the involvement of a Notified Body is now required under the EU IVDR).</p>
      <p>It’s also important to note that manufacturers won’t be able to use expired certificates, unless the EU has deemed them valid under specific conditions.</p>
      <p>So, if you’re relying on an EU IVDD CE certificate with extended validity under Article 110 to place devices on the GB market, be sure to <a href="https://aic.mhra.gov.uk/era/drsystem.nsf/a508926735cb834f802576880054e0c3/0afbc51d01dee249802577f0003861bb">update the MHRA Device Online Registration System</a> as outlined in the guidance. The devices can stay on the market until the 30th June 2030 (or until the certificate expires).</p>
      <h3 id="northern-ireland-ni">Northern Ireland (NI)</h3>
      <p>The rules for placing IVD devices on the NI market are different from those for GB. Since 26th May 2022, the EU IVDR has applied in both EU Member States and Northern Ireland.</p>
      <p>CE certificates with extended validity under the EU IVDR transitional arrangements (Article 110) can still be used to place devices on the NI market, as long as EU IVDD CE-marked medical devices are accepted.</p>
      <p>For these devices to be valid on the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/medical-devices-eu-regulations-for-mdr-and-ivdr">NI market</a>, they must meet the conditions set out in Article 110(3c), including:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Continued compliance with Directive 98/79/EC</li>
        <li>No significant changes to the design or intended purpose</li>
        <li>No unacceptable risk to the health or safety of patients, users, or others, or to public health protection</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Additionally, there are some important steps you must follow:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>By 26th May 2025, you’ll need to provide evidence that you’ve implemented a quality management system in accordance with EU IVDR Article 10(8).</li>
        <li>By 26th May 2025, you’ll also need to provide evidence that you or your authorised representative have made a formal application to a Notified Body.</li>
        <li>By 26th September 2025, you must provide evidence that both the Notified Body and the manufacturer have signed a written agreement.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If you plan to rely on an EU IVDD CE certificate with extended validity under Article 110 for placing devices on the NI market, the MHRA encourages you to reflect this on the <a href="https://aic.mhra.gov.uk/era/drsystem.nsf/a508926735cb834f802576880054e0c3/0afbc51d01dee249802577f0003861bb">MHRA Device Online Registration System</a>.</p>
      <h3 id="previously-expired-certificates">Previously expired certificates</h3>
      <p>If you want to rely on a certificate that expired before 9th July 2024 but was still valid on 26th May 2022, you must upload a letter from the Notified Body. This letter should confirm that they’ve received the manufacturer’s application for conformity assessment and that a written agreement has been finalised.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, you could upload a completed template instead of the letter, which should declare that the key conditions for extending the certificate under EU IVDR Article 110 have been met. These conditions include:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A signed contract with the Notified Body that was in place before the certificate expired, or</li>
        <li>If no contract existed at the time of expiry, confirmation that the manufacturer had received a derogation from conformity assessment procedures under Article 54(1) of the EU IVDR, or</li>
        <li>Confirmation that they were allowed extra time to complete the conformity assessment as per Article 92(1) of the EU IVDR.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3 id="certificates-expiring-on-or-after-9th-july-2024">Certificates expiring on or after 9th July 2024</h3>
      <p>If you intend to rely on a certificate that was valid on 26th May 2022 and has expired on or after 9th July 2024, you must upload a letter from the Notified Body confirming that they have received the manufacturer’s application for conformity assessment and that a written agreement has been finalised.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, instead of the letter, you can upload a declaration stating that the certificate remains valid under <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng">EU IVDR Article 110</a>.</p>
      <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
      <p>Navigating the evolving landscape of IVDR compliance can be complex. These updated guidelines offer crucial clarity, streamlining the process and ensuring your devices maintain market access. From extended certificate validity to essential documentation, staying informed is key.</p>
      <p>Following these guidelines will help ensure the ongoing safety, quality, and regulatory compliance of your IVD products. To successfully navigate the transition to IVDR, be sure to explore <a href="/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period">our latest article</a> for an in-depth guide on what steps you need to take.</p>
      <p>Stay informed on the latest IVDR updates and their potential impact by subscribing to our newsletter below.</p>
      ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The EU and the MHRA have extended the validity of IVDD certificates, allowing you more time to transition to the IVDR. We explain what this means for manufacturers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSPR 1: A New Era of Performance with Safety at the Core</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gspr-1-a-new-era-of-performance-with-patient-safety-at-the-core" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSPR 1: A New Era of Performance with Safety at the Core" /><published>2025-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-13T18:39:33+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gspr-1-a-new-era-of-performance-with-patient-safety-at-the-core</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gspr-1-a-new-era-of-performance-with-patient-safety-at-the-core"><![CDATA[<p>In order to be effective and successful in patient care, the safety and performance of medical devices is paramount. The General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs) are a key aspect of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32017R0745">Medical Device Regulation (MDR)</a> and <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32017R0746"><em>In Vitro</em> Diagnostic Medical Device Regulation (IVDR)</a>, ensuring that medical devices in the European Union (EU) meet high standards of safety and performance. In our new GSPR series, we will take an in-depth look at each of the GSPRs, outlining the key requirements to ensure compliance.</p>
    <p>The <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/mantrasystems_medicaldevices-gspr-mdr-activity-7262434101956165632-TaAy">GSPRs</a> specify the essential requirements that medical devices must meet to be placed on the market, and they cover a wide range of topics including design and manufacturing, risk management, labelling, and instructions for use. Compliance with the GSPRs is mandatory, and failure to meet these requirements can result in serious consequences, such as product recalls, fines, or legal action.</p>
    <p>In the first article of the GSPR series, we will be taking a look at GSPR 1:</p>
    <!-- TODO: Markup properly -->
    <blockquote>
      <p>“<em>Devices shall achieve the performance intended by their manufacturer and shall be designed and manufactured in such a way that, during normal conditions of use, they are suitable for their intended purpose. They shall be safe and effective and shall not compromise the clinical condition or the safety of patients, or the safety and health of users or, where applicable, other persons, provided that any risks which may be associated with their use constitute acceptable risks when weighed against the benefits to the patient and are compatible with a high level of protection of health and safety, taking into account the generally acknowledged state of the art.</em>”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <h2 id="understanding-gspr1-the-basics">Understanding GSPR1: The Basics</h2>
    <p>GSPR 1 is one of the foundational requirements under the <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/ivdr-consulting">IVDR</a>/<a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/mdr-consulting">MDR</a>, to regulate the safety and efficacy of medical devices in the EU. It outlines a comprehensive approach to ensuring that medical devices are safe, effective, and of high quality. This specific requirement focuses on ensuring that the design and manufacturing of these devices must prioritise safety in a way that minimises risk to both patients and users.</p>
    <p>The regulation mandates that manufacturers must design their devices with a comprehensive risk management process in place. This includes identifying potential risks and mitigating them through:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Design:</strong> The design phase involves developing the device in such a way that risks to patient safety and device performance are minimised. This could mean ensuring the device operates effectively under all intended conditions, incorporating fail-safes, or using ergonomic designs that reduce the likelihood of user error.</li>
      <li><strong>Material selection:</strong> Choosing the right materials is crucial to ensure that the device is safe for its intended use. This includes considering factors such as biocompatibility, durability, and potential for allergic reactions or other adverse events.</li>
      <li><strong>Testing before the device can be marketed or used on patients:</strong> Extensive testing is required before the device can be marketed. This involves testing to confirm that the device meets the required safety and performance standards. Testing helps to identify any potential issues that may not have been apparent during the design or material selection phases.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>These safeguards are proposed to prevent harm in the short and long term.</p>
    <h2 id="gspr1-core-principles-you-need-to-know">GSPR1: Core Principles You Need to Know</h2>
    <ul>
      <li><strong><a href="/enable-ce-mark/online-video-training-courses/risk-management">Risk Management</a></strong> – A robust risk management system lies at the heart of GSPR 1. All possible hazards associated with the device, including any foreseeable misuse, need to be assessed by the manufacturer. These risk assessments must be done throughout the product’s lifetime, from design and development to production and use. One of the key aims is to ensure there is a minimal likelihood of harm, and if risks are identified, they are appropriately mitigated.</li>
      <li><strong>Quality</strong> – GSPR 1 stresses that the design and manufacturing process should ensure that the device maintains its performance for the duration of its use. The conditions that it is subjected to during its intended use should be withstood by the device, and manufacturers are to ensure its durability.</li>
      <li><strong>Biocompatibility</strong> – GSPR 1 mandates that the materials used in medical devices must be compatible with the human body, not causing any adverse reactions. Manufacturers must ensure that the material does not provoke harmful immune responses, toxicity, or irritation, regardless of whether the device will have direct or indirect contact with the patient. Biocompatibility testing is essential to verify that the materials used will not negatively affect patients. This is especially important for implantable devices or those that are used over extended periods.</li>
      <li><strong>Design Considerations</strong> – The design of the device plays a pivotal role in preventing user error. GSPR 1 requires that devices are designed in a way that reduces the risk of incorrect use – whether that be considerations like intuitive user interfaces, clear instructions, or an ergonomic design.</li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="why-gspr1-matters-key-reasons-for-compliance">Why GSPR1 Matters: Key Reasons for Compliance</h2>
    <p>GSPR 1 serves as a cornerstone of patient and user safety. By ensuring that safety and performance are prioritised from the earliest stages of design and manufacturing, this regulation aims to prevent potential harm before it happens.</p>
    <p>The requirement also fosters innovation in device design by encouraging manufacturers to continuously evaluate and enhance safety features. With an emphasis on risk management and continual improvement, GSPR 1 not only meets current needs but anticipates future challenges, allowing the medical device industry to respond effectively to evolving healthcare environments and patient needs.</p>
    <h2 id="the-bottom-line-gspr-1s-impact-on-the-future">The Bottom Line: GSPR 1’s Impact on the Future</h2>
    <p>GSPR 1 is fundamental within the MDR and IVDR and underscores the importance of designing and manufacturing devices that prioritise the safety and performance of both patients and users of the medical device. Through rigorous risk management, thought-out material selection, and user-centred design, GSPR 1 seeks to ensure that medical devices do not pose harm to those relying on them for care.</p>
    <p>Ultimately, GSPR 1 represents a commitment by the medical device industry to uphold the highest standards of safety and quality, fostering trust in devices that are critical to patient health and wellbeing.</p>
    <p>If you’re unsure whether you have the necessary evidence to demonstrate conformity with GSPR requirements, don’t worry – we’re here to help! Contact us today, and our team will provide expert guidance to ensure you’re fully compliant with all relevant GSPRs.</p>
    <p><a href="/contact">Get in touch now</a> for personalised support and peace of mind!</p>
    ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This regulation emphasizes risk management, durable design & biocompatibility to ensure medical devices are safe and effective. GSPR 1 protects users while driving innovation in medical technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybersecurity Vulnerabilities in Medical Devices: FDA Alerts on Contec and Epsimed Monitors</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/fda-alerts-cybersecurity-vulnerablities-medical-devices-contec-epsimed-monitors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybersecurity Vulnerabilities in Medical Devices: FDA Alerts on Contec and Epsimed Monitors" /><published>2025-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-13T19:42:15+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/fda-alerts-cybersecurity-vulnerablities-medical-devices-contec-epsimed-monitors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/fda-alerts-cybersecurity-vulnerablities-medical-devices-contec-epsimed-monitors"><![CDATA[<p>The FDA recently <a href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/safety-communications/cybersecurity-vulnerabilities-certain-patient-monitors-contec-and-epsimed-fda-safety-communication">issued a safety communication</a> to raise awareness of cybersecurity vulnerabilities in the Contec CMS8000 patient monitor and the Epsimed MN-120 patient monitor which may put patients at risk when connected to the internet.</p>
  <p>These vulnerabilities, which include a software backdoor, could compromise digital security and pose significant risks to patients when the devices are connected to the internet. As more medical devices become internet-connected, this development underscores the critical importance of robust cybersecurity measures in protecting patient safety and data.</p>
  <p>While the FDA’s warning highlights the risks, the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/745/oj/eng">EU Medical Device Regulations (MDR)</a> and <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng">In-Vitro Diagnostic Medical Device Regulation (IVDR)</a> introduced stricter safety requirements to address such challenges. These regulations apply to medical devices that incorporate electronic programmable systems and software, which are now classified as medical devices themselves. Manufacturers must design and manufacture devices in accordance with the state of the art by applying risk management principles, including information security. Additionally, the regulations establish minimum IT security requirements, including protection against unauthorised access.</p>
  <p>In this article we discuss cybersecurity requirements of the EU MDR and IVDR and summarise the Medical Device Coordination Group (MDCG) guidance document - <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/b23b362f-8a56-434c-922a-5b3ca4d0a7a1_en">MDCG 2019-16 Rev 1</a>: Guidance on Cybersecurity for medical devices.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-cybersecurity">What is cybersecurity?</h2>
  <p>In ISO 81001-1, cybersecurity is defined as:</p>
  <!-- TODO:Markup properly -->
  <blockquote>
    <p>“<em>a state where information and systems are protected from unauthorised activities, such as access, use, disclosure, disruption, modification, or destruction to a degree that the related risks to confidentiality, integrity, and availability are maintained at an acceptable level throughout the life cycle</em>”.</p>
  </blockquote>
  <h2 id="what-guidance-does-the-mdcg-2019-16-rev-1-provide">What guidance does the MDCG 2019-16 Rev 1 provide?</h2>
  <p>The MDCG 2019-16 Rev 1 provides guidance on fulfilling the general safety and performance requirements of Annex I of the EU MDR and IVDR concerning cybersecurity. It emphasises a “secure by design” approach, integrating cybersecurity into every stage of a medical device’s lifecycle. This includes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Security Risk Management:</strong> Manufacturers must establish a process to identify, evaluate, and mitigate cybersecurity risks, aligning with the overall risk management system required by the MDR.</li>
    <li><strong>Security Capabilities:</strong> Devices should incorporate essential security features such as authentication, encryption, and malware protection, tailored to their intended use and operational environment.</li>
    <li><strong>Minimum IT Requirements:</strong> Manufacturers must define and communicate the minimum IT security requirements for the device’s operating environment, including hardware and network characteristics, to ensure baseline protection.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The guidance also addresses the complex medical device supply chain, providing supplementary considerations for actors other than manufacturers. Additionally, it includes an annex outlining other EU and global legislation and guidance relevant to cybersecurity.</p>
  <h2 id="what-are-the-cybersecurity-requirements-contained-in-mdr-annex-i">What are the cybersecurity requirements contained in MDR Annex I?</h2>
  <h3 id="basic-cybersecurity-requirements">Basic Cybersecurity Requirements</h3>
  <p>Annex I of the MDR and IVDR emphasise the importance of cybersecurity in maintaining the general safety and performance requirements of medical devices with a focus on cybersecurity. The requirements are categorised into three key areas:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>IT Security:</strong> Protecting the information technology systems of medical devices is crucial. This includes safeguarding against unauthorised access and ensuring data integrity (referencing sections 17.4, 23.4ab).</li>
    <li><strong>Operation Security:</strong> Devices must operate securely under all conditions. This involves ensuring that the device functions as intended without compromising safety (referencing sections 14.1, 14.2, 17.1).</li>
    <li><strong>Information Security:</strong> Protecting sensitive data is a top priority. Medical devices must ensure that patient data and other critical information are secure from breaches (referencing section 17.2).</li>
  </ul>
  <h3 id="requirements-for-the-secure-design-and-manufacture-of-medical-devices">Requirements for the Secure Design and Manufacture of Medical Devices</h3>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/understanding-cybersecurity-requirements-for-medical-devices.svg" alt="Diagram illustrating the components considered for the cybersecurity of medical devices." loading="lazy" width="800" height="566" />
    <figcaption>Cybersecurity considerations for the design and manufacturing of medical devices</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>Cybersecurity must be integrated into every stage of a medical device’s lifecycle. Annex I of the MDR and IVDR highlights several critical aspects of secure design and manufacture:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Risk Management:</strong> Risks must be identified, assessed, and managed throughout the device’s lifecycle (sections 3, 14.4, 14.5, 19.3).</li>
    <li><strong>Protection Against Risks:</strong> Devices must be designed to protect against risks during both intended use and foreseeable misuse (sections 3c, 8).</li>
    <li><strong>Unauthorised Access:</strong> Measures must be in place to prevent unauthorised access to the device and its data (sections 17.4, 18.8).</li>
    <li><strong>Threats and Vulnerabilities:</strong> Manufacturers must identify and address security threats, vulnerabilities, and risks (section 4b).</li>
    <li><strong>Risk Control Measures:</strong> Effective risk control measures must be established to mitigate identified risks (section 4).</li>
    <li><strong>Minimum IT Security Requirements:</strong> Devices must meet minimum IT security standards to ensure baseline protection (sections 17.4, 14.5).</li>
  </ul>
  <p>A key driver of secure design and manufacturing is the <strong>state of the art</strong> (sections 1, 4, 17.2). Manufacturers should consider the state of the art when designing developing and upgrading medical devices across their life cycle. This involves incorporating the latest advancements, technologies, and best practices into their decision-making processes to address security risks proportionally and appropriately. By aligning with the state of the art, manufacturers can ensure that their devices are not only compliant with regulatory requirements but also resilient against emerging threats, safeguarding patient safety and data security over the long term.</p>
  <h3 id="how-are-the-cybersecurity-requirements-under-mdr-interrelated-to-the-other-relevant-eu-legislations-cybersecurity-act-gdpr-and-nis">How are the cybersecurity requirements under MDR interrelated to the other relevant EU legislations (Cybersecurity Act, GDPR and NIS)?</h3>
  <p>Cybersecurity requirements under the MDR are interconnected with other EU legislations, such as the Cybersecurity Act, General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), and the Network and Information Security (NIS) Directive. While the EU MDR and IVDR focus on the safety and performance of medical devices, these additional legislations address broader aspects of cybersecurity, data protection, and network security. The <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/download/b23b362f-8a56-434c-922a-5b3ca4d0a7a1_en">MDCG 2019-16 Rev 1</a> guidance provides a detailed discussion of how these requirements overlap and complement each other.</p>
  <h3 id="what-cybersecurity-activities-does-the-manufacturer-need-to-carry-out-during-the-lifecycle-of-a-medical-device-according-to-mdr">What cybersecurity activities does the manufacturer need to carry out during the lifecycle of a medical device according to MDR?</h3>
  <p>Pre-market cybersecurity activities include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Secure Design (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Risk management (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Establish Risk Control Measures (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Validation, Verification, Risk Assessment, Benefit Risk Analysis (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Technical Documentation (Annex II and III)</li>
    <li>Conformity Assessment (Article 52)</li>
    <li>Establish a Post-market Surveillance Plan and Post-market Surveillance System (Article 83 and 84)</li>
    <li>Clinical evaluation process (Chapter VI)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Post-market activities include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Risk management (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Modify Risk Control Measures /Corrective Actions/Patches (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Validation, Verification, Risk Assessment, Benefit Risk Analysis (Annex I)</li>
    <li>Maintain and update a Post-market Surveillance Plan and Post-market Surveillance System (Article 83 and 84)</li>
    <li>Trend Reporting (Article 88)</li>
    <li>Analysis of Serious Incidents (Article 89)</li>
    <li>Post-Market Surveillance Report (Article 85)</li>
    <li>Periodic Safety Update Report (Article 86)</li>
    <li>Update Technical Documentation (Annex II and III)</li>
    <li>Inform the Electronic System on Vigilance (Article 92)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Cybersecurity is a critical aspect of ensuring the safety and performance of medical devices under the EU MDR and IVDR. By adopting a secure-by-design approach, prioritising risk management, and maintaining robust post-market surveillance, manufacturers can protect patients from potential threats and ensure compliance with regulatory standards.</p>
  <p>If you need guidance on EU MDR and IVDR requirements or have concerns about cybersecurity compliance for your medical device, <a href="/contact">contact us today to arrange a free, no-obligation discussion</a>.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>clare-dixon</name></author><category term="SaMD" /><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Patients can be exposed to risks when devices are online. We explore implications for EU MDR/IVDR cybersecurity requirements, including MDCG guidance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding UDI: Your Ultimate Guide to Smarter Medical Device Labelling</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/decoding-udi-ultimate-guide-to-smarter-medical-device-labelling" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding UDI: Your Ultimate Guide to Smarter Medical Device Labelling" /><published>2025-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-10T15:31:49+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/decoding-udi-ultimate-guide-to-smarter-medical-device-labelling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/decoding-udi-ultimate-guide-to-smarter-medical-device-labelling"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-a-udi-and-why-does-it-matter">What Is a UDI and Why Does It Matter?</h2>
  <p>The <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/applying-unique-device-identifier-step-by-step-guide-mantrasystems-v7dqe/">Unique Device Identifier (UDI)</a> is a crucial element in the medical device industry, designed to enhance the traceability and safety of medical devices. Think of UDI as a sort of “digital fingerprint” for each device—a unique combination of numbers and codes that provide important details about the device, such as its model, manufacturing batch, and more. It’s like putting a <em>superpower</em> into your device packaging, empowering manufacturers, regulators, and healthcare providers to quickly identify and track a device.</p>
  <p>A UDI is made up of two core components:</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/breaking-down-the-udi.svg" alt="Diagram illustrating the UDI-DI vs UDI-PI split." loading="lazy" width="840" height="290" />
  </figure>
  <h3 id="1-udi-di-device-identifier">1. UDI-DI (Device Identifier)</h3>
  <p>This is the fixed portion of the UDI and uniquely identifies the model or version of the device. It’s used to identify the product at a high level, no matter where it is sold or used. The UDI-DI is assigned by the manufacturer and remains constant across all units of that particular device.</p>
  <h3 id="2-udi-pi-production-identifier">2. UDI-PI (Production Identifier)</h3>
  <p>The variable portion of the UDI includes critical details about the device, such as its serial number, lot number, expiry date, or manufacture date. This part of the UDI ensures the traceability of each individual unit, making it easy to track and manage the device throughout its lifecycle.</p>
  <h2 id="whats-the-udi-carrier">What’s the UDI Carrier?</h2>
  <p>The UDI carrier is the machine-readable version of the UDI that is placed on the label or packaging of the medical device. It’s typically a barcode or QR code—something that can be quickly scanned by healthcare providers, distributors, or anyone handling the device. UDI carriers make tracking the device in real-time much more efficient.</p>
  <p>There are two common forms of UDI carriers:</p>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/which-udi-carrier.svg" alt="Diagram showing which UDI carrier should be used for medical devices?" loading="lazy" width="744" height="309" />
  </figure>
  <p>In accordance with Annex VI, Part C, Section 4.1, the UDI Carrier – both the Automatic Identification and Data Capture (AIDC) and the Human Readable Interpretation (HRI) must be placed on the label, the device itself, and all higher packaging levels. However, Section 4.2 allows the UDI carrier to be placed on the next higher packaging level if space on the unit of use packaging is limited. Additionally, Section 4.3 states that for single-use devices of Classes I and IIa, the UDI carrier is not required on the individual packaging but must appear on the next higher packaging level (e.g., a carton containing multiple devices).</p>
  <h2 id="understanding-udi-and-eudamed">Understanding UDI and EUDAMED</h2>
  <p>Under the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/745/oj/eng">EU MDR 2017/745</a>, medical device manufacturers must submit UDI data to <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">EUDAMED</a> for all devices that fall under the regulation. Here’s how UDI submission fits into EUDAMED:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Manufacturers must submit UDI-DI information for each product (or product model) to EUDAMED to ensure that it is tracked in the European market.</li>
    <li>UDI-DI Data: This includes the unique identifier for each device, along with essential details such as the device’s name, model, classification, and the manufacturer’s information.</li>
    <li>EUDAMED Registration: Manufacturers must first register in EUDAMED to begin submitting UDI-DI information. Only those devices that are subject to MDR or IVDR are required to be listed in EUDAMED.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="udi-format-explained">UDI Format Explained</h2>
  <p>In the HRI format, you can see the UDI-DI, which is the number after the (01). Each time you see the 01 between brackets, this means this is the placeholder for the UDI-DI.</p>
  <p>Then, we arrive at the UDI-PI part. As mentioned, this part can vary depending on the production characteristic of the product.</p>
  <p>You can identify some numbers in the bracket on the UDI-PI part. Let’s decode them. Each of these numbers provides specific information about the product:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>(10) is for the lot number</li>
    <li>(11) is for the production date</li>
    <li>(17) defines the expiration date</li>
    <li>(21) is the serial number.</li>
  </ul>
  <p><strong>Example: (01)00827002005112­(17)000004(10)­1234(21)8234</strong></p>
  <p>All this information is dynamic and will have to change each time you have a new batch or a new expiry date.</p>
  <h2 id="the-basic-udi-di">The Basic UDI-DI</h2>
  <p>The Basic UDI-DI is an EU approach for linking devices to their regulatory documentation and it is intended to uniquely identify the product model throughout the entire life cycle of the product.</p>
  <p>The Basic UDI-DI is a primary identifier of a device model i.e. it connects devices with the same intended purpose, risk class, and essential design and manufacturing characteristics. It is also the main record key in the UDI database i.e. it connects all associated UDI-DIs in the UDI database with the information in other EUDAMED modules.</p>
  <p>You’ll have it on your:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Certificates (Notified Bodies)</li>
    <li>Declaration of conformity</li>
    <li>Technical Documentation</li>
    <li>Summary of safety and clinical performance</li>
    <li>Certificate of free sale (Article 60(1) of MDR)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>This one does not appear on the packaging of the products. It’s really an invisible number for your customers and is used solely in administration.</p>
  <h2 id="decoding-udi-strategic-takeaways">Decoding UDI: Strategic Takeaways</h2>
  <p>In conclusion, understanding and implementing the Unique Device Identifier (UDI) system is crucial for ensuring the safety, traceability, and regulatory compliance of medical devices. By breaking down the components of UDI, such as the UDI-DI, UDI-PI, and their formats (AIDC and HRI), manufacturers can streamline their processes and meet both EU and global regulatory requirements.</p>
  <p>With the correct application of UDI, medical device manufacturers enhance transparency, facilitate recalls, and ultimately contribute to better patient safety and device management in healthcare systems worldwide.</p>
  <p><a href="/contact">Contact us today</a> for a personalised consultation or to learn more about how we can help ensure your compliance with the regulations. Together, we can make the process smooth and efficient, protecting both your business and patients.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>kamiya-crabtree</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Unique Device Identifier (UDI) ensures medical device traceability and compliance. We break down its structure, Device Identifier (UDI-DI), Production Identifier (UDI-PI) and its role in EUDAMED.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Risk-Based Classification of In Vitro Medical Devices Under EU IVDR</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-risk-based-classification-of-in-vitro-medical-devices-under-eu-ivdr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Risk-Based Classification of In Vitro Medical Devices Under EU IVDR" /><published>2025-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-07T18:42:38+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-risk-based-classification-of-in-vitro-medical-devices-under-eu-ivdr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-risk-based-classification-of-in-vitro-medical-devices-under-eu-ivdr"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="/solutions/mdd-mdr-transition-legacy-devices">transition from IVDD to IVDR</a> replaces the list-based classification system with a risk-based approach for <em>in vitro</em> diagnostic medical devices. To ensure compliance, manufacturers must thoroughly understand the classification rules outlined in Annex VIII of the IVDR.</p>
  <h2 id="what-has-changed">What has changed?</h2>
  <p>A significant change for manufacturers with the <a href="/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period">transition from IVDD 98/79/EC to EU IVDR 2017/746</a> is the shift in classification of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostic medical devices from a “list-based” system to a “risk-based” approach.</p>
  <p>Under the IVDD, devices were categorized into List A and List B based on specific medical conditions. Devices on these lists required Notified Body submission, while all others were considered self-certifiable.</p>
  <p>In alignment with EU MDR, classification of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostic medical devices is now risk-based and moves through a system of class A, B, C and D. This classification considers both patient risk and broader public health implications. To achieve this, the IVDR makes use of 10 implementation rules and 7 classification rules to classify <em>in vitro</em> medical devices (<a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng#anx_VIII">Annex VIII IVDR</a>).</p>
  <h2 id="risk-categories-explained">Risk categories explained</h2>
  <p>The risk of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostic medical devices is assessed based on the potential consequences of an incorrect result or diagnosis.</p>
  <p>Class A is the lowest risk category. It includes general laboratory devices, instruments and specimen receptacles. Non-sterile Class A devices can self-certify for a CE mark, meaning that they do not have to complete the process of conformity through a Notified Body.</p>
  <p>Class B risk category is the default class for all <em>in vitro</em> medical devices which are not covered specifically by other classification rules. It covers devices which are considered to be lower risk to patients and to the wider population. Examples include self-testing devices for pregnancy and fertility, self-testing kits for blood cholesterol or glucose levels, and urine tests for white or red blood cells, or bacteria.</p>
  <p>Class C includes IVDs that pose a lower risk to the wider population but a higher risk to the patient if the test result is inaccurate. In these cases, a diagnostic failure could have life-threatening consequences, such as in tests for infectious diseases or cancer. This class also covers companion diagnostics and genetic screening. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/understanding-companion-diagnostics-what-you-need-know-iyche/">Companion diagnostics</a> are IVDs which provide information which is essential for the safe and effective use of a corresponding drug or biological product.</p>
  <p>The highest risk classification is Class D. This class includes IVDs which test for general life-threatening conditions, and more specifically, for highly transmissible infectious agents in blood and biological material, which may be transplanted or readministered into the body. These transmissible agents may also present a high risk to the wider population. Class D also includes IVDs for blood grouping and tissue typing.</p>
  <h2 id="consequences-of-the-new-classification-rules">Consequences of the new classification rules</h2>
  <p>A major impact of the new risk classification system under IVDR is that approximately 78% of IVDs now require Notified Body certification, a significant increase from just 8% under the previous IVDD1. Initially there was a backlog in conformity assessments due to the low number of IVDR designated NBs. However, that has been rectified to some extent, with 12 notified bodies designated for IVDR submissions as of October 2024.</p>
  <p>Results from a recent Notified Body survey2 on certifications and applications, performed by the European Commission, found that one of the primary reasons for IVDR application refusals of IVDR applications was “wrong qualification/classification of device”. This highlights the importance of understanding and implementing the classification rules of Annex VII of the IVDR prior to the production of the technical file.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The transition from IVDD replaces list-based classification with a risk-based approach. Manufacturers must thoroughly understand the rules outlined in Annex VIII of the IVDR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IMDRF Sets the Standard: 10 Key Principles for AI-enabled Medical Devices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/imdrf-ets-the-standard-10-principles-ai-medical-devices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IMDRF Sets the Standard: 10 Key Principles for AI-enabled Medical Devices" /><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T14:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/imdrf-ets-the-standard-10-principles-ai-medical-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/imdrf-ets-the-standard-10-principles-ai-medical-devices"><![CDATA[<p>The International Medical Device Regulators Forum (IMDRF) has released a new document outlining ten guiding principles for <a href="https://www.imdrf.org/documents/good-machine-learning-practice-medical-device-development-guiding-principles">Good Machine Learning Practice (GMLP)</a> in the development of medical devices that incorporate artificial intelligence (AI), including machine learning. This document is intended to promote the development of safe, effective, and <a href="/solutions/regulatory-consulting-for-samd-software-as-a-medical-device">high-quality AI-enabled medical devices</a>.</p>
  <p>The ten guiding principles are:</p>
  <ol>
    <li><strong>Well-defined intended use:</strong> AI-enabled medical devices must be designed and used to address clinically meaningful needs. This requires a thorough understanding of the device’s intended use, benefits, and risks throughout its lifecycle. Multidisciplinary expertise should be leveraged to ensure safety and effectiveness.</li>
    <li><strong>Good software engineering, medical device design, and security practices:</strong> It is vital to ensure robust software engineering practices are implemented throughout the product life cycle. This can be achieved by using validated quality management systems and quality assurance tools, as well as following strict data management and cybersecurity protocols. This also includes having well-structured risk management and design processes to ensure confidence in the outputs of the model.</li>
    <li><strong><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical evaluation</a> with representative datasets:</strong> Data collection protocols must ensure the datasets used for training, testing, and monitoring the AI model sufficiently represent the intended patient population, use environment, and inputs. This helps manage bias, promote generalisability, assess usability, and identify potential underperformance.</li>
    <li><strong>Independent training and test datasets:</strong> Training and test datasets should be selected and maintained independently of one another. All potential sources of dependence, including factors related to patients, sites, and data acquisition, should be considered and addressed.</li>
    <li><strong>Fit-for-purpose reference standards:</strong> Accepted methods for developing reference standards should be used to ensure that clinically relevant and well-characterised data is collected. The limitations of reference standards should be understood, and the rationale for their choice should be documented based on the device’s intended use and assessment of their suitability for the intended use environment.</li>
    <li><strong>Model choice and design tailored to data and intended use:</strong> The choice and design of the AI model should be evaluated and shown to be suitable for the available data and support the mitigation of known risks such as overfitting, performance degradation, and security risks. The clinical benefits and risks related to the product should be well understood and used to derive clinically meaningful performance goals for testing.</li>
    <li><strong>Assessment of human-AI interactions:</strong> Device performance should be evaluated within its intended use environment and clinical workflow, considering interactions with all users. Human factors like user skills, understanding of model outputs, potential for overreliance, device autonomy, and user error should be addressed for both normal use and foreseeable misuse.</li>
    <li><strong>Performance testing in clinically relevant conditions:</strong> Methodologically and statistically sound test plans should be developed and executed to generate clinically relevant device performance information independently of the training dataset. Considerations should include the intended patient population, relevant subgroups, clinical environment, use by the human-AI team, measurement inputs, and potential confounding factors.</li>
    <li><strong>Clear and essential information for users:</strong> All users (healthcare professionals, patients, etc.) must receive clear, relevant information about the product’s intended use, indications, benefits, risks, performance, and limitations. This includes details about the model’s development, data used, inputs, outputs, and user interface. Users should also be informed about device updates and have a way to report concerns to the manufacturer.</li>
    <li><strong>Monitoring of deployed models and management of re-training risks:</strong> Deployed models should be capable of ongoing monitoring in real-world use with a focus on maintaining or improving safety and performance. When models are retrained after deployment, appropriate controls should be in place to manage risks of overfitting, unintended bias, or degradation of the model that may impact safety and performance.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>These guiding principles are a call to action for international standards organisations, regulators, and other collaborative bodies to further advance GMLP. Areas of collaboration include research, educational tools and resources, international harmonisation, and consensus standards to inform regulatory policies and guidelines.</p>
  <figure class="inline">
    <div class="image bordered">
      <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/good-machine-learning-practice-diagram.svg" alt="Diagram illustrating what is considered a good machine learning process." loading="lazy" width="800" height="700" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>Good Machine Learning Practice</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>The IMDRF emphasises the importance of GMLP in the context of evolving AI technologies, particularly generative AI. Generative AI presents unique considerations and potential risks, such as the use of foundation models not under the provenance of medical device manufacturers. The regulatory science of measuring performance and characterising and detecting errors in these models is maturing to meet these challenges.</p>
  <p>As the field of AI medical devices continues to evolve, so too must GMLP and consensus standards. The IMDRF’s publication of these guiding principles is a significant step in promoting the safe and effective development of AI-enabled medical devices. Medical device manufacturers should familiarise themselves with these principles and incorporate them into their development processes to ensure compliance and maintain patient safety.</p>
  <p><a href="/newsletter">Subscribe to our newsletter</a> for the latest updates on this rapidly changing field. If you have any questions, <a href="/solutions/regulatory-consulting-for-samd-software-as-a-medical-device">book a free, no-obligation call</a> with one of our Software as a Medical Device (SaMD) experts.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>ron-sangal</name></author><category term="SaMD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Good Machine Learning Practice (GMLP) principles ensure safe devices, covering intended use, clinical evaluation & Human-AI Interaction (HAII).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Key Updates for Navigating EMDN: MDCG 2024-2 Rev.1 &amp;amp; 2021-12 Rev.1</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/key-updates-navigating-emdn-mdcg-2024-2-2021-12-revision-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Key Updates for Navigating EMDN: MDCG 2024-2 Rev.1 &amp;amp; 2021-12 Rev.1" /><published>2025-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T11:50:56+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/key-updates-navigating-emdn-mdcg-2024-2-2021-12-revision-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/key-updates-navigating-emdn-mdcg-2024-2-2021-12-revision-1"><![CDATA[<p>The Medical Device Coordination Group (MDCG) has released revised guidance documents, <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/de470384-e8be-45e7-a334-226757f8816d_en">MDCG 2024-2 Rev.1</a> and <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/d90b3f63-1d62-43e6-bf5f-fb32ea7c47a2_en">2021-12 Rev.1</a>, focusing on the European Medical Device Nomenclature (EMDN). This update, released in January 2025, provides critical clarifications and insights for medical device manufacturers, aiming to ensure accurate and consistent use of the EMDN system.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-the-emdn-and-how-does-it-affect-me">What is the EMDN, and how does it affect me?</h2>
  <p>The EMDN is a standardised system for classifying and identifying medical devices within the European Union. Introduced under Article 26 of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/745/oj/eng">Medical Device Regulation (MDR) (EU) 2017/745</a> and Article 23 of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng">In Vitro Diagnostic Medical Device Regulation (IVDR) (EU) 2017/746</a>, the EMDN plays a crucial role in the functioning of the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/eudamed">European Database on Medical Devices (EUDAMED)</a>.</p>
  <p>Manufacturers utilise the EMDN to register their devices in EUDAMED, linking each device with a Unique Device Identifier - Device Identifier (UDI-DI). Beyond registration, the EMDN is vital for device documentation, notified body assessments, post-market surveillance, vigilance activities, and data analysis. It serves as a key reference for all stakeholders, including patients, providing clear device descriptions and promoting transparency in the medical device market. The EMDN is reviewed and updated annually based on user feedback and practical use.   </p>
  <h2 id="key-changes-at-a-glance">Key changes at a glance</h2>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: left">Update</th>
        <th style="text-align: left">Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">New and revised FAQs</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">The guidance document includes a restructured FAQ section with new questions and clarifications on various aspects of the EMDN.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Code granularity</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Manufacturers are reminded to use the most specific and detailed (terminal) EMDN code available for each device.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Multiple codes</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Clearer instructions are provided for using multiple EMDN codes for devices with multiple intended purposes, especially complex systems.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Code gaps</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">A process for proposing new EMDN codes when existing codes are not suitable is outlined, ensuring the nomenclature stays current.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Annual review and updates</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">The importance of staying informed about annual EMDN updates and making necessary changes to device registrations and documentation is emphasised.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: left">Obsolete and split codes</td>
        <td style="text-align: left">Clear procedures for managing obsolete and split codes in EUDAMED are provided, including archiving and public accessibility.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>The updated guidance document features a restructured FAQ section with new questions addressing specific aspects of EMDN implementation and management. Some of the key areas covered include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>EMDN Code Assignment:</strong> The document emphasises assigning the most granular and terminal code available to each device in EUDAMED. It clarifies the use of multiple codes for devices with multiple intended purposes, particularly complex systems with diverse functions.</li>
    <li><strong>Handling Code Gaps:</strong> If an appropriate EMDN term is not available, manufacturers are advised to use the code extension ‘99’ (‘Other’) and submit a proposal for a new code. This ensures the EMDN stays current with technological advancements and evolving device types.</li>
    <li><strong>Annual EMDN Review:</strong> The update highlights the annual EMDN update cycle and the importance of timely updates to EUDAMED entries and related documentation. Manufacturers are encouraged to review the updated EMDN annually to identify any changes impacting their devices and notify their notified bodies accordingly.</li>
    <li><strong>Code Updates and EUDAMED:</strong> The guidance provides clear instructions on handling obsolete or split codes in EUDAMED. Obsolete codes remain visible for a period, allowing for a smooth transition, while split codes are archived and made publicly accessible.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="annual-revision-process">Annual revision process</h2>
  <figure>
    <div class="image">
      <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/emdn-annual-revision-process-diagram.png" alt="Diagram showing the annual update cycle of the EMDN annual revision process." loading="lazy" width="800" height="705" />
    </div>
  </figure>
  <p>MDCG <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/de470384-e8be-45e7-a334-226757f8816d_en">2024-2 Rev.1</a> contains a detailed explanation of the annual EMDN revision process. The most important part of the process for manufacturers is the collection of requests step. EMDN users, including competent authorities, notified bodies, manufacturers, and other stakeholders, can submit requests for changes to the EMDN through a dedicated platform. The deadline for submitting requests for processing in that same year is 31st January.  </p>
  <p>These requests are then reviewed by the EMDN Technical Team (EMDN-TT) and the MDCG Nomenclature Working Group (NOM WG) over the course of the year before finally being published to EUDAMED by the end of the year.</p>
  <p>In addition to the annual update cycle, a pilot procedure for ad-hoc updates requiring expedited review has been introduced. This ad-hoc process is limited to new code requests and is only available to competent authorities and notified bodies.  </p>
  <h2 id="what-does-this-mean-for-me">What does this mean for me?</h2>
  <p>This update underscores the importance of staying informed about EMDN changes and ensuring accurate EMDN code assignment for all medical devices. Manufacturers must proactively engage with the annual EMDN review process, participate in code update proposals, and maintain accurate device information in EUDAMED.</p>
  <p>By adhering to these guidelines manufacturers can:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Enhance Regulatory Compliance:</strong> Accurate EMDN coding is crucial for meeting regulatory requirements and avoiding potential issues with notified bodies and market access.</li>
    <li><strong>Improve Data Quality:</strong> Consistent and precise EMDN coding contributes to the quality and reliability of data in EUDAMED, supporting effective post-market surveillance and regulatory decision-making.</li>
    <li><strong>Increase Transparency:</strong> Clear and standardised device identification through the EMDN promotes transparency for patients, healthcare professionals, and other stakeholders.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>The MDCG have provided valuable guidance for medical device manufacturers navigating the EMDN system. By understanding and implementing these guidelines, manufacturers can ensure accurate device classification, maintain regulatory compliance, and contribute to a transparent and well-functioning medical device market.</p>
  <p>Navigating the complexities of EMDN and EUDAMED can be challenging. Partnering with Mantra Systems allows you to focus on your core business while we handle the intricacies of EMDN compliance. <a href="/contact">Book a free, no-obligation chat with one of our regulatory experts</a> to see how we can help.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>ron-sangal</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Release of the updated guidance helps manufacturers navigate the EMDN system for accurate device classification, ensuring market access.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From IVDD to IVDR: Ensuring Compliance During the Transitional Period</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From IVDD to IVDR: Ensuring Compliance During the Transitional Period" /><published>2025-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-29T09:49:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ivdd-ivdr-ensuring-compliance-during-transitional-period"><![CDATA[<p>The European Union <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2017/746/oj/eng">In Vitro Diagnostic Regulation (EU IVDR 2017/746)</a> has transformed the medical device industry. Replacing the In Vitro Diagnostic Directive (IVDD 98/79/EC), <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/ivdr-consulting">the IVDR</a> establishes more rigorous standards to enhance the safety, performance, and quality of in vitro diagnostic medical devices (IVDs).</p>
  <p>However, the transition from IVDD to IVDR can be complex and manufacturers of legacy devices must navigate a range of considerations to ensure compliance while adapting to the new regulatory landscape.</p>
  <h2 id="maintaining-regulatory-compliance-during-the-ivdd-to-ivdr-transition">Maintaining Regulatory Compliance During the IVDD-to-IVDR Transition</h2>
  <p>To facilitate a smooth transition, IVDD-compliant legacy devices may continue to be placed on the market until the following deadlines:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Class D devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2027</strong>.</li>
    <li><strong>Class C devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2028</strong>.</li>
    <li><strong>Class B and Class A sterile devices:</strong> Compliance required by <strong>31 December 2029</strong>.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>These <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/document/dfd7a1c6-f319-4682-9bac-77bef1165818_en">extended timelines</a> aim to provide manufacturers with the opportunity to adjust to the IVDR. However, continuing to market legacy devices during this period is conditional upon strict adherence to specific requirements.</p>
  <h2 id="conditions-for-placing-ivdd-compliant-devices-on-the-market">Conditions for Placing IVDD-Compliant Devices on the Market</h2>
  <p>Legacy devices may remain on the market during the transition period only if the following conditions are met:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>The device must remain fully compliant with the IVDD.</li>
    <li>There are no significant changes to device design or intended purpose.</li>
    <li>The device does not present an unacceptable risk to patient or user health and safety, nor to public health.</li>
    <li>By <strong>26 May 2025</strong>, the manufacturer must have implemented a Quality Management System (QMS) in accordance with Article 10(8) of the IVDR.</li>
    <li>A formal application must have been lodged with a notified body (as per section 4.3, Annex VII) for conformity assessment no later than the 26 May 2025 for Class D devices, <strong>26 May 2026</strong> for Class C devices, and 26 May 2027 for Class B and Class A sterile devices.</li>
    <li>The manufacturer must have written agreement with the Notified Body by <strong>26 September 2025</strong> for Class D devices, <strong>26 September 2026</strong> for Class C devices, and <strong>26 September 2027</strong> for Class B and Class A sterile devices.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Failure to meet these conditions will negate compliance under transitional provisions.</p>
  <h2 id="implementing-an-ivdr-compliant-qms">Implementing an IVDR-Compliant QMS</h2>
  <p>Having an IVDR complaint QMS in place is not just about meeting regulatory requirements; it is a proactive strategy to ensure the continuous safety and performance of an IVD in a competitive market. To meet IVDR requirements, the QMS must include the following elements:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>A strategy for regulatory compliance, including management of modifications to devices.</li>
    <li>Identification of safety and performance requirements and strategies to address them.</li>
    <li>Clear management responsibility and accountability.</li>
    <li>Resource management, including oversight of suppliers and subcontractors.</li>
    <li>Comprehensive risk management in line with Annex I, Section 3.</li>
    <li>Performance evaluation, including Post-Market Performance Follow-up (PMPF) per Article 56 and Annex XIII.</li>
    <li>Processes for product realisation, from design and development to production and service.</li>
    <li>Verification of <strong>Unique Device Identifier (UDI)</strong> assignments and consistent device information management under Articles 24(3) and 26.</li>
    <li>A robust <strong>Post-Market Surveillance (PMS)</strong> system, as outlined in Article 78.</li>
    <li>Effective communication with stakeholders, including authorities, notified bodies, and customers.</li>
    <li>Processes for reporting serious incidents and implementing corrective and preventive actions (CAPA).</li>
    <li>Monitoring, measurement, and continuous product improvement.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="an-ivdr-compliant-qms-for-legacy-devices">An IVDR-Compliant QMS for Legacy Devices</h2>
  <p>Manufacturers must ensure their QMS is aligned with IVDR regulatory requirements. However, for certain aspects outlined in Article 10(8), such as points (b), (e), and (f), a distinction must be made for “legacy devices”. For these devices, manufacturers are not required to have identified all relevant safety and performance requirements, implemented comprehensive risk management, or conducted a full performance evaluation. However, it is important to note that from the 26 May 2025, manufacturers must ensure that their QMS addresses how compliance with these requirements will be achieved for legacy devices, ensuring full alignment with IVDR standards.</p>
  <p>Manufacturers have a few strategic options for updating to an IVDR-compliant QMS. One approach is to establish a parallel QMS. This approach enables clear reference to the appropriate procedures and highlights the transition to the new system. For companies with complex, long-standing QMS, it offers the chance to streamline and enhance efficiency. However, this approach demands considerable effort to develop and eventually replace the old procedures.</p>
  <p>Alternatively, companies whose existing QMS already aligns closely with the new IVDR requirements might prefer to update their current system. While this option can be more efficient, it may present challenges in ensuring that certain QMS elements are applied consistently across all products.</p>
  <p>Despite the chosen approach, documenting the transition is critical, clearly defining which procedures apply, when they take effect, and which products they impact. This can be done either within the procedures themselves or through a separate project plan. In addition, comprehensive training is key to ensuring everyone involved understands and implements the new requirements effectively.</p>
  <h2 id="the-time-to-act-is-now">The Time to Act Is Now</h2>
  <p>As the transition deadlines approach, manufacturers of legacy IVDs need to act swiftly to remain competitive and compliant in the evolving European market. The IVDR represents a major overhaul of IVD regulation in the EU, but it aims to ensure medical devices are safer, more effective, and of higher quality. Manufacturers who embrace these changes and take proactive steps to comply will be better positioned to navigate the evolving regulatory environment, ensuring continued market access and patient safety.</p>
  <p>Struggling with your IVDD to IVDR transition? Mantra Systems is here to help! Our expertise can guide you through the complexities of achieving IVDR compliance and ensure your QMS is up to date with the latest regulatory requirements. <a href="/contact">Contact us today</a>.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>shona-richardson</name></author><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Legacy device manufacturers need to manage challenging timelines as well as address transitional provisions and update QMS.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Overview of the UK’s 2024 Post-Market Surveillance Update</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Overview of the UK’s 2024 Post-Market Surveillance Update" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T17:13:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/overview-of-uk-2024-post-market-surveillance-update"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/medical-devices-post-market-surveillance-requirements/the-medical-devices-post-market-surveillance-requirements-amendment-great-britain-regulations-2024-guidance-on-implementation">UK’s Medical Devices (Post-market Surveillance Requirements) (Amendment) Regulations 2024</a> introduce significant changes to the Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) landscape for medical devices. These changes aim to strengthen the PMS system in the UK, ultimately improving patient safety. In this article, we will provide a detailed breakdown of these changes and what they mean for you.</p>
  <h2 id="introduction-to-the-mandatory-pms-plan">Introduction to the Mandatory PMS Plan</h2>
  <p>One of the most significant changes is the mandatory requirement for manufacturers to <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">have a PMS plan in place</a>. This plan, which outlines the methods for gathering and analysing device performance and safety data throughout the device’s lifecycle, is a crucial component of the updated regulations.</p>
  <p>The PMS plan should include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Objectives of the PMS system</li>
    <li>Processes to gather information, ensuring comprehensive real-world data is obtained</li>
    <li>Methods of data analysis</li>
    <li>Processes for fulfilling <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/vigilance">vigilance reporting</a> obligations</li>
    <li>Links to preventive and corrective action as part of a risk management process</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Manufacturers must review the actions taken according to the PMS plan at regular intervals and document the review in a Post-Market Surveillance Report (PMSR) or Periodic Safety Update Report (PSUR), as appropriate.</p>
  <h2 id="enhancing-patient-and-public-engagement">Enhancing Patient and Public Engagement</h2>
  <p>The regulations underscore the significance of gathering feedback directly from patients and the public. This inclusive approach ensures that their experiences and perspectives are considered.</p>
  <p>This includes obtaining feedback on the device’s usability and the adequacy of the instructions for use. Depending on the device type, manufacturers need to assess and document the extent to which this is relevant and achievable.</p>
  <h2 id="focusing-on-similar-devices">Focusing on Similar Devices</h2>
  <p>To improve signal detection, manufacturers must collect data on their devices across all markets and review publicly available information on the safety of similar devices offered by competitors.</p>
  <p>The regulations define similar devices as those based on the same or similar technology and with the same or similar intended purpose.</p>
  <h2 id="taking-preventive-and-corrective-actions">Taking Preventive and Corrective Actions</h2>
  <p>The regulations require manufacturers to take preventive and corrective actions to address potential safety or conformity issues with their devices. This includes cooperating with the Medicines &amp; Healthcare products Regulatory Agency (MHRA) on any actions taken.</p>
  <p>Preventive actions should be taken before the manufacturing process is completed, while corrective actions should be taken after the devices have been manufactured.</p>
  <h2 id="understanding-reporting-requirements">Understanding Reporting Requirements</h2>
  <p>Manufacturers must submit PMSRs or PSURs to the MHRA, depending on the device classification. The PSURs must follow a standardised format and be updated at set intervals.</p>
  <p>The PMSR or PSUR should provide a comprehensive and critical analysis of the device’s risk-benefit balance and include a summary of the analysis and conclusions from the review of the PMS data gathered since the last report.</p>
  <h2 id="incorporating-vigilance-reporting">Incorporating Vigilance Reporting</h2>
  <p>The regulations outline the requirements for reporting serious incidents, Field Safety Corrective Actions (FSCAs), and adverse trends to the MHRA. This includes specific timelines for reporting and the use of the MHRA’s Manufacturer’s Incident Report (MIR) form.</p>
  <p>A serious incident is defined as one that directly or indirectly led to, or could have led to, death or serious deterioration in the state of health of a patient, user, or another person.</p>
  <h2 id="communicating-field-safety-notices-fsns">Communicating Field Safety Notices (FSNs)</h2>
  <p>Manufacturers must communicate FSCAs to affected customers using FSNs. The FSNs must include Unique Device Identifier (UDI) information where available and be sent in a searchable format. The MHRA encourages manufacturers to host a copy of the FSN on their website for transparency.</p>
  <p>The FSN should clearly communicate the risk and the actions taken to mitigate it. Manufacturers should take reasonable steps to ensure that all affected end-users receive and understand the FSN.</p>
  <h2 id="fscas-outside-great-britain">FSCAs Outside Great Britain</h2>
  <p>If a manufacturer undertakes an FSCA outside Great Britain that affects the same type of devices supplied in Great Britain, they must notify the MHRA within three UK working days of the FSN being circulated, even if the devices in Great Britain are not affected.</p>
  <p>This requirement is in place to provide transparency and avoid confusion by clarifying why the FSCA does not affect the UK.</p>
  <h2 id="additional-important-changes">Additional Important Changes</h2>
  <p>The update also amends the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Clarification of Important Terms:</strong> The regulations define key terms, such as “lifetime” and “PMS period,” to ensure consistency and clarity.</li>
    <li><strong>Reportable Side Effects:</strong> The regulations clarify the definition of reportable side effects to include any negative impact on the health of the patient, their care, or wider public health.</li>
    <li><strong>Self-Administered Treatment:</strong> The regulations clarify that interventions to prevent serious deterioration in health include self-administered treatment.</li>
    <li><strong>Use Errors:</strong> The regulations specify that use errors do not need to result in serious deterioration in health to be reportable; the risk of occurrence is sufficient.</li>
    <li><strong>UDI Information:</strong> The regulations require the inclusion of Unique Device Identifier (UDI) information in incident reports and FSNs where available.</li>
    <li><strong>Trend Reporting:</strong> The regulations require manufacturers to submit trend reports for incidents that are reportable individually, as well as those that do not meet the criteria for individual reporting.</li>
    <li><strong>Custom-Made Devices:</strong> The regulations clarify that trend reports are not required for custom-made devices.</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>The UK’s Medical Devices (Post-market Surveillance Requirements) (Amendment) Regulations 2024 represent a significant step towards strengthening the PMS system for medical devices. By clarifying requirements, enhancing patient engagement, and focusing on proactive risk mitigation, these regulations aim to improve patient safety and ensure the continued effectiveness of medical devices in the UK market.</p>
  <p>If you need to speak to an expert to understand more about what this update might mean for you, <a href="/contact">contact us to arrange a free, no-obligation discussion</a>.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>ron-sangal</name></author><category term="News &amp;amp; Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What might mandatory PMS plans - which emphasise enhanced patient engagement and proactive risk management - mean for the industry?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Clinical Evidence Requirements with MDCG 2020-6</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Clinical Evidence Requirements with MDCG 2020-6" /><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-15T12:40:25+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/understanding-clinical-evidence-requirements-mdcg-2020-6"><![CDATA[<p>As legacy devices transition to compliance with the new Medical Device Regulation (MDR), manufacturers face the challenge of meeting updated clinical evidence requirements. <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/40904/">MDCG 2020-6 offers essential guidance</a> on how to assess and demonstrate sufficient clinical evidence to ensure legacy devices meet MDR General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</p>
  <h2 id="what-constitutes-a-legacy-device-and-what-are-the-clinical-evidence-requirements">What constitutes a ‘legacy device’ and what are the clinical evidence requirements?</h2>
  <p>Legacy devices include all <a href="/articles/keeping-medical-devices-in-market-maintaining-ce-marks">devices previously CE marked</a> under the European Medical Devices Directive 93/42/EEC (MDD) or the <a href="https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/european-standards/harmonised-standards/implantable-medical-devices_en">Active Implantable Medical Devices Directive 90/385/EEC (AIMDD)</a>.</p>
  <p>The MDR states that for legacy devices “sufficient” clinical evidence is required to demonstrate conformity with the relevant General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs).</p>
  <p>MDCG 2020-6 offers guidance on demonstrating sufficient clinical evidence for legacy devices. It states that both MDD and MDR require the quantity and quality of clinical data to be sufficient to demonstrate safety, performance and the acceptability of the benefit-risk ratio: both the Directives and the MDR require clinical evidence to be robust and the conclusions derived from this evidence to be scientifically valid. The guidance also reports that “the level of clinical evidence required for the device under evaluation needs to be determined by the manufacturer and verified by the notified body. The level of clinical evidence shall be appropriate in view of the characteristics of the device and its intended purpose.”</p>
  <h2 id="clinical-evaluation-for-legacy-devices">Clinical evaluation for legacy devices</h2>
  <p>The clinical evaluation process under EU MDR 2017/745 requires clinical data to:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Demonstrate conformity with the applicable GSPRs set out in MDR Annex I under the normal conditions of the intended use of the device</li>
    <li>Assess undesirable side effects and the acceptability of the benefit-risk ratio.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>For legacy devices, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">the MDR clinical evaluation process</a> relies on post-market clinical data and clinical data generated during conformity assessments under MDD/AIMDD. Devices previously CE marked under MDD/AIMDD are expected to have continuously collected evidence in line with evolving regulatory requirements and guidance. However, MDCG 2020-6 clarifies that clinical data from conformity assessments under the MDD may not necessarily provide sufficient clinical evidence to meet MDR requirements. Therefore, manufacturers should assess whether additional evidence is needed to comply with MDR standards.</p>
  <p>Sections of the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/docsroom/documents/17522/attachments/1/translations/">MEDDEV 2.7/1 rev. 4</a> that remain relevant under the MDR are listed in Appendix I of the document. Additionally, if clinical data from an equivalent device has been used, manufacturers must verify that these devices still meet the <a href="/articles/five-tips-for-making-a-medical-device-equivalence-claim-under-the-mdr">MDR’s equivalence criteria</a>.</p>
  <p>During the transitional period, legacy devices are not exempt from the MDR’s additional requirements, including those related to Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) and <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-clinical-follow-up-pmcf">Post-Market Clinical Follow-Up (PMCF)</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="how-can-mdcg-2020-6-help-with-the-mdr-conformity-assessment">How can MDCG 2020-6 help with the MDR conformity assessment?</h2>
  <p>MDCG 2020-6 provides guidance on establishing or updating a Clinical Evaluation Plan for legacy devices; the minimum content for the Clinical Evaluation Plan is described in Appendix II of the guidance document.</p>
  <p>Guidance is also described for the identification of available clinical data including pre-market and post-market sources, appraisal of the clinical data with respect to the overall clinical evaluation, generation of new clinical data to bridge gaps and analysis of the clinical data to demonstrate conformity with relevant GSPRs.</p>
  <p>A list of the suggested hierarchy of clinical evidence is documented in Appendix III of MDCG 2020-6, ranked from strongest to weakest level of evidence.</p>
  <p>Listed as number 1 are “results of high-quality clinical investigations covering all device variants, indications, patient populations, duration of treatment etc”; however, it is acknowledged that clinical investigations may not be feasible or necessary for legacy devices with a wide range of indications.</p>
  <h2 id="when-must-my-legacy-device-conform-to-the-updated-mdr-assessment">When must my legacy device conform to the updated MDR assessment?</h2>
  <p>Under the timelines established by the MDR, the deadline for manufacturers to apply to a Notified Body for a conformity assessment and to have a compliant Quality Management System (QMS) in place was 26 May 2021. Additionally, manufacturers were required to have a formal, written agreement with the Notified Body by 26 September 2024.</p>
  <p>Transition deadlines for legacy devices depend on their classification:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>For <strong>Class III custom-made implantable devices</strong>, the deadline for full MDR compliance is <strong>26 May 2026</strong>.</li>
    <li>For <strong>Class III and Class IIb implantable devices that are non-WET (Well-Established Technologies)</strong>, the deadline for MDR compliance is <strong>31 December 2027</strong>.</li>
    <li>For all other <strong>Class IIb, Class IIa, Class Is, and Class Im devices</strong>, the deadline for MDR compliance is <strong>31 December 2028</strong>.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The recent release of MDCG 2021-25 Rev. 1 provides crucial insights into applying MDR requirements to ‘legacy’ and ‘old’ devices in light of the extended transitional period from MDD to MDR.</p>
  <p><strong>If you need to speak to an expert to understand more about potential need for clinical evidence for a legacy device, <a href="/contact">contact us to arrange a free, no obligation discussion</a>.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>clare-dixon</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can manufacturers ensure legacy devices meet MDR's stringent requirements? Discover how MDCG 2020-6 guidance simplifies the path to compliance.]]></summary></entry></feed>