<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-08T11:35:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Systems</title><entry><title type="html">Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Device ‘Significant Changes’ – Navigating EU MDR Article 120(3) using MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1" /><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T11:07:57+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/medical-device-significant-changes-navigating-eu-mdr-article-120-3"><![CDATA[<p>With the transition to the EU MDR, legacy devices with certificates issued under the old EU directives (Directive 93/42/EEC on medical devices, MDD, and Directive 90/385/EEC on active implantable medical devices, AIMDD) can stay on the market under the transitional provisions set out in Article 120(3) of the MDR, provided they do not undergo any <b>significant changes</b>.</p>
      <p>In this article, we explain the concept of a ‘significant change’ and, using examples, help you understand whether you can still take advantage of the transitional arrangements in MDR Article 120(3).</p>
      <h2 id="transition-periods">Transition periods</h2>
      <p>The transition periods in Article 120(3) MDR as per Regulation (EU) 2023/607 are as follows:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Class III and IIb implants: new transition period until 31 December 2027</li>
        <li>Class IIb and lower: new transition period until 31 December 2028</li>
        <li>Class III custom-made products: new transition period until 31 December 2026</li>
        <li>No ‘sell-off’ deadline</li>
      </ul>
      <h2 id="what-does-significant-change-mean">What does significant change mean?</h2>
      <p>A significant change in the design or intended purpose consists of two cumulative elements:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>There is a change in the design or intended purpose, <b>and</b></li>
        <li>The change is significant</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Therefore, changes that do not concern the design or intended purpose are out of scope of Article 120(3) of the MDR. Changes that concern the design or intended purpose only fall under Article 120(3) if they are considered ‘significant’.</p>
      <h2 id="responsibilities-of-medical-device-manufacturers-regarding-significance-of-changes">Responsibilities of medical device manufacturers regarding ‘significance’ of changes</h2>
      <p>Medical device manufacturers have two primary responsibilities regarding changes:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>provide evidence and justification that a change does not affect the design or intended purpose, or</li>
        <li>in cases where the change affects the design or intended purpose of the device, that it is non-significant.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The outcome of this assessment should be documented and made available to a competent authority when requested.</p>
      <p>If a change to a legacy device is not a significant change in design or intended purpose, it can be implemented using the above transitional arrangement. In these instances, manufacturers must adhere to the documentation criteria of AIMDD/MDD, meaning that the revised technical documentation must enable the evaluation of the product’s compliance with the relevant standards.</p>
      <h2 id="determining-a-significant-change-to-the-design-or-intended-purpose">Determining a significant change to the design or intended purpose</h2>
      <p>The <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a> guidance document sets out whether a change in the design or intended purpose of a device is considered ‘significant’ within the meaning of EU MDR Article 120(3c), point (b).</p>
      <p><b>Examples of changes in design and/or intended purpose that are ‘non-significant’:</b></p>
      <ul>
        <li>Changes related to corrective actions assessed and accepted by the competent authority</li>
        <li>Correction of spelling mistakes or merely editorial changes of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label or instructions for use)</li>
        <li>Clarifications of intended purpose, population, or clinical application in the information to be supplied with the device in line with the original certification</li>
        <li>Updates of the information to be supplied with the device (e.g. label, instructions for use or implant card) if they are required by EU legislation other than the MDR, are mere clarifications and do not adversely affect the devices’ safety and performance in relation to existing or new risks</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The following diagram, taken from the <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a>, helps understand when <b>changes in design and/or intended purpose may be considered ‘significant’</b>:</p>
      <figure class="inline">
        <div class="image bordered">
          <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/significant-changes-main-chart.png" alt="Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart" loading="lazy" />
        </div>
        <figcaption>Design changes and changes of the intended purpose which may be considered 'significant' when interpreting Art. 120(3c), point (b) MDR – Main Chart taken from <a href="https://health.ec.europa.eu/system/files/2023-09/mdcg_2020-3_en_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDCG 2020-3 rev. 1</a></figcaption>
      </figure>
      <p>Charts A to E in the MDCG guideline contain specific areas where changes in the intended purpose, device design, device software, changes related to a substance or material or changes related to sterilisation are likely to be held to be significant. It’s vital to consult these charts when understanding whether a change will be significant and, by extension, whether your device can make use of the transitional arrangement.</p>
      <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
      <p>The definition of a “significant change” involves two cumulative elements: a change in design or intended purpose that is deemed significant. Manufacturers bear the responsibility of determining and justifying whether a change in their medical device is significant or not, and therefore whether relevant technical documents require updating in line with the changes. The MDCG 2020-3 guidance document provides guidance on determining the significance of changes in design or intended purpose.</p>
      <p>For further information regarding how we can meet your MDR requirements, including advice on whether changes are likely to be significant, <b>please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free and confidential discussion.</b></p>
      ]]></content><author><name>shen-may-khoo</name></author><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand what changes to your medical device are considered 'significant' under EU MDR (2017/745).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MDR or IVDR - A sibling rivalry?" /><published>2023-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T11:07:57+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/mdr-or-ivdr-a-sibling-rivalry"><![CDATA[<p>Medical devices and <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic devices are like twin cities on different continents - both serving the needs of modern medicine, both highly regulated and, following the advent of updated legislation in Europe, governed by parallel legislation. However, sometimes the distinction between the two is less clear than might be thought.</p>
    <p>In this article, we unpick the differences between these two categories of product and explore requirements for gaining and maintaining market access for these device types.</p>
    <h2 id="is-my-product-regulated-by-the-mdr-or-the-ivdr">Is my product regulated by the MDR or the IVDR?</h2>
    <p>The now well-known <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745 (MDR)</a> and the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32017R0746&amp;qid=1698152662286" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i>In Vitro</i> Diagnostic Medical Devices Regulation (EU) 2017/746 (IVDR)</a> were developed to improve the regulatory framework which oversees products placed on the market in the EU.</p>
    <p>There are many similarities between the two Regulations in terms of quality management, risk management, risk based classification and post market surveillance. Despite the areas of overlap between them, it is essential for manufacturers to correctly categorise their product as a medical device or as an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (IVD) in order to demonstrate the applicable compliance with EU rules.</p>
    <h2 id="basic-definitions">Basic definitions</h2>
    <p>The definition of a medical device (Article 2 (1) MDR):</p>
    <blockquote class="standard">
      <p>'medical device' means any instrument, apparatus, appliance, software, implant, reagent, material or other article intended by the manufacturer to be used, alone or in combination, for human beings for one or more of the following specific medical purposes:</p>
      <ul class="disc">
        <li>diagnosis, prevention, monitoring, prediction, prognosis, treatment or alleviation of disease,</li>
        <li>diagnosis, monitoring, treatment, alleviation of, or compensation for, an injury or disability,</li>
        <li>investigation, replacement or modification of the anatomy or of a physiological or pathological process or state,</li>
        <li>providing information by means of <i>in vitro</i> examination of specimens derived from the human body, including organ, blood and tissue donations,</li>
      </ul>
      <p>and which does not achieve its principal intended action by pharmacological, immunological or metabolic means, in or on the human body, but which may be assisted in its function by such means.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>Examples of medical devices include surgical implants, wheelchairs, disposable gloves, pacemakers and infusion pumps.</p>
    <p>Indent 4 of the definition above includes medical devices which <i>‘provide information by means of in vitro examination of specimens.’</i> However, Article 1(6) MDR specifically states that the Regulation <strong>does not apply</strong> to <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices covered by Regulation (EU) 2017/746. Therefore, an IVD can be seen as a subset of the medical device family, but with its own governing Regulation IVDR (EU) 2017/746.</p>
    <p>The definition of an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device (Article 2 (2) IVDR):</p>
    <blockquote class="standard">
      <p>'<i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device' means any medical device which is a reagent, reagent product, calibrator, control material, kit, instrument, apparatus, piece of equipment, software or system, whether used alone or in combination, intended by the manufacturer to be used <i>in vitro</i> for the examination of specimens, including blood and tissue donations, derived from the human body, solely or principally for the purpose of providing information on one or more of the following:</p>
      <ol class="lower-alpha">
        <li>concerning a physiological or pathological process or state</li>
        <li>concerning congenital physical or mental impairments</li>
        <li>concerning the predisposition to a medical condition or a disease</li>
        <li>to determine the safety and compatibility with potential recipients</li>
        <li>to predict treatment response or reaction</li>
        <li>to define or monitor therapeutic measures</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Specimen receptacles are also deemed to be <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>Examples of IVDs include laboratory machines which screen for infectious agents, compatibility for blood or tissue such as ABO or Rhesus and genetic tests. Self-tests for pregnancy, blood sugar and cholesterol are included in the definition. Companion diagnostics, where a device is specifically linked to a medicinal product to evaluate therapeutic response, are also categorised as IVDs.</p>
    <h2 id="patient-vs-sample">Patient vs Sample</h2>
    <p>An exclusion of the IVDR is any <i>‘invasive sampling products or products which are directly applied to the human body for the purpose of obtaining a specimen’</i>. Patients are not directly in contact with an IVD, other than a self-test IVD, which is not considered invasive. A sample of urine, blood or saliva which is collected from the patient, is then prepared and analysed by an IVD, either as a self-test, near-patient test (such as a hospital room) or in a laboratory. The results are then used for the management of the patient along with other therapeutic options.</p>
    <p>A device which obtains a sample from the patient in an invasive way such as a spinal needle for CSF collection or a punch biopsy for a tissue sample, falls under the medical device umbrella.</p>
    <h2 id="blurred-lines">Blurred lines</h2>
    <p>Of course, there may be cases where a product is a combination of a medical device and an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device. Both regulations are clear in this situation (as stated in Article 1 (4) IVDR and Article 1 (7) MDR).</p>
    <p>Any medical device which incorporates, as an integral part, an <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical device, shall be governed by the MDR, while the IVDR will apply to the <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic part of the device. The manufacturer will then have to meet both regulatory requirements in order to gain a CE mark for the combined device.</p>
    <h2 id="in-a-nutshell">In a nutshell</h2>
    <p><i>In vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices are a subcategory of medical devices with their own regulatory framework IVDR (EU) 2017/746. Although there is considerable overlap with the MDR (EU) 2017/745, it is imperative to categorise the product correctly from the beginning of the EU market access journey.</p>
    <p><b>For further information regarding compliance with the EU MDR or IVDR, <a href="/contact">contact Mantra Systems</a> for a FREE and open discussion.</b></p>
    ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="IVDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A guide to easily understanding whether your device is a medical device or an in vitro diagnostic medical device (IVD).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What the latest Brexit U-turn means for CE Marking of medical devices in Great Britain</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the latest Brexit U-turn means for CE Marking of medical devices in Great Britain" /><published>2023-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T11:07:57+00:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/what-the-latest-brexit-u-turn-means-for-ce-marking-of-medical-devices-in-great-britain"><![CDATA[<p>The UK Department for Business and Trade (DBT) announced on 1st August 2023 that <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-government-announces-extension-of-ce-mark-recognition-for-businesses">CE safety marking of products for businesses is to continue indefinitely in the UK</a>, beyond the 2024 deadline.</p>
  <p>Following the departure of the UK from the European Union in 2016, UKCA marking was to replace the CE mark, along with changes to the process of medical device regulation. Several extensions to the transitional arrangements have already been made, with the latest deadline for mandatory use of the UKCA mark being the 30th June 2024.</p>
  <p>Due to issues surrounding the burden of these changes on businesses and impact on economic growth, the DBT has consulted with industry professionals and will now allow the continued use of the CE mark alongside the UKCA. For the time being, this update refers to 18 regulations it will apply to (that fall under the DBT), of which medical devices has not been included.</p>
  <p><b>The regulations stated are as follows:</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>toys</li>
    <li>pyrotechnics</li>
    <li>recreational craft and personal watercraft</li>
    <li>simple pressure vessels</li>
    <li>electromagnetic compatibility</li>
    <li>non-automatic weighing instruments</li>
    <li>measuring instruments</li>
    <li>measuring container bottles</li>
    <li>lifts</li>
    <li>equipment for potentially explosive atmospheres (ATEX)</li>
    <li>radio equipment</li>
    <li>pressure equipment</li>
    <li>personal protective equipment (PPE)</li>
    <li>gas appliances</li>
    <li>machinery</li>
    <li>equipment for use outdoors</li>
    <li>aerosols</li>
    <li>low voltage electrical equipment</li>
  </ul>
  <p><b>Whether medical device regulation will be impacted is yet to be confirmed</b>, although given the current trend in extensions made to the transition deadline, it would not be a surprise if it were to follow suit. To date, no update has been provided by the MHRA regarding this matter.</p>
  <p>Keep an eye out for an article regarding an update on this topic.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss how we can help you with your CE &amp; UKCA certification in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>hanna-gul</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Will Great Britain continue to allow the use of the CE mark for medical devices beyond the 2024 deadline?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gain confidence, reassurance and control over your EU MDR strategy</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gain confidence, reassurance and control over your EU MDR strategy" /><published>2023-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/gain-confidence-reassurance-and-control-over-your-eu-mdr-strategy"><![CDATA[<p>What if there was a way to save a portion of your regulatory budget by writing your own MDR technical documents? What if you could build your own technical file using proven frameworks and detailed templates, with step-by-step guidance from EU MDR experts?</p>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE from Mantra Systems</a> is a product suite created for medical device manufacturers who would like to take control of their own regulatory processes but are in need of training, support or guidance from regulatory specialists.</p>
  <p>By building your own technical files within a guided framework, unnecessary financial outlays for comprehensive regulatory consulting packages can be minimised.</p>
  <h2 id="the-cost-of-compliance">The cost of compliance</h2>
  <p>With increasing costs across the industry, the requirements to become EU MDR compliant can add significant expense to an already tight balance sheet. Afterall, transitioning to the MDR is costly — <a href="https://www.ukri.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/IUK-171221-UK-SME-MDR-ReadinessFinalReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MedTech Europe estimates</a> compliance costs of 8-15% of revenue from certified devices, which translates into £800K - £1.5M for an SME with revenues of £10M.</p>
  <p>In the MedTech Europe report (commissioned by Innovate UK in September 2019), the readiness of UK small and medium size enterprise (SME) medical device companies for the Regulation (EU) 2017/745, commonly referred to as the EU Medical Device Regulation (MDR), was investigated.</p>
  <p>In response to the survey, with less than one year to go to the date of application of the MDR, 60% of medical device manufacturers had not yet budgeted for the MDR. Of the 40% who had, only 12% had provisioned between 8-15% of their impacted sales revenues.</p>
  <p>Regardless of the device classification, <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">EU MDR compliance</a> is a labour-intensive and expensive exercise. It requires significantly more in terms of clinical evidence, risk assessments, post market surveillance, supply chain obligations and data for the Unique Device Identification (UDI) system and the new EU Eudamed database.</p>
  <h2 id="enablece--saving-you-time-and-money">EnableCE – saving you time and money</h2>
  <p><a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE</a> was built to give the control of timelines and regulatory budgets back to the medical device manufacturer. Regardless of the degree of assistance you require, there is an EnableCE product for everyone.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-training-courses/">EnableCE Learn</a> provides on-demand training courses by experts, for expert training on driving your own EU MDR strategy.</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/">EnableCE Build</a> provides validated templates, documents and tools to enable you to build your own EU-MDR compliant file, tailor-made for your business.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Mantra Systems is well positioned to be your regulatory partner for <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, guiding and supporting you while you complete your own MDR compliant technical file.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>gayle-buchel</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Find out how to build your own technical files within a guided framework while minimising financial outlays.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Still racing to achieve MDR compliance? A transition period update</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Still racing to achieve MDR compliance? A transition period update" /><published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/still-racing-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-updates-on-the-transition-periods"><![CDATA[<p>At the EPSCO Board meeting on December 9, 2022, the EU Health Minister urged the European Commission to extend the transition period for the Medical Device Regulation. The proposal was under consideration of the European Parliament and the Council.</p>
  <p><strong>On January 6th 2023, the EU commission has adopted the proposal to extend the transition rules of Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745 (MDR)</strong> to allow more time for certification and to alleviate the foreseeable shortage of medical devices.</p>
  <h2 id="status-quo">Status quo</h2>
  <p>Under transitional arrangements, medical devices are allowed to enter the EU market under CE certifications issued according to Directive 93/42/EEC (MDD) or 90/385/EEC (AIMDD). The previously extended MDR transition time was due to end on 26 May 2024, meaning that after this time devices would require a recertification under MDR.</p>
  <p>Numerous industry stakeholders and key opinion leaders had expressed concerns in recent months that this deadline is unrealistic and that its implementation could have an impact on the continuous availability of different medical devices required by patients and healthcare providers in the EU.</p>
  <p>Moreover, opinions were that the suggested transitional time range could jeopardise research and innovation in addition to availability issues by delaying access to cutting-edge medical devices in EU nations.</p>
  <p>In addition to the strong backlash from stakeholders, limitations in Notified Body capacity was also a significant factor in calls for an extension to the transition period.</p>
  <h2 id="the-proposal">The proposal</h2>
  <p>In order to address the concerns and mitigate foreseeable risks associated with device shortage, the EU commission proposed a longer transition period with new deadlines depending on the medical device’s risk class.</p>
  <p>It is worth noting that the proposal does not alter any of the existing performance and safety standards outlined in the Medical Device Regulation 2017/745. It only amends the transitional provisions to provide additional time to transfer from the formerly applicable norms.</p>
  <h3 id="key-elements-of-the-proposal">Key elements of the proposal:</h3>
  <p class="notice info">The transition periods for medical devices authorised under Directive 93/42/EEC (Medical Device Directive) will now last until 31 December 2027 for high risk (Class III and IIb) devices, until 31 December 2028 for medium and low risk (Class IIa and I) devices and until 26 May 2026 for class III implantable custom-made devices.</p>
  <p>It is important to note that <strong>these extensions are subject to certain conditions</strong>. They are only applicable to devices:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>that are “safe”, that do not pose an unacceptable risk to health &amp; safety</li>
    <li>which have not undergone any significant changes in its intended purpose or design</li>
    <li>those for which manufacturers have already taken steps to transition to the rules provided by MDR</li>
  </ol>
  <p>In case of custom-made devices, the transition period is also subject to the application of the manufacturer for a conformity assessment of the device before 26 May 2024.</p>
  <p class="notice info"><b>Elimination of the "sell-off" date</b> of 26 May 2025 that is currently established in the Medical Device Regulation. The "sell-off" date designates the time after which products that have already been sold and are still on the market should be withdrawn.</p>
  <p>Removing the “sell-off” date will, it is argued, prevent safe medical devices from being removed from the market.</p>
  <h2 id="what-this-means">What this means</h2>
  <p>While it will be warmly welcomed by many, the proposal to delay the transitional period now has to be approved by the European Parliament and the Council through an expedited co-decision process. For this reason, manufacturers are still encouraged to continue working towards compliance with the MDR as soon as possible, as the extension is not a “free pass”.</p>
  <p>Notified Bodies will be still monitoring and auditing compliance during the extension period, and as outlined above, the transition period only applies to devices “for which manufacturers have already taken steps to transition to the rules provided by MDR.” Additionally, for Class III devices, the transition period is subject to the application of the manufacturer for a conformity assessment before 26 May 2024.</p>
  <p>So, whether approved by the European Parliament and Council or not, it’s not time to forget about MDR certification. It may, however, take off some of the pressure.</p>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On January 6th 2023, the EU commission has adopted the proposal to extend the transition rules of the EU MDR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A medical device regulations guide for start-up companies</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A medical device regulations guide for start-up companies" /><published>2023-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/a-medical-device-regulations-guide-for-start-ups"><![CDATA[<p>Navigating medical device regulatory requirements is a challenge even for established companies. For start-ups, gaining regulatory approval can be a major hurdle, arguably meaning that many promising device concepts fail to reach the market.</p>
  <p>In this article, we present 7-steps for navigating regulatory requirements on a budget. While aimed at pre-revenue companies, these steps may also be useful for established companies seeking to bring new products to market or reduce their regulatory spend.</p>
  <h2 id="step-1---plan-ahead">Step 1 - Plan ahead</h2>
  <p>The worst - but perhaps most common - mistake made by medical device start-ups is to neglect regulatory requirements until the later stages of product development. With some justification, many companies assume that regulatory documents and processes can only meaningfully be compiled once the device design has been finalised.</p>
  <p>The truth is that while some tasks (such as <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>) are better left until the device has reached a level of maturity, others need to be performed from the earliest possible stages of device development. These can be considered foundational systems that form the bedrock of all successful regulatory strategies.</p>
  <h2 id="step-2---build-foundational-systems">Step 2 - Build foundational systems</h2>
  <p>Foundational systems and activities are:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Establishing and maintaining a Quality Management System (QMS)</li>
    <li>Establishing a Risk Management System</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Let’s consider each in turn.</p>
  <h3 id="1-qms---control-quality-from-the-earliest-stages">1. QMS - Control quality from the earliest stages</h3>
  <p>When it comes to obtaining final approval for your devices, you will be required to produce evidence that device design was conducted according to an established quality framework. It is essentially impossible to do this in retrospect, so it’s vital to set up a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">Quality Management System (QMS)</a> as early as possible. While often thought of as expensive and complex, the truth is that an early-stage QMS can be relatively simple if it incorporates important building blocks that will enable it to grow as the company nears market entry.</p>
  <p>Basic principles include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Adopting a process-driven framework</li>
    <li>Documenting processes and maintaining records</li>
    <li>Controlling documents and records</li>
    <li>Establishing a Quality Policy and Quality Objectives</li>
    <li>Defining roles and responsibilities</li>
    <li>Writing a Quality manual</li>
    <li>Having an effective <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-document-management/">Document Management System</a></li>
    <li>Ensuring that suppliers and third parties operate in accordance with your QMS</li>
  </ul>
  <p>ISO 13485:2016 is the international standard for Quality Management Systems for medical devices and, ultimately, your QMS will almost certainly need to adhere to its requirements. It’s advisable to obtain a copy as early as possible and begin structuring your activities accordingly. If nothing else, basic considerations are to set objectives, keep records, allocate responsibilities, monitor outcomes and, where necessary, conduct corrective actions. Good habits from the earliest stages will make the development of a definitive QMS much easier as the company matures.</p>
  <h3 id="2-risk-management---the-key-to-successful-product-design">2. Risk Management - The key to successful product design</h3>
  <p>It is easy to think of medical device Risk Management as just another administrative burden standing between you and regulatory approval. However, the truth is that an effective approach to <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk Management</a> has, amongst other benefits, a direct bearing on successful medical device design, helping your product differentiate from competitors through a unique (and commercially successful) solution.</p>
  <p>An effective approach to Risk Analysis may indicate that changes to the device’s design are necessary to mitigate identified risks. While this is relatively easy during the early stages of device design, it may be extremely difficult later on - especially if manufacturing infrastructure has been established for the design and if user tests or clinical trials will need to be repeated following changes.</p>
  <p>For these reasons, it’s imperative to begin Risk Management as early as possible. Odds are that the correct approach (based on ISO 14971:2019) will reveal risks that hadn’t previously been considered. Furthermore, you may uncover disadvantages to existing solutions, enabling additional innovation to further differentiate your product.</p>
  <p>Correct conduct of Risk Management - especially in the early stages - needn’t be expensive or complex. The Mantra Systems <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE Toolkit</a> offers a complete, easy to follow start-to-finish guide to building an ISO 14971:2019-compliant risk management system from scratch. The course is suitable for anyone and is complemented by a full package of <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/risk-management-templates">Risk Management document templates</a> to ensure correct documentation and traceability.</p>
  <h2 id="step-3---know-your-objectives">Step 3 - Know your objectives</h2>
  <p>When building a successful regulatory strategy, it’s vital to know what your objectives are. In other words, you need to define what you are hoping to demonstrate compliance with, which in turn will inform how compliance will be achieved and demonstrated.</p>
  <p>Key considerations are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Specifying a clear intended purpose for the device</li>
    <li>Understanding which legislative requirements apply (GSPRs or ERs, depending on framework)</li>
    <li>What risks need to be mitigated or avoided (an output from Risk Management activities)</li>
    <li>The Quality Policy and Quality Objectives that must be addressed by the device</li>
  </ul>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="RxyKV003WaY"></div>
    <p class="video-caption"><b>Video 1:</b> How to work with Annex I from the EU MDR</p>
  </div>
  <p>While legislative requirements (such as GSPRs) are imposed by law, the intended purpose is (within reason) entirely down to the manufacturer’s preference. It is therefore vital to think about intended purpose very early in the device’s development. A <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">systematic literature review</a> of the clinical field may help define scope of the intended purpose, as well as further defining weaknesses in competing solutions.</p>
  <p>Performing an early analysis of legislative requirements (such as the EU MDR Annex I GSPRs) for relevance to the product will define what additional requirements must be met; in turn, this will help define what pre-clinical and clinical testing needs to be conducted to demonstrate compliance. Please watch our video which explains <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxyKV003WaY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how to analyse the MDR Annex I GSPRs for relevance</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="step-4---get-technical">Step 4 - Get technical</h2>
  <p>MDR Annexes II and III set out requirements for a range of additional technical documents that must be produced for each device. In outline, Annex II technical documents include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>General device description &amp; specification</li>
    <li>Information to be supplied by the manufacturer</li>
    <li>Design &amp; manufacturing information</li>
    <li>General Safety &amp; Performance Requirements (GSPRs)</li>
    <li>Verification &amp; Validation information</li>
    <li>Risk assessment</li>
    <li>Declaration of Conformity</li>
  </ul>
  <p>If you follow the framework in this article, you will already have addressed section 4 and much of section 6. For the others, the key is to start early and keep contemporaneous records of document updates and revisions.</p>
  <p>Section 7 (Declaration of Conformity) is the only one that should be left until the end. To ensure correct structuring of Annex II technical documents (and to avoid excluding vital information), the <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/annex-ii-templates">EnableCE Annex II template pack</a> includes everything you need.</p>
  <p>MDR Annex III primarily concerns <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) activities</a>. While a new device won’t have any PMS data, it’s imperative that you specify how PMS activities will be conducted in a PMS Plan.</p>
  <h2 id="step-5---prove-it">Step 5 - Prove it</h2>
  <p>Securing regulatory approval ultimately comes down to one thing: evidence. Can you demonstrate through suitable evidence that your device:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Is suitable for its intended purpose?</li>
    <li>Demonstrates conformity with relevant GSPRs / ERs?</li>
    <li>Has a favourable benefit-risk profile?</li>
    <li>Compares favourably with safety and performance of similar (comparable alternative) devices?</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Because these four questions form the heart of <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, a vital stage in device approval, it’s necessary from foundational stages to consider how you will generate suitable evidence. Depending on the device and the individual requirement, such evidence may include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Proof of adherence to recognised standards (such as ISO 10993 - Biocompatibility)</li>
    <li>Conduct of pre-clinical studies (e.g. on materials properties, packaging integrity, sterility, etc)</li>
    <li>Usability studies</li>
    <li>Clinical studies</li>
  </ul>
  <p>When planning clinical studies, ensure you align with requirements in MDR Annex XV and ISO 14155:2020. Also consider that conduct of clinical studies takes considerable time and, often, money. Which leads us to the next major consideration…</p>
  <h2 id="step-6---budget">Step 6 - Budget</h2>
  <p>There’s no getting away from the fact that gaining regulatory approval will cost money and failure to adequately budget is a common failure point. Contrary to popular belief, investors may be encouraged by a proper consideration of expenses relating to regulatory requirements, since it demonstrates a proper consideration of go-to-market costs.</p>
  <p>The bottom line is: ensure you have enough money set aside. While costs will vary according to device class and complexity, they may run anywhere from £25,000 to £250,000 and beyond, especially if the device requires complex clinical trials.</p>
  <p>The <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">EnableCE Toolkit</a> offers an innovative supported do-it-yourself approach that can really help to control budget. The toolkit combines training resources, document templates and a full document management system, enabling you to develop a full technical document portfolio without the added costs of outsourcing. It’s a unique resource that is perfect for cash-strapped start-ups, alongside established companies looking to reduce outsourcing requirements.</p>
  <h2 id="step-7---get-in-the-queue">Step 7 - Get in the queue</h2>
  <p>One final consideration is that <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Bodies</a> (and UK Approved Bodies) are currently stretched beyond capacity, meaning that gaining access for conformity assessments is taking much longer than would be preferred. While there’s no shortcut to this, the message is to start conversations early, seeing if you can get ‘in the queue’ ahead of time. Note, however, that you do need to be ready should availability arise, so play it carefully.</p>
  <h2 id="further-help">Further help</h2>
  <p>Mantra Systems offers a range of products and services to support start-ups on their journey through regulatory compliance. These include:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/mdready-starter-guide">MDReady</a> - A free starter guide to MDR compliance</li>
    <li><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">EU MDR Compliance Guide</a> - A free compendium of all aspects of working with the EU MDR</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-training-courses/">EnableCE Training Courses</a> providing detailed guidance on key aspects of regulatory compliance</li>
    <li><a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/">EnableCE Document Templates</a> for Annex II technical documents, Risk Management, CERs, CEPs and more</li>
    <li>A <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-templates-documents-tools/gap-analysis-tool">Gap Analysis tool</a> helping you identify key deficiencies in your regulatory system</li>
    <li>A cost-effective <a href="/enable-ce-mark/eu-mdr-document-management/">Document Management System</a> for effective version control, access control and secure document storage</li>
    <li>A range of consulting services including <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a>, <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/post-market-clinical-follow-up">PMCF</a> and <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">systematic literature reviews</a> giving you access to our worldwide network of clinical and regulatory specialists</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> if you have any questions about this article or would like to discuss our products and services in more detail.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>paul-hercock</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We present a 7-step guide to navigating regulatory requirements on a budget.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UKCA Marking of Medical Devices – An update on the status quo</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices-an-update-on-the-status-quo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UKCA Marking of Medical Devices – An update on the status quo" /><published>2022-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices%E2%80%93an-update-on-the-status-quo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/ukca-marking-of-medical-devices-an-update-on-the-status-quo"><![CDATA[<p>UKCA (United Kingdom Conformity Assessed) marking of medical devices was due to become mandatory in July 2023, placing medical device manufacturers under real pressure to ensure they were in alignment with UK requirements.</p>
  <p>However, due to delays in processing applications and introducing the new medical device regulatory framework, the MHRA have just announced that they will be <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementation-of-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-and-extension-of-standstill-period/implementation-of-the-future-regulations">extending the UKCA implementation deadline to July 2024</a>. This comes as a welcome relief to medical device manufacturers, who now have more time to ensure that they are adequately prepared for this transition.</p>
  <p>The availability of more time is not a reason to put UKCA to the back of collective minds however. Rather, it’s an opportunity to take stock and ensure that a UKCA strategy is properly developed and implemented well before the new deadline.</p>
  <p>In this article, we review updated requirements for UKCA marking and what they mean for manufacturers.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-a-ukca-mark">What is a UKCA mark?</h2>
  <p>Following Great Britain’s exit from the EU single market in December 2020, CE (Conformité Européenne) marking was to be replaced by the UKCA mark for medical devices marketed in the territory. The UKCA mark is a mandatory mark on a product which indicates that it conforms to the new GB legislation and operates in much the same way as a CE mark in Europe.</p>
  <p>The manufacturer or, if mandated, their authorised representative is responsible for affixing a UKCA mark to the product, assuming they are authorised to do so following a conformity process.</p>
  <h2 id="where-will-it-apply">Where will it apply?</h2>
  <p>The UKCA mark only applies in Great Britain (England, Scotland and Wales). CE marking will continue in Northern Ireland (NI) as it remains aligned with the EU single market for goods. Products that will be placed on the market in both GB and NI will therefore need both UKCA and CE marking unless they are “Qualifying Northern Ireland Goods”, in which case they can be sold in GB with a CE mark and do not need a UKCA mark.</p>
  <h2 id="are-there-any-differences-between-ukca-and-ce-marking">Are there any differences between UKCA and CE marking?</h2>
  <p>As of today, two different legal frameworks exist to obtain UKCA/CE marking for a product, dependent on whether it is marketed in the UK or the EU, respectively. In the UK, the regulations are based on the old Medical Device Directive (MDD), implemented into domestic law by the UK Medical Device Regulations 2002 (UK MDR 2002). Prior to the end of the transition period, this gave effect in UK law to the following Directives:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01990L0385-20071011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 90/385/EEC</a> on active implantable medical devices (EU AIMDD)</li>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01993L0042-20071011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 93/42/EEC</a> on medical devices (EU MDD)</li>
    <li><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:01998L0079-20120111" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Directive 98/79/EC</a> on in vitro diagnostic medical devices (EU IVDD)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Because the Brexit transition period ended before the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:02017R0745-20170505" target="_blank" rel="noopener">European Medical Device Regulation (EU) 2017/745</a> came into effect, the European MDR has not been adopted in the UK, unlike in Europe where it is now mandatory to comply with MDR 2017/745 to obtain a medical device CE mark. This means that the Great Britain route to market and UKCA marking requirements are still officially based on the requirements in the MDD.</p>
  <p>Moving forwards, this means in principle that companies will need two parallel frameworks to be able to market products in both the UK and EU, hence the need for a transition period. The extended transition period outlined by the MHRA will hopefully lessen the burden of becoming compliant with both systems.</p>
  <h2 id="can-a-product-have-both-ukca-and-ce-marks">Can a product have both UKCA and CE marks?</h2>
  <p>Providing a product fulfils the necessary requirements, it may carry both a UKCA and CE mark. The presence of multiple conformity marks is common on internationally sold products.</p>
  <h2 id="what-uk-legislation-needs-to-be-followed">What UK legislation needs to be followed?</h2>
  <p>The UK government has issued several Statutory Instruments to amend current legislation, including <a href="https://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2019/696/contents/made" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Product Safety and Metrology etc. (Amendment etc.) (EU Exit) Regulations 2019</a> and has now <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-in-the-united-kingdom" target="_blank" rel="noopener">concluded consultation on the UK MDR 2022</a>. The specific details of the new UK medical device framework are yet to be published following the UK government consultation on the proposed changes, which started in 2021. However, the government response in June 2022 highlighted that the new GB medical device regulations will be closely aligned with the 2017 EU Medical Device Regulations.</p>
  <h2 id="when-will-ukca-marking-come-into-force">When will UKCA marking come into force?</h2>
  <p>As previously stated, UKCA marking was due to be enforced from July 2023, in-line with the UK Medical Device Regulations 2022 (UK MDR 2022). However, due to understandable delays with regard to publishing the new regulatory framework and the backlog of applications submitted to notified bodies, the MHRA issued a statement on 21st October 2022 indicating that this will be delayed until July 2024. Since this has not yet been confirmed by law, further updates are expected from the MHRA and will be announced via the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementation-of-the-future-regulation-of-medical-devices-and-extension-of-standstill-period" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MHRA website</a> in the near future. The UK MDR 2022 will also be updated to reflect these changes.</p>
  <p>It is important to highlight that current and valid CE marks will continue to be accepted in Great Britain until this time point. New legislation on medical device regulation highlighting the transitional arrangements is due to be released by the government in Spring 2023. This will also include new Post-Market Surveillance requirements.</p>
  <p>Manufacturers will be able to continue to place CE marked devices on the GB market after 1 July 2023. From July 2024, the transitional arrangements will apply for CE and UKCA marked devices placed on the GB market. Where third party conformity assessment is required, a UK Approved Body is needed. However, manufacturers of non-sterile and non-measuring Class I devices and general IVDs can self-certify against the UKCA marking.</p>
  <p>The government’s June 2022 response has indicated that there will be generous transitional periods in the new medical device framework. These arrangements would allow products to be placed on the market as follows:</p>
  <ol>
    <li><b>General medical devices</b> - until either the certificate expires or for three years after the new regulations take effect (whichever occurred sooner) and</li>
    <li><b>In-vitro Diagnostics (IVDs)</b> - until either the certificate expires or five years after the new regulations take effect (whichever is sooner)</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Transitional provisions would not apply if there were significant changes in the design or intended purpose of the device. Furthermore, all products that will benefit from transitional arrangements will need to comply with post-market requirements. The below schematic illustrates the updated timeline for UKCA marking.</p>
  <h2 id="updated-ukca-timline">Updated UKCA timline</h2>
  <div class="general-wrap">
    <ul class="information row tile info-process">
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b2 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>January 2021</span></h3>
          <p>UKCA marking comes into force.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b3 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>January 2021 to June 2024</span></h3>
          <p>Medical devices &amp; IVD devices can be either CE or UKCA marked (or both).</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b4 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>30th June 2024</span></h3>
          <p>Deadline for medical device &amp; IVD device manufacturers to replace existing CE marks with UKCA mark.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b0 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>1st July 2024</span></h3>
          <p>UKCA mark will be mandatory for all medical devices &amp; IVD devices on the GB market. CE marking will not be recognised.</p>
        </div>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </div>
  <p class="small-text align-center"><strong>Note:</strong> Current timeline in-line with the MHRA update on 21st October 2022 (maybe subject to change)</p>
  <h2 id="what-needs-immediate-action">What needs immediate action?</h2>
  <p>To ensure that manufacturers are prepared for a smooth transition, in-line with the new timescales for UKCA marking, the following are key requirements for placing a device on the GB market:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>All medical devices, including in-vitro diagnostic medical devices (IVDs), custom-made devices and systems or procedure packs, need to be registered with the MHRA before they are placed on the Great Britain market</li>
    <li>If you are a medical device manufacturer based outside the UK and wish to place a device on the GB market, you need to appoint a single <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/person-responsible-for-regulatory-compliance-prrc">UK Responsible Person</a> for all of your devices, who will act on your behalf to carry out specified tasks, such as registration.</li>
    <li>CE marking will continue to be recognised in Great Britain until 30 June 2024</li>
    <li>Certificates issued by <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">EU-recognised Notified Bodies</a> will continue to be valid for the GB market until 30 June 2024</li>
    <li>The EU no longer recognises UK Notified Bodies</li>
    <li>UK Notified Bodies are not able to issue CE certificates - and have become <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/approved-bodies-for-medical-devices" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UK Approved Bodies</a></li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="the-bottom-line">The bottom line</h2>
  <p>The bottom line is – don’t panic! The delay in enforcing UKCA marking is a great opportunity to prepare and re-assess your regulatory strategy so that you are ahead of the game of other competitors in the field. Investing time to get things correct, in-line with new regulations will ensure that your medical devices can continue to be sold and used where they are required most, ultimately leading to improved health outcomes.</p>
  <p>If you require further information you may wish to visit the ‘Useful resources’ section below.</p>
  <p>If you have any concerns about your regulatory strategy that have been brought up in this article, you can <a href="mailto:contact&#64;mantrasystems.co.uk">email us</a> or call <a href="tel:+441142992599">+44(0)114 299 2599</a> to speak directly with our experienced team. <strong>We promise: no phone menus, no waiting, no obligation and complete confidence.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>hanna-gul</name></author><category term="MDR" /><category term="Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We review recently updated requirements for UKCA marking and what it means for your regulatory strategy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing a CER writer for your MDR Clinical Evaluations</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/choosing-a-cer-writer-for-your-mdr-clinical-evaluations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing a CER writer for your MDR Clinical Evaluations" /><published>2022-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/choosing-a-cer-writer-for-your-mdr-clinical-evaluations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/choosing-a-cer-writer-for-your-mdr-clinical-evaluations"><![CDATA[<p>If you are considering outsourcing your medical device Clinical Evaluations to a CEP &amp; CER writer, you are certainly not alone.</p>
  <div class="guide-funnel medium bg-b2 bg-dark">
    <div class="content">
      <h3>
        <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation">
          <b>Expert CEP &amp; CER writers</b>
        </a>
      </h3>
      <p>We have a 100% acceptance rate for CERs &amp; CEPs submitted for the EU &amp; UK MDR.</p>
      <p><a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/clinical-evaluation" class="button small"><span class="icon-angle-right after"><span>Explore <span>our CEP &amp; CER writing services</span></span></span></a></p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <p>Writing <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-report-cer">CERs</a> and <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-plan-cep">CEPs</a> is a complex challenge that calls for extensive experience and a thorough understanding of the MDR, relevant guidelines and applicable standards. For this reason, many companies prefer to outsource to an expert rather than struggle internally and risk non-compliance.</p>
  <p>However, with a broad and confusing range of support options available, how can you be sure you are choosing the best supplier for your needs? What factors should you consider when choosing a contractor for writing your CEPs and CERs?</p>
  <p>We’ve compiled a list of considerations that will help you make the right choice when choosing a medical CEP &amp; CER writer for your Clinical Evaluations.</p>
  <h2 id="1-fixed-and-fair-price">1. Fixed and fair price</h2>
  <p>Sounds obvious - but do you actually know what you will need to pay? <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a> is a complex and time-consuming process, so be wary of any offers that charge per unit time or that cap working time before extra charges kick in.</p>
  <p>Instead, look for suppliers that will commit to a fixed price in advance with no hidden extras. This way, you’ll have control of your budget and won’t be at risk of the ‘sunken cost fallacy’.</p>
  <p>On the flip side, be wary of choosing a CEP / CER writer on the basis of price alone - while it’s important, it shouldn’t be the only factor to be considered when making a decision.</p>
  <h2 id="2-fixed-timeline">2. Fixed timeline</h2>
  <p>Always look for a supplier that will commit to a specific completion date for the work, with regular check-ins throughout the process. This helps ensure that you stay well ahead of any submission deadlines and in full control.</p>
  <p>A CEP / CER writer that will readily commit to a deadline on paper is generally one that has your interests at heart.</p>
  <h2 id="3-do-they-have-the-right-credentials">3. Do they have the right credentials?</h2>
  <p>It’s vital that those tasked with writing your CERs and CEPs are appropriately qualified to do so.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>What assurances can you get that your potential supplier will have suitable regulatory and subject matter expertise?</li>
    <li>What level of experience do they have?</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Be wary of suppliers who are not open about the qualifications of their writers and reviewers; instead, look for those who provide tangible reasons why their writers will fulfil requirements for knowledge, experience and objectivity.</p>
  <h2 id="4-do-they-claim-or-demonstrate-expertise">4. Do they claim or demonstrate expertise?</h2>
  <figure class="inline">
    <div class="image">
      <img src="/assets/images/content/articles/inline/cer-writer.jpg" alt="A photo of a Mantra Systems' CER Writer" loading="lazy" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>There are many factors to consider when deciding on the right CEP &amp; CER writer.</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>There’s an important difference between the two. Plenty of suppliers claim to be experts without doing anything to back up these claims on a public forum. To what extent have they <q>“put themselves out there”</q> and faced unfiltered questions from medical device manufacturers?</p>
  <p>Look for suppliers who have shown a readiness to demonstrate their knowledge and expertise, rather than simply claim it. Be sure to check out any videos or previous Q&amp;A sessions they have run and pay close attention to how knowledgeable they really are.</p>
  <h2 id="5-how-good-is-their-communication">5. How good is their communication?</h2>
  <p>A prospective supplier’s website, emails and marketing material are all great ‘try before you buy’ screening opportunities that reveal the standard of writing you can expect. Don’t risk entrusting complex technical writing to a supplier who makes basic errors in their own material.</p>
  <p>Instead, look for  CEP / CER writers who adhere to the highest standards of written communication in all aspects of their business.</p>
  <h2 id="6-responsiveness">6. Responsiveness</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>How quickly do prospective suppliers get back to you after an enquiry?</li>
    <li>Do they make you feel valued and important right from the outset, or are you left waiting while being told that ‘your enquiry is important’?</li>
    <li>Is your enquiry handled personally by a named individual, or through a ‘boilerplate’ interface and a call centre?</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Clinical Evaluation done properly is a collaborative process that calls for effective and bilateral communication. Look for suppliers who build an instant rapport and put you in direct contact with members of the project team.</p>
  <h2 id="7-dedicated-focus-or-bolt-on-service">7. Dedicated focus or bolt-on service?</h2>
  <p>Clinical Evaluation is not something that lends itself to non-specialists. For this reason, look for suppliers who focus specifically on CERs and CEPs rather than those who bury their Clinical Evaluation service amongst a multitude of others.</p>
  <p>You can’t expect a specialist, dedicated service from a non-specialist. If you can’t easily find details of a Clinical Evaluation service on a supplier’s website, it’s time to move on.</p>
  <h2 id="8-do-they-stand-by-their-work">8. Do they stand by their work?</h2>
  <p>Look for suppliers who will stand by the quality of their work and provide FREE ongoing support once the CER and/or CEP have been submitted to a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Body</a>. After all, why would any company refuse to do this if they truly believed in the standard of their work?</p>
  <h2 id="the-bottom-line">The bottom line</h2>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="cUu6YtEdO9c"></div>
    <p class="video-caption"><b>Video 1:</b> See how our Clinical Evaluation service and Literature Review writing process works from start to finish</p>
  </div>
  <p>Choosing the right CER writer is a key decision when outsourcing the writing of medical device Clinical Evaluations. Making a selection based on price alone can be a costly mistake; instead, focus on the above criteria and make a choice based on proven factors that will directly impact the quality of work delivered.</p>
  <p>Questions? <a href="mailto:contact&#64;mantrasystems.co.uk">Email a member of our friendly team</a>, or call <a href="tel:+441142992599">+44(0)114 299 2599</a> to speak directly with one of our expert medical writers. <strong>We promise: no phone menus, no waiting, no obligation and complete confidence.</strong></p>
  ]]></content><author><name>paul-hercock</name></author><category term="Clinical Evaluation" /><category term="Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We've compiled a list of considerations that will help you make the right choice when choosing a CER writer.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to achieve MDR Compliance for Class I medical devices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/how-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-for-class-i-medical-devices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to achieve MDR Compliance for Class I medical devices" /><published>2022-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/how-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-for-class-i-medical-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/how-to-achieve-mdr-compliance-for-class-i-medical-devices"><![CDATA[<p>Are you a manufacturer of Class I medical devices intended for sale in the EU market? Or are you a supplier who recently learned that your product is classified as a medical device under the new MDR? If your answer to either of these questions is ‘yes’, then this article is for you.</p>
  <p>In order to place a medical device on the market, you as a manufacturer have to demonstrate conformity with the MDR and compliance with the GSPRs laid out in Annex I, regardless of the device classification.</p>
  <p>Because most Class I devices don’t require the involvement of a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Body</a>, it can be tempting to ‘do the minimum’ for Class I regulatory compliance. Under the MDR, however, this can be a big mistake.</p>
  <p>In this article, we will discuss how to achieve <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/">MDR compliance</a> specifically for Class I devices, with a focus on what to keep in mind while self-certifying.</p>
  <h2 id="1-is-your-product-a-medical-device-under-mdr-article-2">1. Is your product a medical device under MDR Article 2?</h2>
  <p>The first step towards MDR compliance is confirming whether your product is a medical device. Whether your product satisfies the definition of a medical device depends in large part on the intended purpose, which you as a manufacturer control. Take great care in matching this against the definition in Article 2 of the MDR. Remember that non-standard items such as “reagents” and “software” can all meet the definition.</p>
  <h2 id="2-what-is-its-risk-classification">2. What is its risk classification?</h2>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="Dx55LZ3snM4"></div>
    <p class="video-caption"><b>Video 1:</b> How to work with Annex VIII from the MDR</p>
  </div>
  <p>The next step is to identify the device’s risk classification. Risk classification in MDR reflects the potential risk of harm that a medical device poses. Medical devices under Class I are generally low risk devices which include non-invasive devices with non-critical functions, such as wound care devices, stethoscopes, tongue depressors, and so on.</p>
  <p>The MDR uses a rule-based system to determine a medical device’s risk class. There are 22 rules outlined in Annex VIII of the MDR for classifying any medical device into its appropriate risk class. Work through it as described in our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dx55LZ3snM4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How to work with Annex VIII of the MDR</a>.</p>
  <h2 id="3-demonstrate-device-conformity">3. Demonstrate device conformity</h2>
  <p>A product can only be placed on the EU market if it satisfies all the applicable MDR requirements, which apply to Class I devices just the way they do to others. The main requirements are:</p>
  <h3 id="i-meet-general-safety-and-performance-requirements-gsprs">i) Meet General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs)</h3>
  <p>As a manufacturer, you are required to perform a relevancy analysis of the MDR Annex I GSPRs to work out which ones apply to your product. The best way to do this is to use a GSPR checklist or table to show which GSPRs apply. Following this, begin collating evidence to support conformity with those that are relevant.</p>
  <h3 id="ii-conduct-a-clinical-evaluation">ii) Conduct a Clinical Evaluation</h3>
  <div class="video-wrap">
    <div class="video-insert youtube-player" data-id="cUu6YtEdO9c"></div>
    <p class="video-caption"><b>Video 2:</b> See how our Clinical Evaluation Report writing service works from start to finish</p>
  </div>
  <p>All devices, regardless of risk class, must undergo a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a> in line with MDR Article 61 and Annex XIV Part A.</p>
  <p>Don’t underestimate the importance of Clinical Evaluation, even to Class I devices – even if you can self-certify, your <b title="e.g. a Government">Competent Authority</b> still has the right to review your technical documents and will often plumb straight for the device’s  <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-report-cer">Clinical Evaluation Report (CER)</a>. That said, a CER needn’t be as complex as for a Class III device – it’s all about balance.</p>
  <p><a href="/contact">Discuss Class I CERs</a> with a member of our team if you are in any doubt.</p>
  <h3 id="iii-prepare-technical-documentation">iii) Prepare technical documentation</h3>
  <p>Technical documentation should contain information on the device’s design, intended use, composition, basic UDI-DI, IFU, labelling, testing, materials, and so on, as required by MDR Article II.</p>
  <p>It should also set out plans for PMS and other activities as per MDR Article III. A well organised technical documentation file is crucial in demonstrating your device’s compliance. Since most Class I devices are self-certified, manufacturers may overlook the importance of a detailed, well-structured, and clear medical device technical file.</p>
  <p>Even though it is self-certified, the manufacturer is required to make the technical documentation available to the Competent Authority, authorised representative (if applicable), and notified body (when applicable). So, it is essential to make sure that the documents are prepared in a clear, orderly, and unambiguous manner.</p>
  <p>If you need help in putting together your technical document library, you may benefit from the range of document templates available through our <a href="/enable-ce-mark/">MDR Academy platform</a>.</p>
  <h3 id="iv-involve-a-notified-body">iv) Involve a Notified Body</h3>
  <p>This step is not applicable for all Class I medical devices. But as a manufacturer, you must involve a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Body</a> for Class I devices which are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>sterile devices (Class Is)</li>
    <li>reusable surgical instruments (Class Ir)</li>
    <li>devices with a measuring function (Class Im)</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="4-meet-the-general-obligations-for-manufacturers">4. Meet the general obligations for manufacturers</h2>
  <p><a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">General obligations for manufacturers</a> are outlined in the Article 10 of the MDR 2017/745. To meet these requirements, manufacturers must:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>ensure that their medical devices are MDR-compliant in design and manufacture</li>
    <li>have <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/risk-management">Risk Management system</a> in place</li>
    <li>perform a thorough <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a></li>
    <li>keep a record of current technical documentation</li>
    <li>have access to a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/person-responsible-for-regulatory-compliance-prrc">Person Responsible for Regulatory Compliance (PRRC)</a></li>
    <li>have a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/quality-management-system-qms">Quality Management System (QMS)</a> in place</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="5-conduct-the-final-steps-before-placing-your-device-on-the-market">5. Conduct the final steps before placing your device on the market</h2>
  <p>Once you complete all the documents to demonstrate the device conformity and meet the manufacturer obligations under the MDR, you must file an EU Declaration of Conformity (DoC) which includes the information listed in Annex IV of the MDR. Don’t forget to include translations for all the countries in which the device will be made available. Once you have a DoC in hand, you can affix a CE mark to your device and register it for sale.</p>
  <h2 id="6-plan-ahead">6. Plan ahead</h2>
  <p>Once your device is on the market, it is your responsibility to have a <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/post-market-surveillance-pms">Post Market Surveillance (PMS) system</a> in place. This is another area that is sometimes overlooked by manufacturers of Class I devices. Once again, the skill is in striking a balance to ensure that systems are comprehensive enough to detect vital information without being too onerous and expensive.</p>
  <p>PMS should enable you to gather and assess safety and performance data to determine whether or not any actions are required. As a part of the PMS system, you must also:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>report all serious incidents and Field Safety Corrective Actions (FSCA) to the appropriate Competent Authorities and execute all relevant investigations</li>
    <li>take prompt action in case there is a reason to think that a device placed on the market or in service is not in compliance with the MDR</li>
  </ul>
  <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
  <p>The key message is — <b>don’t neglect the importance of a full MDR regulatory system for Class I devices</b>. Neglecting key areas such as Clinical Evaluation and Post-Market Surveillance will just lead to trouble down the line. Taking advice before putting systems in place can help ensure that they are sufficiently robust without exceeding what is necessary.</p>
  <p>If you have any doubt or would like to learn more, please <a href="/contact">contact our friendly team</a> today.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We outline a strategy for the regulatory compliance of Class I medical devices.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to achieve MDR Compliance for Class I medical devices</title><link href="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/literature-search-sota-review-and-clinical-evaluation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to achieve MDR Compliance for Class I medical devices" /><published>2022-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T17:43:25+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/literature-search-sota-review-and-clinical-evaluation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantrasystems.co.uk/articles/literature-search-sota-review-and-clinical-evaluation"><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">literature search &amp; review</a> is a vital component of the <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation">Clinical Evaluation</a> of medical devices. It is also challenging to perform and is an aspect of Clinical Evaluation that can be a source of confusion, difficulty and non-conformity.</p>
  <p>In this article, we help to demystify the process of systematic review of literature for Clinical Evaluation.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-meddev-271-rev-4">What is MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4?</h2>
  <p><a href="https://www.medical-device-regulation.eu/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2_7_1_rev4_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4</a> is one of a series of guidance documents published by the European Commission intended to assist <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/medical-device-manufacturers">medical device manufacturers</a> and <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/notified-bodies">Notified Bodies</a> in meeting medical device regulatory obligations. MedDev stands for MEDical DEVices documents. MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 is a detailed document which sets out comprehensive guidelines for medical device manufacturers and notified bodies for the conduct of Clinical Evaluation. MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 is a technical document which can be challenging to digest.</p>
  <p><strong>Appendix 5</strong> of the MedDev guideline sets out requirements for the identification and review of literature in the context of Clinical Evaluation. It is therefore central to performing a compliant literature review.</p>
  <h2 id="what-is-the-role-of-a-literature-review-in-medical-device-clinical-evaluation">What is the role of a literature review in medical device Clinical Evaluation?</h2>
  <p>The review of published literature is a critical component of medical device Clinical Evaluation. A literature review is performed to inform two major elements of a Clinical Evaluation:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>A review of the current knowledge/ the state of the art (SOTA) – this enables the identification of safety and performance benchmarks against which performance of the subject (and, if relevant, equivalent) device may be evaluated</li>
    <li>A review of literature relating to the subject (and equivalent) device.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>It is a requirement that literature searches are performed according to a documented protocol and that they include both favourable and unfavourable data. They must be representative and not be biased or selective; therefore, methods must be set out clearly for inclusion, exclusion, appraisal and analysis of sources.</p>
  <h2 id="what-guidance-is-offered-by-meddev-271-rev-4-appendix-5">What guidance is offered by MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 Appendix 5?</h2>
  <p>Appendix 5 of MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 provides a range of guidance for Clinical Evaluation literature searches &amp; reviews, including:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Offering general instructions on literature searching</li>
    <li>Outlining methods for constructing protocols for undertaking a literature review</li>
    <li>Defining the key elements of literature reviews that are required in order to deliver a compliant <a href="/eu-mdr-compliance/clinical-evaluation-report-cer">Clinical Evaluation Report</a>.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Understanding the literature search &amp; review process explained in <strong>Appendix 5</strong> can be made easier by dividing it into four stages:</p>
  <div class="general-wrap">
    <ul class="information row tile info-process">
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b2 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>Stage 1</span> Background</h3>
          <ol>
            <li>Search criteria</li>
            <li>Databases</li>
            <li>Inclusion &amp; exclusion criteria</li>
          </ol>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b3 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>Stage 2</span> Literature Screen</h3>
          <ol>
            <li>Analysing abstracts</li>
            <li>Full article</li>
          </ol>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b4 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>Stage 3</span> Appraisal &amp; Analysis</h3>
          <ol>
            <li>Selection &amp; Exclusion</li>
            <li>Critique &amp; Appraise</li>
            <li>Analysis</li>
          </ol>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li class="col col-3">
        <div class="content bg-b0 bg-dark">
          <h3><span>Stage 4</span> Literature Report</h3>
          <ol>
            <li>Benefits / Risk</li>
            <li>Conclusion</li>
            <li>Report</li>
          </ol>
        </div>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </div>
  <h2 id="stage-1-background-to-the-literature-search">Stage 1: Background to the literature search</h2>
  <p>Background to the literature search stage sets the scene for the substantive literature search, review, appraisal and report to follow. Performed properly, a rationale for performing the literature review should be clearly documented.</p>
  <p>The background to the literature search should include information such as:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Name of the device/model.</li>
    <li>Importance of literature review in the risk management process. The review should provide data on current therapies, diagnostic measures, and measures for the management of medical conditions for the targeted patient population. This will help in order to assess the acceptable benefits/risks.</li>
    <li>Outcomes of previous literature reviews and literature searches conducted by manufacturer.</li>
    <li>Identification of any equivalent or benchmark devices to be included in the evaluation, including the name and model of these devices.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Carefully formulated research question(s) should be set out to guide the selection of search terms. Selected search terms will then be subjected to an objective, non-biased, systematic search and review. The inputs required for this section are the device description and the expected device performance; these can be applied for the formation of relevant research questions. Methods or protocols adopted for the conduct of literature review should set out the search methodology, sources of data, selection &amp; exclusion criteria and appraisal/critique methodology.</p>
  <h2 id="stage-2-literature-screen">Stage 2: Literature Screen</h2>
  <p>The next step is to screen initial results for relevance to the research questions. This stage can be thought of as a ‘triage’ of sources, with the objective being to limit full appraisal to only those results that are pertinent.</p>
  <p>MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 requires the use of carefully formulated inclusion / exclusion criteria, augmented by an objective, non-biased, systematic screening and review process such as PICO (patient characteristics, type of intervention, control, and outcome queries), or PRISMA (The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses). Whatever method is used, it should align with the method specified in the search protocol (or review protocol) developed prior to commencing the review.</p>
  <p>In a practical sense, begin by reviewing the titles and abstracts – the full text is not required at this stage. Due to the number of results often found by search terms, screening needs to be efficient while maintaining appropriate scrutiny. It may be helpful to use exclusion codes to codify reasons for exclusions (which may include, for example, “unrelated topic” or “article not available in English” etc).</p>
  <p><b>Remember</b> — this stage is all about identifying relevant sources.</p>
  <h2 id="stage-3-appraisal--analysis">Stage 3: Appraisal &amp; Analysis</h2>
  <p>Before considering how to perform appraisal and analysis, it’s important to understand the difference between them:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><b>Appraisal</b> means to assess the quality of a source, methodological quality, scientific validity, reliability, relevance and weighting to the evaluation.</li>
    <li><b>Analysis</b> is the post-appraisal stage of evaluating what the results mean (or what they tell us). Appraisal and weighting should be considered during analysis.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>According to MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4, an appraisal plan should form part of the search protocol. It is advisable to create an appraisal framework covering multiple domains (such as relevance, clinical significance, study type, etc) and it can be useful to assign a code to each appraisal element. As part of appraisal, a score can be applied against each appraisal domain, forming a structured and codified appraisal summary of each source and the ‘body’ of sources as a whole.</p>
  <p>Weighting is a key concept in appraisal that’s worth considering independently. The weighting of a source indicates how much importance should be placed on the results of that source when compared to others. A high weighting indicates that the results should be deemed more relevant to the evaluation than data from a lower weighting source.</p>
  <p>Following appraisal, the next stage is to analyse the data. The analysis will depend on the reason for conducting the literature review; in a clinical evaluation, the appraisal may consider (for example):</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Does the data demonstrate that the device is suitable for its intended purpose?</li>
    <li>Does the data demonstrate compliance with the relevant General Safety and Performance Requirements (GSPRs)?</li>
  </ol>
  <p>During appraisal, ensure that an objective approach is taken and that both favourable and unfavourable data is treated equally.</p>
  <h2 id="stage-4-literature-review-report">Stage 4: Literature Review Report</h2>
  <p>The fourth and final stage of the literature analysis and review process is preparing a literature review report. While writing the report, especially if performed in the context of a clinical evaluation, it is important to identify quantifiable safety and performance parameters, whether in relation to the subject device or comparable alternatives.</p>
  <p>Ensure the report includes enough information for a reviewer to understand how the search was conducted and what appraisal and analysis criteria were used. Present a summary of each source (outlining a rationale for the appraisal and weighting) in the body of the document and outline the analysis towards the end.</p>
  <h2 id="the-bottom-line">The bottom line</h2>
  <p>Performing a systematic literature review to the required standard is not easy. While the framework in Appendix 5 of MedDev 2.7/1 rev 4 is not without its limitations, it is useful as a starting point and in ensuring that the review has an appropriate structure without major omissions.</p>
  <p>At Mantra Systems, our team of medical experts are on hand to support your <a href="/medical-device-regulatory-consulting-services/literature-search-protocol-sota-review">literature search &amp; review</a> needs. If you need any information or advice, please <a href="/contact">contact us</a> for a free discussion.</p>
  <p><strong>Note:</strong> A shortened version of this article was previously published on 20th October, 2021.</p>
  ]]></content><author><name>sandra-gopinath</name></author><category term="Strategy" /><category term="MDR" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We outline a strategy for the regulatory compliance of Class I medical devices.]]></summary></entry></feed>